<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<metadata><Source>http://www.nbii.gov/metadata/mdata/EPA/epa_d_enivdatareg.sgml</Source>
<idinfo>
<citation>
<citeinfo>
<origin>The U.S. Environmental Protection Agency</origin>
<pubdate>2002</pubdate>
<title>The Environmental Data Registry</title>
<geoform>maps data</geoform>
<pubinfo>
<pubplace>Washington, D.C.</pubplace>
<publish>The Environmental Protection Agency</publish>
</pubinfo>
<onlink>http://www.epa.gov/edr/</onlink>
</citeinfo>
</citation>
<descript>
<abstract>
The Environmental Data Registry (EDR) is a comprehensive,
authoritative source of reference information about the definition, source,
and uses of environmental data. The EDR catalogs the Environmental
Protection Agency's (EPA) major data collections and helps locate
environmental information of interest.  As the major tool supporting the
Agency's data standards program, the EDR records and disseminates
information about Agency data standards and the standard-setting process.
The vision for EPA's data standards program is to promote the efficient
sharing of environmental information among EPA, states, tribes, and other
parties through the cooperative development of data standards. The EDR
serves this program in two important ways.  First, as a reference tool, the EDR
catalogs EPA's information resources and provides information for
interpreting the environmental data. The EDR does not contain the
environmental data itself, but rather	information that describes the data to make it more meaningful.  The
Environmental Data Registry (EDR) is a comprehensive, authoritative
reference for information about the definition, source, and uses of
environmental data. It does not contain data, rather offers tools to help
use environmental data. XML tag search allows the user to find XML tags for
the data elements included in EPA data standards. Code Sets contain
permissible values, value meaning names, and value meaning definitions that
can be used in applications. The Code Sets  have values associated with EPA
Data Standards, with national/international standards, or contain lists of
values commonly used by EPA programs. The EDR Compare tool allows you to
search for and compare data elements from various sources (e.g., data
standards).  The information resource search allows the user to find
application system metadata.
</abstract>
<purpose>
The purpose of the Environmental Data Registry is to provide a
comprehensive reference for information about the definition,  source, and
uses of environmental data.
</purpose>
<supplinf>Information listed here was obtained from http://www.epa.gov/edr/.  (previous geoform was 'Database')</supplinf>
</descript>
<timeperd>
<timeinfo>
<sngdate>
<caldate>2002</caldate>
</sngdate>
</timeinfo>
<current>publication date</current>
</timeperd>
<status>
<progress>In Work</progress>
<update>Continually</update>
</status>
<keywords>
<theme>
<themekt>none</themekt>
<themekey>standard update</themekey>
<themekey>XML tags</themekey>
<themekey>code sets</themekey>
<themekey>compare tool</themekey>
<themekey>information resource search</themekey>
<themekey>data standard conformance</themekey>
<themekey>data harmonization</themekey>
</theme>
</keywords>
<accconst>
No access constraints.  The EDR is available to anyone
interested in environmental information, including the public,
environmental decision makers, industry, researchers, regulated entities,
state and local environmental agencies, regulation writers, and computer
system developers and managers.
</accconst>
<useconst>none</useconst>
<ptcontac>
<cntinfo>
<cntperp>
<cntper>Michael Pendleton</cntper>
<cntorg>
United States Environmental Protection Agency,
Office of Environmental Information
</cntorg>
</cntperp>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
<address>1200 Pennsylvania Avenue, NW, Mail Code 2822-T</address>
<city>Washington</city>
<state>D.C.</state>
<postal>20460</postal>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>(202) 566-1658</cntvoice>
<cntfax>(202) 566-1639</cntfax>
<cntemail>pendleton.michael@epa.gov</cntemail>
</cntinfo>
</ptcontac>
</idinfo>
<dataqual>
<logic>not applicable</logic>
<complete>The EDR is a comprehensive, authoritative source of reference information.</complete>
<lineage>
<method>
<methtype>database</methtype>
<methdesc>
The EDR serves to document the diversity of
data representations across information systems through central storage of
application metadata. This information can be used to support initiatives
to identify duplication of data, streamline information collection, and
achieve information consistency and sharing across the programs. Second, as
the repository for standard data elements, the EDR fosters the use of
consistently defined and formatted data elements and sets of data values.
These standard data elements and values can be downloaded for use in
application system design and reengineering. This capability supports
initiatives to achieve enterprise information consistency through standard
information representation. The data can also be accessed using the
Environmental Data Registry (EDR) Portal, a search engine that enables
users to search metadata registry content using a URL with integrated
search capabilities. It enables users to search and seamlessly navigate to
detail pages meeting the search criteria. An EDR Portal Substance Search
has been developed so system developers can build URLs that automatically
query various substance data and display the appropriate detail information
from three EPA applications: Substance Registry System (SRS), Chemical
Registry System (CRS), and the Biology Registry System (BioRS).
</methdesc>
</method>
<procstep>
<procdesc>
The EDR has been redesigned to be part of a single
metadata registry, a reference to EPA information resources. The new system
design integrates several collections of EPA metadata, including data
elements, chemical identification information, biological taxonomy
information, and terms with definitions. The integrated information is
accessed by several EPA applications including the Environmental Data
Registry (EDR), the Substance Registry System (SRS), the Chemical Registry
System (CRS), the Biology Registry System (BioRS), and the Terminology
Reference System (TRS). This integration supports Agency information integration
activities and helps make Agency metadata information more meaningful.
</procdesc>
<procdate>Unknown</procdate>
</procstep>
</lineage>
</dataqual>
<eainfo>
<overview>
<eaover>Entity - Enviromental Information; Attributes - data standards, newsletter, compare tool, XML, code set, search tool, registration, and subscription.</eaover>
<eadetcit>none</eadetcit>
</overview>
</eainfo>
<distinfo>
<distrib>
<cntinfo>
<cntperp>
<cntper>Michael Pendleton</cntper>
<cntorg>
United States Environmental Protection Agency,
Office of Environmental Information
</cntorg>
</cntperp>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
<address>1200 Pennsylvania Avenue, NW, Mail Code 2822-T</address>
<city>Washington</city>
<state>D.C.</state>
<postal>20460</postal>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>(202) 566-1658</cntvoice>
<cntfax>(202) 566-1639</cntfax>
<cntemail>pendleton.michael@epa.gov</cntemail>
</cntinfo>
</distrib>
<distliab>
The EDR contains metadata from EPA and stakeholder
sources. All information in the EDR is displayed as received from the
source. Although the Office of Environmental Information (OEI) accepts no
responsibility for the data's quality, it provides this information to
document the depth and breadth of Agency-related information.  The EDR has
no statutory or regulatory standing. While EPA applied its best efforts to
include complete and accurate information in the EDR, EPA cannot be held
responsible for errors or omissions and is not liable for any direct,
indirect, or consequential damages resulting from using this information.
Reliance on the information contained in these systems by any party cannot
be used as a defense in any administrative or judicial proceeding. In such
proceedings, the specific language of the relevant regulation or statute is
binding. GEMET Copyright
The EDR contains the European Environment Agency (EEA), European Topic
Centre on Catalogue of Data Sources (ETC/CDS), General Multilingual
Environmental Thesaurus (GEMET). The EEA owns the copyright of GEMET.
Although GEMET is owned by the EEA, the Agency distributes it free to interested
users. The ETC/CDS maintains the EEA master file from which copies are produced.
The EEA has no intention of preventing other users from changing it. For example,
new users are free to further develop the master copy. However, unless a contractual agreement
exists between the EEA and the current master copyholder, the latter cannot
claim to be the master file keeper or maintainer. The EEA regards the name
GEMET as its own "registered trademark."
</distliab>
<stdorder>
<digform>
<digtinfo>
<formname>various</formname>
</digtinfo>
<digtopt>
<onlinopt>
<computer>
<networka>
<networkr>http://www.epa.gov/edr/</networkr>
</networka>
</computer>
</onlinopt>
</digtopt>
</digform>
<fees>None, if available online.</fees>
</stdorder>
</distinfo>
<metainfo>
<metd>20020827</metd>
<metfrd>20030827</metfrd>
<metc>
<cntinfo>
<cntperp>
<cntper>Cheryl Solomon</cntper>
<cntorg>Science Systems and Applications, Inc.</cntorg>
</cntperp>
<cntpos>Metadata specialist</cntpos>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
<address>10210 Greenbelt Road, Suite 500</address>
<city>Lanham</city>
<state>Maryland</state>
<postal>20706</postal>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>301 867-2080</cntvoice>
<cntfax>301-867-2149.</cntfax>
<cntemail>solomon@gcmd.nasa.gov</cntemail>
</cntinfo>
</metc>
<metstdn>FGDC Biological Data Profile of the Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
<metstdv>FGDC-STD-001.1-1999</metstdv>
<metac>none</metac>
<metuc>none</metuc>
</metainfo>
<mercury><begdate>20020101</begdate><enddate>20021231</enddate><htmlurl>http://mercury.ornl.gov/metadata/nbii/html/nbii/www.nbii.gov_metadata_mdata_EPA_epa_d_enivdatareg.html</htmlurl><LTER-Site>nbii</LTER-Site></mercury></metadata>
