<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<metadata><Source>http://www.nbii.gov/metadata/mdata/CBI/usgs_brd_cbi_d_badlfield.sgml</Source>
<idinfo>
<citation>
<citeinfo>
<origin>
Remote Sensing and GIS Group, Technical Service
Center, US Bureau of Reclamation, Mail Code
D-8260, POB 25007, Denver CO 80225
</origin>
<pubdate>1999</pubdate>
<title>Badlands National Park Field Data</title>
<geoform>maps data</geoform>
<serinfo>
<sername>USGS-NPS Vegetation Mapping Program</sername>
<issue>Badlands National Park</issue>
</serinfo>
<pubinfo>
<pubplace>Denver, CO</pubplace>
<publish>USGS-BRD</publish>
</pubinfo>
<othercit>Created under contract to the USGS-BRD-CBI</othercit>
<onlink>http://biology.usgs.gov/npsveg/badl/fielddata.html</onlink>
</citeinfo>
</citation>
<descript>
<abstract>
This metadata is for the field data associated with
the vegetation land cover and land use geospatial
database for Badlands National Park and
surrounding areas.  The project is authorized as
part of the USGS/NPS Vegetation Mapping Program
(http://biology.usgs.gov/npsveg). The program is
being administered by the Biological Resources
Division (BRD) of the United States Geological
Survey (USGS).  The USGS/BRD is responsible for
overall management and oversight of all ongoing
mapping efforts.  This mapping effort was
performed by the US Bureau of Reclamation's (USBR)
Remote Sensing and GIS Group, Technical Service
Center, Denver, CO. The vegetation mapping program
is part of a larger Inventory and Monitoring (I&amp;M)
program started by the National Park Service (NPS)
Their website is :http://www1.nature.nps.gov/im/
</abstract>
<purpose>
The purposes of the mapping effort are varied and
include the following: Provides support for NPS
Resources Management; Promotes vegetation-related
research for both NPS and USGS/BRD; Provides
support for NPS Planning and Compliance; Adds to
the information base for NPS Interpretation; and
Assists in NPS Operations.  The NPS  I&amp;M goals
are, among others, to map the vegetation of all
national parks and monuments and provide a
baseline inventory of vegetation.
</purpose>
<supplinf>(previous geoform was 'database')</supplinf>
</descript>
<timeperd>
<timeinfo>
<rngdates>
<begdate>199708</begdate>
<enddate>199712</enddate>
</rngdates>
</timeinfo>
<current>
Time frame given in report as "Field surveys began in
the second week of August 1997 ... " and also described
as "Summer 1997".  Likely extended past August, but the
duration is not known at this time.
</current>
</timeperd>
<status>
<progress>Complete</progress>
<update>None Planned</update>
</status>
<spdom>
<bounding>
<westbc>-102.943</westbc>
<eastbc>-101.817</eastbc>
<northbc>44</northbc>
<southbc>43.432</southbc>
</bounding>
<descgeog>
Badlands National Park, SD including approx 5 mile
buffer around park which includes private lands,
portions of Buffalo Gap National Grassland, and
Pine Ridge Indian Reservation.
</descgeog>
</spdom>
<keywords>
<theme>
<themekt>None</themekt>
<themekey>Land cover</themekey>
<themekey>Land use</themekey>
<themekey>Vegetation</themekey>
<themekey>National Park Service</themekey>
</theme>
<place>
<placekt>None</placekt>
<placekey>South Dakota</placekey>
<placekey>Badlands National Park</placekey>
<placekey>Pine Ridge Indian Reservation</placekey>
<placekey>Red Shirt</placekey>
<placekey>Scenic</placekey>
<placekey>Cheyenne River</placekey>
<placekey>Buffalo Gap National Grassland</placekey>
<placekey>Badlands Wilderness Area</placekey>
<placekey>White River</placekey>
<placekey>Interior</placekey>
</place>
</keywords>
<accconst>None</accconst>
<useconst>
Acknowledgment of the USGS/BRD, National Park Service,
and the USBR/RSGIS Group would be appreciated in
products derived from these data.  Any person using
the information presented here should fully understand
the data collection and compilation procedures, as
described in the metadata, before beginning
analysis.  The burden for determining fitness for
use lies entirely with the user
</useconst>
<ptcontac>
<cntinfo>
<cntperp>
<cntper>USGS-NPS Vegetation Mapping Program Coordinator</cntper>
<cntorg>Center for Biological Informatics, USGS-BRD</cntorg>
</cntperp>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>Mailing Address</addrtype>
<address>PO Box 25046, MS-302</address>
<city>Denver</city>
<state>Colorado</state>
<postal>80225</postal>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>(303) 202-4220</cntvoice>
<cntfax>303-202-4229</cntfax>
<cntfax>303-202-4219 (org)</cntfax>
<cntemail>gs-b-npsveg@usgs.gov</cntemail>
</cntinfo>
</ptcontac>
<browse>
<browsen>http://biology.usgs.gov/npsveg/badl/images/badlplot.jpg</browsen>
<browsed>179 Kbyte</browsed>
<browset>JPEG</browset>
</browse>
<datacred>
Dan Cogan, Doug Crawford, Trudy Meyer, Jean
Pennell &amp; Jim Von Loh with RSGIS Group of USBR;
Jim Drake of TNC; Bruce Bessken and Glenn Plumb of
Badlands NP, NPS
</datacred>
<native>Microsoft Access mdb</native>
<tool>
<tooldesc>The Nature Conservancy's PLOTS database</tooldesc>
<toolacc>
<onlink>http://biology.usgs.gov/npsveg/tools/plotsdatabase.html</onlink>
<toolinst>None</toolinst>
</toolacc>
</tool>
<taxonomy>
<keywtax>
<taxonkt>None</taxonkt>
<taxonkey>Plants</taxonkey>
<taxonkey>Vegetation</taxonkey>
<taxonkey>National Vegetation Classification System</taxonkey>
</keywtax>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Kingdom</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Plantae</taxonrv>
<common>Plant</common>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Division-Phylum</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Tracheophyta</taxonrv>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Class</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Angiospermai</taxonrv>
</taxoncl>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Class</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Gymnospermae</taxonrv>
</taxoncl>
</taxoncl>
</taxoncl>
</taxonomy>
</idinfo>
<dataqual>
<logic>Unknown</logic>
<complete>
Investigators chose representative stands of plant
communities to collect 130 data plots.  Plots were
subjectively placed in vegetation that was representative
of an area, relatively homogeneous, and covered more than
1/2 hectare (the minimum mapping unit).  Thus, ecotones
and small patches of vegetation were avoided.  Forest and
woodland communities were sampled with 20 x 20-meter plots
while shrubland and herbaceous communities were sampled with
10 x 10-meter plots.  Collected data included habitat characteristics
(e.g. slope, aspect, elevation, and soil characteristics), vegetation
composition and structure, and other site features such as wildlife
or human disturbance.  At least three plots were sampled for each
plant community found in the study area, as long as three stands
were available.  For a few uncommon plant communities, only one
or two plots were sampled.  In order to collect large river riparian
data, investigators selected a few sample sites outside, but near
Park boundaries.  All sampled data were entered into TNC's "PLOTS"
database program.
</complete>
<posacc>
<horizpa>
<horizpar>
The UTM coordinates
and elevation of all plots were logged using a hand-held Precision
Lightweight Global Positioning  System (GPS) Receiver (PLGR) unit.
</horizpar>
</horizpa>
</posacc>
<lineage>
<procstep>
<procdesc>
See Methodology Description
In addition, the procedure for classifying vegetation followed
guidelines set forth in the Vegetation Classification Standard
(FGDC 1996) which was developed from the Standardized National
Vegetation Classification System (NVCS) (TNC 1994).  This national
system contains seven classification levels with the two finest (lowest)
being the alliance and association (community) levels.  Associations
are separated from alliances through the use of floristic composition
and are named by the most dominant and/or indicator species.  If two
or more dominant species occur in the same stratum a dash symbol is
used.  If the species occur in different strata then a slash is used.
Parentheses are used in instances when the diagnostic species are not
consistently present in the vegetation unit.
Classification for the Badlands National Park study area involved placing
all observation point data and plot data into groups based on vegetation
structure and composition.  From here, extensive floristic knowledge of the
field team allowed most of the sampled community types to be qualitatively
evaluated and subjectively assigned to an existing NVCS class.  In a few
instances, new NVCS classes were discerned and prepared from evaluations
of the floristic data.  Additional analyses were performed using the plot data
combined with other similar data to provide a better regional perspective on
vegetation types.  TNC quantitatively analyzed the plot data using ordination
techniques (Detrended Correspondence Analysis "CDA" and Non-Metric
Multidimensional Scales "NMS"), a clustering algorithm, Unweighted Pair-Group
Method Using Arithmetic Means (UPGMA), and Two-Way Indicator Species
Analysis (TWINSPAN).  Since, in a number of cases, there were only a few
sample plots per vegetation type, the above analyses could not be solely relied
upon for classification.  However, the results of the numerical analyses were
compared to the subjective classification in order to detect any discrepancies
between the two.  All analyses were completed using PC-ORD.
A dichotomous vegetation key for Badlands National Park was prepared
following the 1997 field season.  The key was tested during the Accuracy
Assessment process and reviewed by TNC, resulting in some modifications.
This dichotomous key leading to association descriptions provided guidance
to researchers in the field during the accuracy assessment.
</procdesc>
<procdate>1997 or 1998 following the 1997 field season.</procdate>
</procstep>
<method>
<methtype>Field</methtype>
<methodid>
<methkt>None</methkt>
<methkey>Field Sample</methkey>
<methkey>GPS</methkey>
<methkey>Field Plot</methkey>
<methkey>releve methodology</methkey>
<methkey>Daubenmire classification</methkey>
</methodid>
<methdesc>
Field surveys began in the second week of August 1997 after aerial
photography was acquired.
Data collection included both plot and observation points, which allowed
investigators to record typical vegetation types and  also to record variation
within plant communities across larger areas.  Observation points were used
to become quickly familiar with community characteristics, ranges of variation,
and to field check the preliminary classification.  Observation point sampling
included UTM X-Y coordinates, dominate species cover data, and brief
environmental characteristics.  Limitations of observation point data included
no measurement or delineation of the sampling area and cover was only
estimated for the common species in each stratum.  Data from 137 observation
points were collected during the field survey.  Points were recorded mainly
within gradsects, and were chosen to sample the range of habitat and
vegetation variability observed on aerial photography, on preliminary maps,
and in the field.
Investigators chose representative stands of plant communities to collect 130
data plots.  Plot sample sites were identified in the field within gradsects using
standard releve methodology (Mueller-Dombois 1974).  Plots were subjectively placed
in vegetation that was representative of an area, relatively homogeneous,
and covered more than 1/2 hectare (the minimum mapping unit).  Thus, ecotones
and small patches of vegetation were avoided.  Forest and woodland communities
were sampled with 20 x 20-meter plots while shrubland and herbaceous
communities were sampled with 10 x 10-meter plots.  Collected data included
habitat characteristics (e.g. slope, aspect, elevation, and soil characteristics),
vegetation composition and structure, and other site features such as wildlife or
human disturbance.  At least three plots were sampled for each plant community
found in the study area, as long as three stands were available.  For a few
uncommon plant communities, only one or two plots were sampled.  In order to
collect large river riparian data, investigators selected a few sample sites outside,
but near Park boundaries.  All sampled data were entered into TNC's "PLOTS"
database program.
To characterize vegetation structure, all species found within a plot were noted
and foliar cover for each species by strata was estimated using a modified
Daubenmire (1959) classification.  Since cover was estimated independently for
both species and strata, total coverage for some of the plots was greater than 100%.
In forests and woodlands, dbh (diameter at breast height) was measured for all trees
greater than 10-cm dbh.  Various environmental data were also collected for each
plot to characterize the abiotic conditions under which the sampled vegetation
occurred.  The UTM coordinates and elevation of all plots were logged using a
hand-held Precision Lightweight Global Positioning System (GPS) Receiver (PLGR)
unit.  35 mm slides were taken for each plot and scanned representatives are
included in the report.
</methdesc>
<methcite>
<citeinfo>
<origin>D. Mueller-Dombois and H. Ellenberg</origin>
<pubdate>1974</pubdate>
<title>Aims and Methods of Vegetation Ecology</title>
<geoform>Book</geoform>
<pubinfo>
<pubplace>New York</pubplace>
<publish>Wiley</publish>
</pubinfo>
</citeinfo>
</methcite>
<methcite>
<citeinfo>
<origin>R. Daubenmire</origin>
<pubdate>1959</pubdate>
<title>A canopy-coverage method of vegetational analysis</title>
<geoform>Journal Article</geoform>
<serinfo>
<sername>Northwest Science</sername>
<issue>23: 69-82</issue>
</serinfo>
</citeinfo>
</methcite>
</method>
</lineage>
</dataqual>
<spdoinfo>
<direct>Point</direct>
</spdoinfo>
<spref>
<horizsys>
<planar>
<gridsys>
<gridsysn>Universal Transverse Mercator</gridsysn>
<utm>
<utmzone>13</utmzone>
<transmer>
<longcm>-105</longcm>
<latprjo>0</latprjo>
<feast>500000</feast>
<fnorth>0</fnorth>
<sfctrmer>.9996</sfctrmer>
</transmer>
</utm>
</gridsys>
<planci>
<plance>coordinate pair</plance>
<coordrep>
<absres>1</absres>
<ordres>1</ordres>
</coordrep>
<plandu>meters</plandu>
</planci>
</planar>
<geodetic>
<horizdn>North American Datum of 1983</horizdn>
<ellips>Geodedic Reference System 80</ellips>
<semiaxis>6378137</semiaxis>
<denflat>298.257</denflat>
</geodetic>
</horizsys>
</spref>
<eainfo>
<overview>
<eaover>
DEFINITIONS of and/or INSTRUCTIONS for populating Data fields
This section lists all of the data fields that you will encounter in the Plots Database System.
Definitions for most of the data fields are provided and/or instructions to: a) locate the
data field; and b) populate the data field.
1.	AA Obs Code
This field is a unique identifier for an AA Observation record.  It is generated by the Plots
Database when you create a new record.  The AA Obs Code is assembled from two parts:
the Location Code and a sequential counter field (AA Code Counter) that is increased
automatically each time a Plot is entered for that Location.
Examples:
SHEN.1 	The first AA Observation record entered for Shenandoah NP
TUZI.8	The eighth AA Observation record entered for Tuzigoot NM
The AA Code Counter can be reset to any number you would like when the system
creates the AA Obs Code for a new AA Observation record.  As you select the Location for
your new AA Observation record, the system will suggest a new AA Obs Code based on the
current setting of the counter.  You can accept this AA Obs Code, or you can change the
counter at this point. Changing the counter setting will cause the counter to start numbering
from the new setting.  This may be desirable if you would like to coordinate data entry with
another installation, and want to avoid using duplicate AA Obs Codes.  See the How to Get
Started section: Entering Data from field forms: Creating a new plot record for more detailed
instructions.  Once you finalize the AA Obs Code, you can not change it directly.  If you
need to change the AA Obs Code of your record, refer to the Troubleshooting/Helpful
Hints section: Editing Problems.
The AA Obs Code is viewed as read-only data in the Identifiers section of the AA
Observation form.
2.	Air Photo Number
The identifying number or code of the aerial photo on which the plot appears.
The Air Photo Number can be edited in the Identifiers 1 section of the Plots form, and in
the Identifiers section of the AA Observation form.
3.	Animal Use Evidence
Comment on any evidence of use of the plot/polygon by non-domestic animals (i.e., tracks,
scat, gopher or prairie dog mounds, etc.).  Notes on domestic animals should be made in
the field Disturbance Comments.
Animal Use Evidence can be edited in the Misc Comments section of the Plots form.
4.	Aspect
Enter slope aspect; use a compass (be sure to correct for the magnetic declination).
Aspect can be edited in the Environment 1 section of the Plots and AA Observation forms.
Use the pull-down list to select an appropriate value.
Values:
FLAT
VARIABLE
N				338-22&amp;Acirc;°
NE				23-67&amp;Acirc;°
E				68-112&amp;Acirc;°
SE				113-157&amp;Acirc;°
S				158-202&amp;Acirc;°
SW				203-247&amp;Acirc;°
W				248-292&amp;Acirc;°
NW				293-337&amp;Acirc;°
5.	Classified Community Name
Once the data are analyzed and the community has been classified, enter the name of the
community from the National Vegetation Classification System.
The Classified Community Name can be edited in the Identifiers section of the AA
Observation form and the Identifiers 1 section of the Plots form.
6.	Common Name
The common name for an individual species record within the NRCS PLANTS Database.
The Common Name can be edited by clicking the 'PLANTS Database Maintenance' button
from the "Main Menu" window.  Click on one of the 'Edit/View Data' buttons.  Edit
according to the instructions in the Functions section: Editing Data: Undo/Edit functions.
NOTE: if you change the contents of the PLANTS Database in any way you can not
represent it to others as the NRCS PLANTS Database.  Please read the PLANTS copyright
notice (click the 'Important Copyright Information' button in the "Main Menu" window).
7.	Corrected Lat
Enter the post-processing correction for the latitude.
Corrected Lat can be edited in the Environment 1 section of the Plots and AA Observation
forms after you click the 'Lat/Long' button.
8.	Corrected Long
Enter the post-processing correction for the longitude.
Corrected Long can be edited in the Environment 1 section of the Plots and AA Observation
forms after you click the 'Lat/Long' button.
9.	Corrected X
X coordinate of Universal Transverse Mercator projection after post-processing correction.
To be filled in at the office, not in the field.
The Corrected X can be edited in the Environment 1 section of the Plots and AA Observation
forms after you click the 'UTM' button.
10.	Corrected Y
Y coordinate of Universal Transverse Mercator projection after post-processing correction.
To be filled in at the office, not in the field.
The Corrected X can be edited in the Environment 1 section of the Plots and AA Observation
forms after you click the 'UTM' button.
11.	Cowardin System
Cowardin System can be edited in the Environment 1 section of the Plots and AA Observation
forms.  Use the pull-down list to enter the appropriate term:  If the system is a wetland, enter the
name of the USFWS system which best describes it's hydrology and landform.  Indicate
"upland" if the system is not a wetland.
Values:
UPLAND - Not a wetland according to the Cowardin System.
ESTUARINE  - Deepwater tidal habitats and adjacent tidal wetlands that are usually semienclosed
by land but have open, partly obstructed, or sporadic access to the open ocean, and in which
ocean water is at least occasionally diluted by freshwater runoff from the land.  The salinity is
above 0.5 parts per thousand, and may be periodically increased above that of the open ocean
by evaporation.  Along some low energy coastlines there is appreciable dilution of sea water.
Offshore areas with typical estuarine plants and animals, such as red mangroves and eastern
oysters are also included in the Estuarine System.  The presence of halophytic plants may be
used to differentiate Estuarine from other freshwater systems if there is insufficient data on
salinity.
PALUSTRINE - Nontidal wetlands dominated by trees, shrubs, persistent emergents, emergent
mosses or lichens, and all such wetlands that occur in tidal areas where salinity due to
ocean derived salts is below 0.5 parts per thousand.  It also includes wetlands lacking
such vegetation, but with all of the following four characteristics: (1) area less than 8 ha
(20 acres); (2) active waveformed or bedrock shoreline features lacking; (3) water depth in
the deepest part of basin less than 2m at low water; and (salinity due to ocean derived salts
less than 0.5 parts per thousand.
RIVERINE - Includes all wetlands and deepwater habitats contained within a channel, with two
exceptions: (1) wetland dominated by trees, shrubs, persistent emergents, emergent mosses,
or lichens, and (2) habitats with water containing ocean derived salts in excess of 0.5 parts
per thousand.  A channel is "an open conduit either naturally or artificially created which
periodically or continuously contains moving water, or which forms a connecting link
between two bodies of standing water".
LACUSTRINE - Includes wetlands and deepwater habitats with all of the following characteristics:
(1) situated in a topographic depression or a dammed river channel; (2) lacking trees, shrubs,
persistent emergents, emergent mosses or lichens with greater than 30% areal coverage; and
(3) total area exceeds 8 ha (20 acres).  Similar wetland and deepwater habitats totaling less
than 8 ha are also included in the Lacustrine System if an active waveformed or bedrock
shoreline feature makes up all or part of the boundary, or if the water depth in the deepest
part of the basin exceeds 2 m (6.6 feet) at low water.  Lacustrine waters may be tidal or
nontidal, but ocean derived salinity is always less than 0.5 parts per thousand.
12.	DBH
For forests and woodlands, list for each tree species the DBH of all trees above 10 cm
diameter.  Separate the measurements with a comma and note whether in cm or inches.
The DBH field can be edited by clicking the 'View/Edit Species List' button in the
Identifiers 1 section of the Plots form, then scrolling right by clicking on the right arrow
button in the lower right section of one of the subwindows.
The DBH field is not found in the AA-Species form.
13.	Diagnostic
This is to be checked if the species is known to be diagnostic of the vegetation type.
The Diagnostic field can be edited by clicking the 'View/Edit Species List' button in the
Identifiers section of AA Observation or the Identifiers 1 section of the Plots form, then
scrolling right by clicking on the right arrow button in the lower right section of one of
the subwindows.
Click on the data square labeled Diagnostic to produce an 'x' if it is diagnostic.  Click
the data square again to remove the 'x'.
14.	Disturbance Comments
Comment on any evidence of natural or anthropogenic disturbance and specify the
source.
Disturbance Comments can be edited through the Misc Comments section of the Plots
and AA Observation forms.
15.	Elevation
Elevation of the plot.  Using the associated check-offs/data squares, specify whether
feet or meters (this will depend on the units used on the topographic map/DEM's being
used).
Elevation can be edited through the Environment 1 section of the Plots and AA
Observation forms.  Click on a data square to produce an 'x' to indicate that your
measurement is in 'm' or 'ft'.
16.	Environmental Comments
Enter any additional noteworthy comments on the environmental setting.
Environmental Comments can be edited in the Environment 2 section of the Plots and
AA Observation forms.
17.	Family
The family name for an individual species record within the NRCS PLANTS Database.
The plant Family can be edited by clicking the 'PLANTS Database Maintenance' button
from the "Main Menu" window.  Click on one of the 'Edit/View Data' buttons.  Edit
according to the instructions in the Functions section: Editing Data: Undo/Edit functions.
NOTE: if you change the contents of the PLANTS Database in any way you can not
represent it to others as the NRCS PLANTS Database.  Please read the PLANTS
copyright notice (click the 'Important Copyright Information' button in the "Main
Menu" window).
18.	Field Lat
If latitude and longitude were used to measure geographic position, enter the latitude
value read from the GPS at the time of sampling.
To edit Field Lat click on the 'Lat/Long' button of the Environment 1 section of the
Plots or AA Observation forms.
19.	Field Long
If latitude and longitude were used to measure geographic position, enter the longitude
value read from the GPS at the time of sampling.
To edit Field Long click on the 'Lat/Long' button of the Environment 1 section of the
Plots or AA Observation forms.
20.	Field X
X coordinate of Universal Transverse Mercator projection read from the GPS at the
time of sampling.
To edit Field X click the 'UTM' button of the Environment 1 section of the Plots or
AA Observation forms.
21.	Field Y
Y coordinate of Universal Transverse Mercator projection read from the GPS at
the time of sampling.
To edit Field Y click the 'UTM' button of the Environment 1 section of the Plots
or AA Observation forms.
22.	Frame Number
If photos have been taken at the plot, enter the film frame number to help identify
the photos after film processing.
Edit Frame Number in the Identifiers 2 section of the Plots form.  This data field is
not found in the AA Observation form.
23.	GPS File
Enter the filename assigned to the plot when collecting GPS information.  It should
be in the form XXMMDDHH ( unique plot identifier*, month, day, hour, i.e.
23071313 - plot 23 collected on July 13 at 1pm).
* Depending on your own data and situation, the counter portion of the Plot Code
might serve as a convenient identifier.
Edit GPS File by clicking the 'UTM' or 'Lat/Long' buttons in the Environment 1
section of the Plots and AA Observation forms.
24.	GPS Techniques
Indicate the projection and GPS datum, plus any noteworthy comments regarding
equipment and/or techniques used to process the GPS data.
Edit GPS Techniques by clicking the 'UTM' or 'Lat/Long' buttons in the Environment
1 section of the Plots and AA Observation forms.
25.	Hydrologic Regime
Assess the hydrologic regime of the plot using the descriptions that follow of
hydrological modifiers used to identify wetland units at the formation level (adapted
from Cowardin et al. 1979).  Edit Hydrologic Regime in the Environment 1 section of the
Plots and AA Observation forms.  Select the appropriate term from the pull-down list.
SEMIPERMANENTLY FLOODED - Surface water persists throughout growing season in
most years except during periods of drought.  Land surface is normally saturated
when water level drops below soil surface.  Includes Cowardin's Intermittently
Exposed and Semipermanently Flooded modifiers.
SEASONALLY FLOODED - Surface water is present for extended periods during the growing
season, but is absent by the end of the growing season in most years.  The water table
after flooding ceases is very variable, extending from saturated to a water table well
below the ground surface.  Includes Cowardin's Seasonal, Seasonal-Saturated, and
Seasonal-Well Drained modifiers.
SATURATED -  Surface water is seldom present, but substrate is saturated to surface for
extended periods during the growing season.  Equivalent to Cowardin's Saturated modifier.
TEMPORARILY FLOODED - Surface water present for brief periods during growing season,
but water table usually lies well below soil surface.  Often characterizes flood-plain
wetlands.  Equivalent to Cowardin's Temporary modifier.
INTERMITTENTLY FLOODED - Substrate is usually exposed, but surface water can be present
for variable periods without detectable seasonal periodicity.  Inundation is not predictable
to a given season and is dependent upon highly localized rain storms.  This modifier was
developed for use in the arid West for water regimes of Playa lakes, intermittent streams,
and dry washes but can be used in other parts of the U.S. where appropriate.  This
modifier can be applied to both wetland and non-wetland situations.  Equivalent to
Cowardin's Intermittently Flooded modifier.
PERMANENTLY FLOODED - Water covers the land surface at all times of the year in all years.
Equivalent to Cowardin's "permanently flooded".
PERMANENTLY FLOODED TIDAL - Salt water covers the land surface at all times of the
year in all years.  This modifier applies only to permanently flooded areas irregularly
flooded by fresh tidal water.  Equivalent to Cowardin's "permanently flooded/tidal".
TIDALLY FLOODED - flooded by the alternate rise and fall of the surface of oceans, seas,
and the bays, rivers, etc. connected to them, caused by the attraction of the moon
and sun [or by the back-up of water caused by unfavorable winds.
UNKNOWN -- The water regime of the area is not known.  The unit is simply described as '(wetland).'
26.	Hydrology Evidence
Describe the hydrological factors that caused you to assign the type to the hydrologic
regime that you chose.  What were the clues that caused you to make the call you did?
Hydrology Evidence can be edited in the Environment 1 section of the Plots and AA
Observation forms.
27.	Jurisdiction
The two-character State or Province code, or the ISO Nation code if appropriate.  To
edit the Jurisdiction for a particular location, enter the Locations form by clicking on the
'Supporting Data' button from the "Main Menu" window.  You can use the pull-down
list to help populate this field, although you can also type in values that are not found
in the list.
28.	Landform
Enter a descriptive term for the landform characteristics of the area.  Landform is edited
in the Environment 1 section of the Plots and AA Observation forms.
29.	Landscape Comments
Describe the landscape context of the community.  What are the adjacent communities?
Are there any other important landscape features influencing this community?
Landscape Comments can be edited in the Environment 2 section of the Plots and AA
Observation forms.
30.	Leaf Phenology
Leaf Phenology can be edited in the Lifeforms section of the Plots and AA Observation
forms. Using the pull-down list, select the value which best describes the leaf phenology
of the dominant stratum.
Definitions:
EVERGREEN - Greater than 75% of the total woody cover is never without green foliage.
DECIDUOUS - Greater than 75% of the total woody cover sheds its foliage simultaneously in
connection with the unfavorable season.
COLD DECIDUOUS - Unfavorable season mainly characterized by winter frost.
DROUGHT DECIDUOUS - Unfavorable season mainly characterized by drought, in most cases
winter-drought.  Foliage is shed regularly every year.  Most trees with relatively thick,
fissured bark.
MIXED EVERGREEN - DECIDUOUS -  Evergreen and deciduous species generally contribute 25-75%
of the total woody cover.
MIXED EVERGREEN / COLD DECIDUOUS - Evergreen and cold-deciduous species admixed.
MIXED EVERGREEN / DROUGHT DECIDUOUS - Evergreen and drought-deciduous species admixed.
HERB - PERENNIAL - Herbaceous vegetation composed of more than 50% perennial species.
HERB - ANNUAL - Herbaceous vegetation composed of more than 50% annual species.
31.	Leaf Type
Leaf Type can be edited in the Lifeforms section of the Plots and AA Observation forms.
Using the pull-down list, select one value which best describes the leaf form of the dominant
stratum.
Values:
BROADLEAF - Woody vegetation primarily broadleaved (generally contribute to greater than 50%
of the total woody cover).
NEEDLELEAF - Woody vegetation primarily needleleaved (generally contribute to greater than 50% cover).
MICROPHYLLOUS - Woody cover primarily microphyllous.
GRAMINOID - Herbaceous vegetation composed of more than 50% graminoid / stipe leaf species.
BROADLEAF HERBACEOUS (FORB) - Herbaceous vegetation composed of more than 50% broadleaf
forb species.
PTERIDOPHTYE - Herbaceous vegetation composed of more than 50% species with frond or frondlike
leaves.
32.	Location Code
Location Code is the unique record identifier for Location Records held in the Locations table.
Each location (e.g. Park, Site, etc.) for which you are recording Plot or AA Observation data
must have a record in the Locations table.   In the case of units of the National Park System, the
Location Code is the standard 4-character Park Code.  Location Codes for other types of Locations
should be selected according to standard convention, if one exists.  For example, conservation
design sites recorded in the Site Basic Record within the BCD System should probably use their
Site codes as Location Codes.
The Location Code can be edited in the Locations form by clicking on the 'Supporting Data'
button from the "Main Menu" window.  It is also found as read-only data in the Identifiers
section of the AA Observation form and the Identifiers 1 section of the Plots form.
33.	Location Name
The name of the location (e.g. Park Name).
The Location Name can be edited in the Locations form by clicking on the 'Supporting Data'
button from the "Main Menu" window.  It is also found as read-only data in the Identifiers
section of the AA Observation form and the Identifiers 1 section of the Plots form.
34.	Organization
The abbreviation or name of the organization that owns or manages the location.  These
should be standardized among all Locations records, such that "NPS" is always used for the
U.S. National Park Service, "TNC" for The Nature Conservancy, etc.
The Organization field can be edited in the Locations form by clicking on the 'Supporting
Data' button from the "Main Menu" window.  It is also found as read-only data in the
Identifiers section of the AA Observation form and the Identifiers 1 section of the Plots
form.  There it is identified as 'Location Organization'.
35.	Other Comments
Use this field for general comments, or any comments that don't seem to fit elsewhere.
Other Comments can be edited in the Misc Comments section of the Plots and AA
Observation forms.
36.	Other Measure1, Other Measure2, Other Measure1 Defined, Other Measure2 Defined
If measures other than percent cover were taken,  use these fields to hold the results
and define the measurements in the Other Measure1 Defined and Other Measure2
Defined fields.
These data fields can be edited by clicking on the 'View/Edit Species List' button in
the Identifiers section of the Plots or AA Observation forms.  To edit Other Measure1
and Other Measure 2, scroll right by clicking on the right arrow of the subwindow's
lower right corner.
37.	Permanent
Check-off indicating if the plot has been permanently marked.  Click on the data square
to produce an 'x'.  Click again to remove the 'x'.  Permanent can be accessed in the
Identifiers 2 section of the Plots form.
38.	Photos
Check-off indicating whether photos of the plot have been taken at the time of sampling.
Click on the data square to produce an 'x'.  Click again to remove the 'x'.  Photos can be
accessed in the Identifiers 2 section of the Plots form.
39.	Physiognomic Class
Physiognomic classes are determined by assessing the relative percent cover and height
of the lifeform comprising the uppermost strata with cover greater than 10%.  (Note:
Percent canopy cover and height ranges are provided as guidelines, not strict cutoff points).
Physiognomic Class is edited in the Lifeforms section of the Plots and AA
Observation forms. Using the pull-down list, select the value which best describes the
physiognomy.  Definitions are modified from the 1973 UNESCO and 1984 Driscoll et al.
Formation Classes and are defined by the relative percent cover of the tree, shrub, dwarf
shrub, herbaceous, and nonvascular strata.
FOREST - Trees (&gt; 5m) with crowns interlocking (generally forming 60-100% cover).
WOODLAND - Trees (&gt; 5m) with crowns not touching (25-60% cover).
SPARSE WOODLAND - Trees (&gt;5m) with crowns widely spaced (10-25% cover).
SHRUBLAND - Shrubs/Trees (0.5-5m) with 25-100% cover.
SPARSE SHRUBLAND - Shrubs/Trees (0.5-5m) with 10-25% cover.
DWARF SHRUBLAND - Dwarf Shrubs/Shrubs/Trees (&lt;0.5m) with 25-100% cover.
SPARSE DWARF SHRUBLAND - Dwarf Shrubs/Shrubs/Trees (&lt;0.5m) with 10-25% cover.
HERBACEOUS - Herbaceous plants with 10-100% cover.
SPARSE VASCULAR/NON-VASCULAR - 1-10% Vascular Vegetation.
40.	Plant Symbol
The Symbol field provides an quick and easy way to search for a species name in the
PLANTS database.  It is accessed by clicking on the 'View/Edit Species List' button
of the Identifiers section of the Plots and AA Observation forms.  The Symbol code
is the identifier for records in PLANTS.  It generally consists of the first two characters
of the Genus name, plus the first two characters of the Species name.
Example:  for Pinus ponderosa, the Symbol is PIPO.
Identical Symbol codes that are for different species names are appended with
tie-breaker characters.
Example:   Pinguicula primuliflora  =  PIPR,    Piptochaetium pringlei  =  PIPR1
To use the Symbol code to search for a species name in PLANTS, type in the
beginning characters of the code and press Enter (or move to the next field).  You
will be shown a list of the PLANTS records that have Symbol codes that start with
the characters you entered.  You can choose the name you are looking for from the list.
41.	Plot Code
This field is the unique identifier for a Plot record.  It is generated by the system, at
the time a new record  is entered into the database.  The Plot Code is assembled from
two parts: the Location Code and the Plot Code Counter, which is a sequential counter
field that is increased automatically each time a Plot is entered for that Location.
Examples:
SHEN.1 		The first Plot record entered for Shenandoah National Park
TUZI.8		The eighth Plot record entered for Tuzigoot National Monument
The sequential counter can be reset to any number you would like when the system
creates the Plot Code for a new Plot record.  As you select the Location for your new Plot
record, the system will suggest a new Plot Code based on the current setting of the counter.
You can accept this Plot Code, or you can change the counter at this point.  Changing the
counter setting will cause the counter to start numbering from the new setting.  This may be
desirable if you would like to coordinate data entry with another installation, and want to
avoid using duplicate Plot Codes. See the How to Get Started section: Entering Data from
field forms: Creating a new plot record for more detailed instructions.  Once you finalize the
Plot Code, you can not change it directly.  If you need to change the Plot Code of your
record, refer to the Troubleshooting/Helpful Hints section: Editing Problems.
The Plot Code is viewed as read-only data in the Identifiers 1 section of the Plots form.
42.	Plot Directions
Precise directions to the site using a readily locatable landmark (e.g., a city, a major
highway, etc.) as the starting point on a state or local road map.  Use clear sentences that
will be understandable to someone who is unfamiliar with the area and has only your
directions to follow.  Give distances as closely as possible to the 0.1 mile and use compass
directions.  Give additional directions to the plot within the site.
Plot Directions can be edited in the Identifiers 2 section of the Plots form.
43.	Plot Representativeness
Does this plot well represent the average species composition and structure, and
environmental setting of the polygon?  If not, were additional plots taken to cover the
range of variability within the polygon?
Plot Representativeness can be edited in the Identifiers 2 section of the Plots form.
44.	Plot Shape
Plot Shape can be edited in the Identifiers 2 section of the Plots form. Using the
pull-down list, select the plot shape which best describes that used for this sample
Values:
Rectangular
Square
Circular
Transect/strip
Other (type in your own term)
45.	Polygon Code
Code indicating the vegetation polygon where the plot was taken.  Fill this out only
if working from previously delineated photos.
The Polygon Code can be edited in the Identifiers section of the AA Observation form
and the Identifiers 1 section of the Plots form.
46.	Polygon Heterogeneity Comments
Enter any observations regarding the heterogeneity (or lack thereof) of the community
and environmental characteristics within the polygon.
Polygon Heterogeneity Comments can be edited in the Misc Comments section of the
AA Observation form.
47.	Polygon Size
Polygon Size can be edited in the Identifiers section of the AA Observation form.  Using
the pull-down list, enter the category that corresponds to the size of the polygon.
48. 	Provisional Community Name
Using the classification system, assign the name of the vegetation type which most
closely resembles this type.  Enter the finest level of the classification possible.  This is
meant to be a field call of the vegetation classification and may change when the data are
analyzed.  Colloquial names can be used in this field if necessary.
Provisional Community Name can be edited in the Identifiers section of the AA
Observation form and the Identifiers 1 section of the Plots form.
49.	Quad Code
Code of USGS 7.5 minute quadrangle map.  Quad Code can be edited in the Identifiers
section of the AA Observation form and the Identifiers 1 section of the Plots form.
50.	Quad Name
Appropriate name/scale from survey map used; use 7.5 minute quadrangle if possible.
Quad Name can be edited in the Identifiers section of the AA Observation form and the
Identifiers 1 section of the Plots form.
51.	Range Cover
Use this field only if you do not use the Real Cover field to specify a true percentage.
Range Cover can be edited by clicking on the 'View/Edit Species List' button in the
Identifiers section of the Plots or AA Observation forms, then scrolling right by clicking
on the right arrow button in the lower right section of one of the subwindows.  Using the
pull-down list, select the value for estimated cover of this species within the stratum. The
system will convert the value you select to a single midpoint percent figure for analysis,
and automatically place that figure in the Real Cover field.
Values:
01	&lt;1%
02	1-5%
03	2-25%
04	25-50%
05	50-75%
06	75-100%
52.	Real Cover
Use this field only if you are not using the Range Cover field to specify a value from
the cover scale.  Enter the actual percent cover for the species within the stratum. Real
Cover can be edited by clicking on the 'View/Edit Species List' button in the Identifiers
section of the Plots or AA Observation forms, then scrolling right by clicking on the
right arrow button in the lower right section of one of the subwindows.
53.	Roll Number
If photos have been taken at the plot, enter the film roll number to help identify the
photos after film processing.
Roll Number can be edited in the Identifiers 2 section of the Plots form.
54.	Salinity/Halinity Modifiers
Salinity/Halinity Modifiers can be edited in the Environment 1 section of the AA
Observation and Plot forms.  Using the pull-down list, enter the salinity/halinity
modifiers of the hydrologic regime.
Values:
Designation				Content
Coastal Tidal: Saltwater - tidal			&gt; 30 ppt
Coastal Tidal: Brackish			0.5 - 30 ppt
Coastal Tidal: Freshwater			&lt; 0.5 ppt
Inland: Saltwater				&gt; 30 ppt
Inland: Brackish				0.5 - 30 ppt
55.	Scientific Name
The scientific name for an individual species record within the NRCS PLANTS
Database.  As supplied by the NRCS, this field also contains authority information.
This field is used as validation data when a species' name is entered into the Species
Scientific Name field in either the Plots or the AA Observations table.
The Scientific Name can be edited by clicking the 'PLANTS Database Maintenance'
button from the "Main Menu" window.  Click on one of the 'Edit/View Data' buttons.
Edit according to the instructions in the Functions section: Editing Data: Undo/Edit
functions.
NOTE: if you change the contents of the PLANTS Database in any way you can not
represent it to others as the NRCS PLANTS Database.  Please read the PLANTS
copyright notice (click the 'Important Copyright Information' button in the "Main Menu"
window).
56.	Slope
Measure slope degrees using a clinometer.  Slope can be edited in the Environment 1
section of the AA Observation and Plots forms.  Using the pull-down list, select an
entry that corresponds to the degree measurement.
VALUES:
Degree		Percent
FLAT				0		0%
GENTLE				0-5&amp;Acirc;°		1-9%
MODERATE			6-14&amp;Acirc;°		10-25%
SOMEWHAT STEEP		15-26&amp;Acirc;°		26-49%
STEEP				27-45&amp;Acirc;°		50-100%
VERY STEEP			45-69&amp;Acirc;°		101-275%
ABRUPT				70E-100&amp;Acirc;°		276-300%
OVERHANGING/SHELTERED		&gt;100&amp;Acirc;°	       	&gt;300%
57.	Soil Depth
Enter the depth of the soil. Using the associated check-offs indicate the units of
measurement.  Click on the data square to produce an 'x'.  In the Environmental
Comments field indicate whether this was measured or estimated.
Soil Depth can be edited in the Environment 2 section of the Plots form.
58.	Soil Drainage
Soil Drainage can be edited in the Environment 2 section of the Plots form. Using the
pull-down list, enter the appropriate term describing soil drainage characteristics, per
the following discussion:
The soil drainage classes are defined in terms of (1) actual moisture content (in
excess of field moisture capacity), and (2) the extent of the period during which excess
water is present in the plantroot zone.
It is recognized that permeability, level of groundwater, and seepage are factors
affecting moisture status.  However, because these are not easily observed or measured
in the field, they cannot be used generally as criteria of moisture status.  It is further
recognized that soil profile morphology, for example mottling, normally, but not always,
reflects soil moisture status.  Although soil morphology may be a valuable field indication
of moisture status, it should not be the overriding criterion.  Soil drainage classes cannot
be based solely on the presence or absence of mottling.  Topographic position and
vegetation as well as soil morphology are useful field criteria for assessing soil moisture
status.
RAPIDLY DRAINED - The soil moisture content seldom exceeds field capacity in any horizon
except immediately after water addition.  Soils are free from any evidence of gleying
throughout the profile.  Rapidly drained soils are commonly coarse textured or soils on
steep slopes.
WELL DRAINED - The soil moisture content does not normally exceed field capacity in any
horizon (except possibly the C) for a significant part of the year. Soils are usually free
from mottling in the upper 3 feet, but may be mottled below this depth.  B horizons, if
present, are reddish, brownish, or yellowish.
MODERATELY WELL DRAINED - The soil moisture in excess of field capacity remains for a
small but significant period of the year. Soils are commonly mottled (chroma &lt; 2) in the
lower B and C horizons or below a depth of 2 feet.  The Ae horizon, if present, may be
faintly mottled in fine textured soils and in medium textured soils that have a slowly
permeable layer below the solum.  In grassland soils the B and C horizons may be
only faintly mottled and the A horizon may be relatively thick and dark.
SOMEWHAT POORLY DRAINED - The soil moisture in excess of field capacity remains
in subsurface horizons for moderately long periods during the year. Soils are
commonly mottled in the B and C horizons; the Ae horizon, if present, may be mottled.
The matrix generally has a lower chroma than in the well drained soil on similar parent
material.
POORLY DRAINED - The soil moisture in excess of field capacity remains in all horizons for
a large part of the year. The soils are usually very strongly gleyed.  Except in
highchroma parent materials the B, if present, and upper C horizons usually have
matrix colors of low chroma.  Faint mottling may occur throughout.
VERY POORLY DRAINED - Free water remains at or within 12 inches of the surface most
of the year. The soils are usually very strongly gleyed.  Subsurface horizons usually
are of low chroma and yellowish to bluish hues.  Mottling may be present but at
depth in the profile.  Very poorly drained soils usually have a mucky or peaty surface
horizon. Simplified Key to Soil Texture (Brewer and McCann, 1982).
59.	Soil Taxon/Description
Soil Taxon/Description can be edited in the Environment 2 section of the Plots form.
Provide the soil name and the name of the soil report/map from which the
information was obtained.  Also provide a basic description of the soils noting the
most significant features with respect to classifying the vegetation.  A soil core
should be taken.  Describe the soil horizons and note the depth, texture, and color
of each.  Note significant changes such as depth to mottling, depth to water table,
root penetration depth, depth of the organic layer.  Also include general description
soil depth class (shallow, deep, very deep, etc.) pH, stoniness, erosion potential and
type, etc.  If it is not possible to take a soil core, as much information as possible
should be recorded from the soil report and it should be noted that no core was taken.
60.	Soil Texture
Soil Texture can be edited in the Environment 2 section of the Plots form. Using the
pull-down list, enter the appropriate term describing the soil texture.  Use the following
key to derive the term:
Simplified Key to Soil Texture (Brewer and McCann, 1982)
A1		Soil does not remain in a ball when squeezed. . . . .  . .  sand
A2		Soil remains in a ball when squeezed. . . . . . . . . . . . . . B
B1		Squeeze the ball between your thumb and forefinger, attempting to make a ribbon
that you push up over your finger.  Soil makes no ribbon.  . . . .  loamy sand
B2		Soil makes a ribbon; may be very short. . . . . . . . . . . . . C
C1		Ribbon extends less than 1 inch before breaking . . . . . . . . D
C2		Ribbon extends 1 inch or more before breaking . . . . . . . . . E
D1		Add excess water to small amount of soil;
soil feels at least slightly gritty . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . loam or sandy loam
D2		Soil feels smooth . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .  silt loam
E1		Soil makes a ribbon that breaks when 12 inches long;
cracks if bent into a ring . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . F
E2		Soil makes a ribbon 2+ inches long;
doesn't crack when bent into a ring . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . G
F1		Add excess water to small amount of soil;
soil feels at least slightly gritty. . . . . . . . . . . . .sandy clay loam or clay loam
F2		Soil feels smooth . . .  . . . . . . . . . . silty clay loam or silt
G1		Add excess water to a small amount of soil;
soil feels at least slightly gritty . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . sandy clay or clay
G2		Soil feels smooth. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . silty clay
61.	Source
This field indicates the source of the name record in the PLANTS Database.
Values:
SS	Standard Source  (e.g. the NRCS PLANTS list)
NS	Non-standard Source  (any source other than NRCS)
SY 	Accepted synonym by NRCS list
The Source can be edited by clicking the 'PLANTS Database Maintenance'
button from the "Main Menu" window.  Click on one of the 'Edit/View Data'
buttons.  Edit according to the instructions in the Functions section: Editing
Data: Undo/Edit functions.
NOTE: if you change the contents of the PLANTS Database in any way you can not
represent it to others as the NRCS PLANTS Database.  Please read the PLANTS
copyright notice (click the 'Important Copyright Information' button in the "Main
Menu" window).
62.	Species Scientific Name
The scientific name for an individual species found in a Plot or Accuracy
Assessment observation.
To edit the Species Scientific Name, click on the 'View/Edit Species List' button
in the Identifiers 1 section of the Plots form or the Identifiers section of the AA
Observation form.
Please see the How to Get Started section: Entering Data from field forms: Entering
Species Data for a Plot.
63.	Specimen #
Enter the Specimen # if a specimen of the species was collected.  Enter the number
catalogued on the specimen.  If your program doesn't  already have guidelines
in place for cataloguing specimens, use the plot code + a counter to create
the specimen number.  (Example: SHEN.1.1).
To edit the Specimen #, click on the 'View/Edit Species List' button in the Identifiers
1 section of the Plots form or the Identifiers section of the AA Observation form.
64.	Standard Source Name
The Standard Source Name is the Scientific Name accepted by NRCS as the
standard name to be used in classification.
The "Specify Plant Species" window is divided into two columns.  The first
column gives the Scientific Name, while the second gives the Common Name
OR the Standard Source Name if the Scientific Name is a synonym recognized by
NRCS.  The Standard Source Name is preceded by an '=' sign.  If you would like
to avoid entering the Synonym, then return to step 2) and search for the Standard
Source Name.
65.	Stratum
Visually divide the community into vegetation layers (strata).
To edit the Stratum, click on the 'View/Edit Species List' button in the Identifiers
1 section of the Plots form or the Identifiers section of the AA Observation form.
Using the pull-down list, select the identifier abbreviation for the stratum in which
this species occurs.
Lifeforms:
EMERGENT TREE				T1
TREE CANOPY				T2
TREE SUBCANOPY				T3
TALL SHRUB (25m)				S1
SHORT SHRUB (&lt;2m)			S2
DWARF-SHRUB				S3
HERBACEOUS				H
NONVASCULAR				N
EPIPHYTE				E
VINE/LIANA				V
66.	Stratum Height Class
Visually divide the community into vegetation layers (strata).  Stratum Height
Class is the height scale that represents the average height of the stratum.
To edit the Stratum Height Class, enter the Lifeforms section of the Plots or AA
Observation forms. Using the pull-down list, select the class that indicates the
average height of the stratum (the height scale is also shown below).
TREES are defined as single-stemmed woody plants, generally greater than
5m in height or greater at maturity and under optimal growing conditions.
SHRUBS are defined as multiple-stemmed woody plants generally less than
5m in height at maturity and under optimal growing conditions.
Height Scale for Strata
01		&lt;0.5 m
02		0.5-1m
03		1-2 m
04		2-5 m
05		5-10 m
06		10-15 m
07		15-20 m
08		20-35 m
09		35 - 50 m
10		&gt;50 m
Lifeforms -
EMERGENT TREE				T1
TREE CANOPY				T2
TREE SUBCANOPY				T3
TALL SHRUB (25m)				S1
SHORT SHRUB (&lt;2m)			S2
DWARF-SHRUB				S3
HERBACEOUS				H
NONVASCULAR				N
EPIPHYTE				E
VINE/LIANA				V
67.	Stratum Percent Cover
Visually divide the community into vegetation layers (strata).  Stratum Percent
Cover is the class value that represents the average percent cover of the whole
stratum.
To edit the Stratum Height Class, enter the Lifeforms section of the Plots or AA
Observation forms.  Using the pull-down list, select the class value indicating
the average percent cover of the whole stratum.
TREES are defined as single-stemmed woody plants, generally greater than 5m in
height or greater at maturity and under optimal growing conditions.  SHRUBS are
defined as multiple-stemmed woody plants generally less than 5m in height at
maturity and under optimal growing conditions.
Lifeforms -
EMERGENT TREE					T1
TREE CANOPY					T2
TREE SUBCANOPY					T3
TALL SHRUB (25m)					S1
SHORT SHRUB (&lt;2m)				S2
DWARF-SHRUB					S3
HERBACEOUS					H
NONVASCULAR					N
EPIPHYTE					E
VINE/LIANA					V
68.	Sublocation
Provisional name assigned by field worker that describes where the data were
collected; should represent an identifiable feature on topographic map.
Sublocation can be edited in the Identifiers 1 section of the Plots form and the
Identifiers section of the AA Observation form.
69.	SubPlot
Click on the data square to produce an 'x' if the plot is a subplot of another larger
plot. Leave blank if the plot is not a subplot of another plot.
SubPlot can be edited in the Identifiers 1 section of the Plots form.
70.	SubPlot Parent Code
Enter the Plot Code for the plot for which this record is a subplot.  Use the pull-down
list to find the correct Plot Code.
SubPlot Parent Code can be edited in the Identifiers 1 section of the Plots form.
71.	Surficial Geology
Surficial Geology can be edited in the Environment 1 section of the Plots and AA
Observation forms.  Using the pull-down list, select a term that describes the
geologic substrate influencing the plant community (bedrock or surficial materials).
The list provided with the Plots Database software is to serve as an example of the
kinds of terms you could use.  You can customize this list by clicking on the button
'Edit Geology List', which will take you to the Surficial Geology Classes form.
72.	Survey Date
Date the survey was taken; month, day, year*.  *Year is entered as 4 characters, so
as to avoid the "Year 2000" computer problem.  After it has been entered, 20th
century years appear as two characters, 21st century years appear with all four
characters.
Survey Date can be edited in the Identifiers 1 section of the Plots form and the
Identifiers section of the AA Observation form.
73.	Surveyors
Names (and addresses, if appropriate) of surveyors, principle surveyor listed first.
Surveyors can be edited in the Identifiers 1 section of the Plots form and the Identifiers
section of the AA Observation form.
74.	Synonym
The Synonym is the Scientific Name accepted by NRCS as a synonym.
The "Specify Plant Species" window is divided into two columns.  The first column
gives the Scientific Name, while the second gives the Common Name OR the Standard
Source Name if the Scientific Name is a synonym recognized by NRCS.  The Standard
Source Name is preceded by an "=" sign.  If you would like to avoid entering the
Synonym, then return to step 2) and search for the Standard Source Name.
75.	TNC Elcode
Enter the Elcode (Element Code) for the community element corresponding to the
Classified Community Name.
TNC Elcode can be edited in the Identifiers 1 section of the Plots form and the
Identifiers section of the AA Observation form.
76.	TNC EONum-Suffix
Enter the EO Number, State/Province, and Nation portion of the EOCODE (i.e., that
portion of the EOCODE that follows the ELCODE) that identifies the Element
Occurrence Record (EOR) for this plot.
TNC EONum-Suffix can be edited in the Identifiers 1 section of the Plots form and the
Identifiers section of the AA Observation form.
77.	Topo Position
Topographic position of the plot.  Use the pull-down list to select an appropriate value.
Topo Position can be edited in the Environment 1 section of the Plots and AA
Observation forms.
Values:
INTERFLUVE: (crest, summit, ridge): linear top of ridge, hill, or mountain; the elevated
area between two fluves (drainageways) that sheds water to the drainageways.
HIGH SLOPE: (shoulder slope, upper slope, convex creep slope): geomorphic component
that forms the uppermost inclined surface at the top of a slope. Comprises the
transition zone from backslope to summit. Surface is dominantly convex in profile
and erosional in origin.
HIGH LEVEL (mesa): level top of plateau.
MIDSLOPE (transportational midslope, middle slope): intermediate slope position
BACKSLOPE (dipslope): subset of midslopes which are steep, linear, and may include cliff
segments (fall faces).
STEP IN SLOPE (ledge, terracette): nearly level shelf interrupting a steep slope, rock wall, or
cliff face.
LOWSLOPE (lower slope, foot slope, colluvial footslope): inner gently inclined surface at the
base of a slope. Surface profile is generally concave and a transition between midslope or
backslope, and toe slope.
TOESLOPE (alluvial toeslope): outermost gently inclined surface at base of a slope. In profile,
commonly gentle and linear and characterized by alluvial deposition.
LOW LEVEL (terrace): valley floor or shoreline representing the former position of an alluvial
plain, lake, or shore.
CHANNEL WALL (bank): sloping side of a channel.
CHANNEL BED (narrow valley bottom, gully arroyo): bed of single or braided watercourse
commonly barren of vegetation and formed of modern alluvium.
BASIN FLOOR (depression): nearly level to gently sloping, bottom surface of a basin.
78.	Unvegetated Surface categories
In each category field (e.g. % Bedrock, % Large Rocks, etc.), enter the percentage of
surface covered by each category.  Include only the categories/fields covering over
5 percent.
Use the "% Other" field to note any additional category that may be significant, and
indicate the name of that category in the "Description" field.
Unvegetated Surface can be edited in the Environment 2 section of the Plots and
AA Observation forms.
Definitions:
BEDROCK: sheets of bedrock exposed at the surface.
LARGE ROCKS: includes boulders and cobbles greater than 10 cm diameter.
SMALL ROCKS: includes gravel, 0.2-10 cm diameter.
SAND: small particles 0.1 - 2 mm diameter.
BARE SOIL (mineral / organic): includes small particles less than 0.1 mm diameter.
LITTER, DUFF: litter includes freshly-fallen leaves, needles, twigs, bark, fruits, and wood
fragments less than 1 cm.  Duff is fermentation layer and humus layer (organic horizon).
WOOD: downed fragments greater than 1 cm.
79.	Used PLANTS
This field will be automatically checked if the name appearing in the Species Scientific
Name field is found in the PLANTS database.  Note that the automatic check-off will only
take place if there is an exact match between the Species Scientific Name and the name as
listed in PLANTS (which typically lists the authority).
Used PLANTS can not be edited.
80.	X Dimension
Enter the length in meters* of one side of each of the plots in which samples were taken.
If the plot is circular, enter the length of its radius.  If transects were used, enter their length
here. The value of X Dimension should correspond to the plot specified in the Plot Shape
field.  *NOTE:  Dimensions MUST be converted to meters.
X Dimension can be edited in the Identifiers 2 section of the Plots form.
81.	Y Dimension
Enter the length in meters* of the side of the plot adjacent to the side entered in the X
Dimension field.  The value entered in the Y Dimension field should correspond to the plot
referred to in the Plot Shape  and X Dimension  fields.  Leave this field blank if the plot is
circular.  Enter a one if a transect was used.  *NOTE:  Dimensions MUST be converted to meters.
Y Dimension can be edited in the Identifiers 2 section of the Plots form.
82.	Zone
Zone of the Universal Transverse Mercator projection. To be filled in at the office, not
in the field.
Zone can be edited in the Environment 1 section of the Plots and Accuracy Assessment forms.
</eaover>
<eadetcit>
See:
http://biology.usgs.gov/npsveg/ftp/vegmapping/tncplots/USER7.DOC,
http://biology.usgs.gov/npsveg/badl/report.pdf#appendix6
and
http://biology.usgs.gov/npsveg/badl/report.pdf#appendix7
</eadetcit>
</overview>
</eainfo>
<distinfo>
<distrib>
<cntinfo>
<cntperp>
<cntper>USGS-NPS Vegetation Mapping Program Coordinator</cntper>
<cntorg>Center for Biological Informatics, USGS-BRD</cntorg>
</cntperp>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>Mailing Address</addrtype>
<address>PO Box 25046, MS-302</address>
<city>Denver</city>
<state>Colorado</state>
<postal>80225</postal>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>(303) 202-4220</cntvoice>
<cntfax>303-202-4229</cntfax>
<cntfax>303-202-4219 (org)</cntfax>
<cntemail>gs-b-npsveg@usgs.gov</cntemail>
</cntinfo>
</distrib>
<resdesc>Badlands National Park Field Data</resdesc>
<distliab>
Although these data have been processed
successfully on a computer system at the
Biological Resources Division, no warranty
expressed or implied is made regarding the
accuracy or utility of the data on any other
system or for general or scientific purposes, nor
shall the act of distribution constitute any such
warranty. This disclaimer applies both to
individual use of the data and aggregate use with
other data.  It is strongly recommended that these
data are directly acquired from a Biological
Resources Division server, and not indirectly
through other sources which may have changed the
data in some way.  It is also strongly recommended
that careful attention be paid to the contents of
the metadata file associated with these data.  The
Biological Resources Division shall not be held
liable for improper or incorrect use of the data
described and/or contained herein.
</distliab>
<stdorder>
<digform>
<digtinfo>
<formname>HTML</formname>
</digtinfo>
<digtopt>
<onlinopt>
<computer>
<networka>
<networkr>http://biology.usgs.gov/npsveg/badl/fielddata.html</networkr>
</networka>
</computer>
</onlinopt>
</digtopt>
</digform>
<fees>None</fees>
</stdorder>
</distinfo>
<metainfo>
<metd>200111</metd>
<metrd>20050511</metrd>
<metc>
<cntinfo>
<cntorgp>
<cntorg>USGS-NPS Vegetation Mapping Program Coordinator</cntorg>
</cntorgp>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
<address>
U.S. Geological Survey, Center for Biological Informatics, MS 302,
Room 8000, Building 810, Denver Federal Center
</address>
<city>Denver</city>
<state>Colorado</state>
<postal>80225</postal>
<country>USA</country>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>(303) 202-4220</cntvoice>
<cntfax>(303) 202-4219</cntfax>
<cntemail>gs-b-npsveg@usgs.gov</cntemail>
</cntinfo>
</metc>
<metstdn>FGDC-STD-001.1-1999 Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata, 1998 Part 1: Biological Data Profile, 1999</metstdn>
<metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
<metextns>
<onlink>http://biology.usgs.gov/fgdc.bio/bionwext.txt</onlink>
<metprof>Biological Data Profile FGDC-STD-001.1-1999</metprof>
</metextns>
</metainfo>
<mercury><begdate>19970801</begdate><enddate>19971231</enddate><htmlurl>http://mercury.ornl.gov/metadata/nbii/html/nbii/www.nbii.gov_metadata_mdata_CBI_usgs_brd_cbi_d_badlfield.html</htmlurl><LTER-Site>nbii</LTER-Site></mercury></metadata>
