<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<metadata><Source>http://www.nbii.gov/metadata/mdata/brd-bib/usgs_brd_fresc_b_pub25816.sgml</Source>
<idinfo>
<citation>
<citeinfo>
<origin>Linda S. Schueck, John M. Marzluff, and Karen Steenhof</origin>
<pubdate>2001</pubdate>
<title>Influence of military activities on raptor abundance and behavior</title>
<geoform>Journal article</geoform>
<serinfo>
<sername>Condor</sername>
<issue>103:606-615</issue>
</serinfo>
<othercit>
Science Information System Project #: 733
Publication Control #: Olendorf-25816; FRESC HQ-1035
</othercit>
</citeinfo>
</citation>
<descript>
<abstract>This publication presents the results of  a study that investigated the influence of military training on abundance and behavior of raptors at a National Guard military training area in the Snake  River Birds of Prey National Conservation Area in Idaho during the breeding seasons of 1991-1994.  The purpose of the study was to determine whether military training activity influenced raptor use of and behavior in an area with an exceptionally high density and diversity of raptors. The study found that during training exercises, raptors perched and flew at low levels less often than when training did not occur.  There were fewer prey capture attempts on training days than on non-training days.  Training that involved firing was more disruptive than other forms of training.  Military training affected raptor behavior only when training intensity was high and prey availability was low.  Observed levels of military training  during years with adequate prey should have minimal adverse effects on raptor behavior. Suggestions for mitigating adverse effects include changing the timing and location of training activities.</abstract>
<purpose>Reporting research results</purpose>
<supplinf>
Extent of item: 9pp
Illustrative Matter: tables, graphs
</supplinf>
</descript>
<timeperd>
<timeinfo>
<rngdates>
<begdate>1991</begdate>
<enddate>1994</enddate>
</rngdates>
</timeinfo>
<current>ground condition</current>
</timeperd>
<status>
<progress>Complete</progress>
<update>None planned</update>
</status>
<spdom>
<descgeog>Snake River Birds of Prey Area</descgeog>
<bounding>
<westbc>-116.5003</westbc>
<eastbc>-115.6253</eastbc>
<northbc>43.3753</northbc>
<southbc>43.0417</southbc>
</bounding>
</spdom>
<keywords>
<theme>
<themekt>NBII Biocomplexity Thesaurus</themekt>
<themekey>Birds of Prey</themekey>
<themekey>Human impact</themekey>
<themekey>Foraging behavior</themekey>
</theme>
<theme>
<themekt>None</themekt>
<themekey>avian conservation</themekey>
<themekey>military training</themekey>
<themekey>raptor</themekey>
</theme>
<place>
<placekt>none</placekt>
<placekey>Snake River Birds of Prey National Conservation Area</placekey>
<placekey>Idaho</placekey>
<placekey>ID</placekey>
</place>
</keywords>
<taxonomy>
<keywtax>
<taxonkt>None</taxonkt>
<taxonkey>birds</taxonkey>
</keywtax>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Kingdom</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Animalia</taxonrv>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Phylum</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Chordata</taxonrv>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Subdivision</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Vertebrata</taxonrv>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Class</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Aves</taxonrv>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Order</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Falconiformes</taxonrv>
</taxoncl>
</taxoncl>
</taxoncl>
</taxoncl>
</taxoncl>
</taxonomy>
<accconst>None</accconst>
<useconst>None</useconst>
<ptcontac>
<cntinfo>
<cntorgp>
<cntorg>Olendorff Library</cntorg>
</cntorgp>
<cntpos>Librarian</cntpos>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
<address>
USGS FRESC Snake River Field Station
970 Lusk Street
</address>
<city>Boise</city>
<state>ID</state>
<postal>83706</postal>
<country>USA</country>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>208 426-5218</cntvoice>
<cntfax>208 426-5210</cntfax>
<cntemail>fresc_outreach@usgs.gov</cntemail>
</cntinfo>
</ptcontac>
</idinfo>
<distinfo>
<distrib>
<cntinfo>
<cntorgp>
<cntorg>Olendorff Library</cntorg>
</cntorgp>
<cntpos>Librarian</cntpos>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
<address>
USGS FRESC Snake River Field Station
970 Lusk Street
</address>
<city>Boise</city>
<state>ID</state>
<postal>83706</postal>
<country>USA</country>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>208 426-5218</cntvoice>
<cntfax>208 426-5210</cntfax>
<cntemail>fresc_outreach@usgs.gov</cntemail>
</cntinfo>
</distrib>
<resdesc>Publication Control #: 25816</resdesc>
<distliab>
The USGS Forest and Rangeland Ecosystem Science Center and its research partners make every effort to provide and maintain accurate, complete, usable, and timely information. However, some USGS data and information may, of necessity, be preliminary in nature. These data and information are provided with the understanding that they are not guaranteed to be correct or complete. Users are cautioned to consider carefully the provisional nature of these data and information before using them for decisions that concern personal or public safety or the conduct of business that involves substantial monetary or operational consequences. It is also strongly recommended that careful attention be paid to the contents of the metadata file associated with these data and information. Conclusions drawn from, or actions undertaken on the basis of, such data and information are the sole responsibility of the user.
USGS-authored or produced data and information are in the public domain. Whereas the content of many USGS publications and other information resources are in the public domain, some USGS products contain material that is copyrighted by others and used by the USGS with permission. Users of this information may need to obtain permission from the copyright owner for other uses. Furthermore, some non-USGS data, products, and information referred to may be protected under U.S. and foreign copyright laws. Users may need to obtain permission from the copyright owner to acquire, use, reproduce, or distribute these materials. It is the sole responsibility of the user of the information to secure all necessary permission.
</distliab>
<stdorder>
<nondig>Publications are available as reprints, reports, pamphlets, or brochures.</nondig>
<fees>None</fees>
<ordering>Request specific publications by reference number.</ordering>
</stdorder>
</distinfo>
<metainfo>
<metd>20050413</metd>
<metrd>20011111</metrd>
<metc>
<cntinfo>
<cntorgp>
<cntorg>Olendorff Library</cntorg>
</cntorgp>
<cntpos>Librarian</cntpos>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
<address>
USGS FRESC Snake River Field Station
970 Lusk Street
</address>
<city>Boise</city>
<state>ID</state>
<postal>83706</postal>
<country>USA</country>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>208 426-5218</cntvoice>
<cntfax>208 426-5210</cntfax>
<cntemail>fresc_outreach@usgs.gov</cntemail>
</cntinfo>
</metc>
<metstdn>FGDC Biological Data Profile of the Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
<metstdv>FGDC-STD-001.1-1999</metstdv>
</metainfo>
<mercury><begdate>19910101</begdate><enddate>19941231</enddate><htmlurl>http://mercury.ornl.gov/metadata/nbii/html/brd/www.nbii.gov_metadata_mdata_brd-bib_usgs_brd_fresc_b_pub25816.html</htmlurl><LTER-Site>brd</LTER-Site></mercury></metadata>
