<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<metadata><Source>http://www.nbii.gov/metadata/mdata/CSIRO/csiro_d_ausfishcollection.sgml</Source>
<idinfo>
<citation>
<citeinfo>
<origin>Peter Last, and Alastair Graham, CSIRO Marine Research</origin>
<pubdate>Unknown</pubdate>
<title>Australian National Fish Collection</title>
<geoform>maps data</geoform>
<pubinfo>
<pubplace>Hobart, Australia</pubplace>
<publish>CSIRO Division of Marine Research</publish>
</pubinfo>
</citeinfo>
</citation>
<descript>
<abstract>The Australian National Fish Collection (formerly the I.S.R. Munro Ichthyological Collection) is a collection of some 135,000 vouchered fish specimens from 2,800 species, originally started by Dr. I.S.R. Munro of CSIRO Division of Fisheries in the 1940's and now housed at CSIRO Marine Research in Hobart. It holds information on taxonomic identity of specimens, and collection details. Materials come from community studies and findings, fishers, and expeditions and cruises on CSIRO survey and research vessels, notably Fairwind (Papua New Guinea region, 1948-1950), Stanley Fowler (tropical Australia, 1948-1950), Rama (Gulf of Carpentaria, 1963-1965), Courageous (1975-1979), Soela (1979-1989) and Southern Surveyor (1990 to present). While the largest part of the collection is from Australian waters, there are also collections from Papua New Guinea, the Bismarck Archipelago, Solomon Islands, New Zealand, Antarctic waters, south-east Asia, and Europe. As well as adult fishes, the collection also contains specimens of fish eggs and larvae, and otoliths. Also included is an extensive collection of associated photographs and x-rays. This metadata record is sourced from 'MarLIN', the CSIRO Marine Laboratories Information Network.</abstract>
<purpose>In addition to its value as a reference library for other scientists and research organisations, the Collection has proved an invaluable resource for producing CSIRO publications. These include the recently published Australian Seafood Handbook: an identification guide to domestic species, and guides to the South East Fishery trawl quota species and Australian sharks and rays.</purpose>
<supplinf>Information was obtained from: http://www.marine.csiro.au/marine/mcdd/data/CSIRODMR/CSIRODMR_datasets.html.  (previous geoform was 'collection')</supplinf>
</descript>
<timeperd>
<timeinfo>
<rngdates>
<begdate>19400101</begdate>
<enddate>Present</enddate>
</rngdates>
</timeinfo>
<current>ground condition</current>
</timeperd>
<status>
<progress>In Work</progress>
<update>Continually</update>
</status>
<spdom>
<descgeog>Australian EEZ, Indian Ocean, Indonesia coastal waters, New Zealand coastal waters, Pacific Ocean, Papua New Guinea coastal waters, Southern Ocean</descgeog>
<bounding>
<westbc>75</westbc>
<eastbc>180</eastbc>
<northbc>45</northbc>
<southbc>-85</southbc>
</bounding>
</spdom>
<keywords>
<theme>
<themekt>none</themekt>
<themekey>fish collection</themekey>
<themekey>geographical distribution</themekey>
<themekey>reproduction and development</themekey>
</theme>
<place>
<placekt>none</placekt>
<placekey>Australia</placekey>
<placekey>Australian EEZ</placekey>
<placekey>Indian Ocean</placekey>
<placekey>Indonesia coastal waters</placekey>
<placekey>New Zealand coastal waters</placekey>
<placekey>Pacific Ocean</placekey>
<placekey>Papua New Guinea coastal waters</placekey>
<placekey>Southern Ocean</placekey>
</place>
</keywords>
<taxonomy>
<keywtax>
<taxonkt>none</taxonkt>
<taxonkey>fish</taxonkey>
<taxonkey>shark</taxonkey>
<taxonkey>ray</taxonkey>
</keywtax>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Kingdom</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Animalia</taxonrv>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Phylum</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Chordata</taxonrv>
<common>chordates</common>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Subphylum</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>vertebrata</taxonrv>
<common>vertebrates</common>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Superclass</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Osteichthyes</taxonrv>
<common>bony fishes</common>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Class</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Sarcopterygii</taxonrv>
</taxoncl>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Class</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Actinopterygii</taxonrv>
<common>ray-finned fishes</common>
<common>spiny rayed fishes</common>
</taxoncl>
</taxoncl>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Superclass</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Agnatha</taxonrv>
<common>cyclostomes</common>
<common>jawless fishes</common>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Class</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Pteraspidomorphi</taxonrv>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Subclass</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Pteraspidomorpha</taxonrv>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Order</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Myxiniformes</taxonrv>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Family</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Myxinidae</taxonrv>
</taxoncl>
</taxoncl>
</taxoncl>
</taxoncl>
</taxoncl>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Superclass</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>unknown</taxonrv>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Class</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Chondrichthyes</taxonrv>
<common>cartilaginous fishes</common>
<common>rays</common>
<common>sharks</common>
</taxoncl>
</taxoncl>
</taxoncl>
</taxoncl>
</taxoncl>
</taxonomy>
<accconst>By arrangement with custodian.</accconst>
<useconst>None</useconst>
<ptcontac>
<cntinfo>
<cntperp>
<cntper>Alistair Graham</cntper>
<cntorg>CSIRO Division of Marine Research</cntorg>
</cntperp>
<cntpos>Fish Collection Manager</cntpos>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
<address>G.P.O.Box 1538</address>
<city>Hobart</city>
<state>TAS</state>
<country>Australia</country>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>(03) 6232 5351</cntvoice>
<cntfax>+61 (0)362 325000</cntfax>
<cntemail>alastair.graham@csiro.au, Alastair.Graham@marine.csiro.au</cntemail>
</cntinfo>
</ptcontac>
</idinfo>
<dataqual>
<logic>not applicable</logic>
<complete>Approximately 2,800 of Australia's estimated 4,500 fish species are represented in the collection.  Judged by the diversity of species it holds, the Collection is among the largest in the Southern Hemisphere. All specialist collections strive for quality and diversity. The Collection&amp;#146;s focus on Indo Pacific shark and ray, and temperate and Southern Ocean species gives it a pre-eminence among international collections. The 135,000 specimens from 2,800 species (representing 300 fish families) include oceanic, deep-water, demersal, inshore, estuarine, river and lake fishes. Most are from Australian waters, but there are also collections from Papua New Guinea, the Bismarck Archipelago and the Solomon Islands, as well as fish from New Zealand, the Antarctic continent and sub-Antarctic islands, Europe and South-east Asia, including Sri Lanka, Malaysia, the Philippines and Japan. The Collection holds 35 holotypes and 200 paratypes of 70 species new to science. It also contains a substantial amount of voucher material relating to published books and papers, illustrations and photographs. A valuable component of the Collection is the large Photographic Index of Australian Fishes (PIAF see back page) and the radiographs, which are useful for detailed bone studies. The Collection also contains hundreds of jars of ichthyoplankton (fish eggs and larval fish), some of which are unsorted, and collections of otoliths (ear bones, for determining the age of fish). A computerized index of the contents of the Collection has been developed using Texpress software designed by KE Software of Melbourne. This index will be linked up with other CSIRO collections and museum systems in the near future. A substantial collection from the Tasmanian Department of Sea Fisheries, together with material from museums, professional fishermen and other Government organisations, has been incorporated into th Collection, which is managed by a staff of three people.</complete>
<posacc>
<horizpa>
<horizpar>Variable.  Most collections from recent research vessels come from known depths and positions verified by ship's GPS.</horizpar>
</horizpa>
</posacc>
<lineage>
<method>
<methtype>Field</methtype>
<methdesc>Material has been obtained in many ways  from community studies and findings, fishers, and expeditions and cruises on survey and research vessels, notably Fairwind (Papua New Guinea region, 1948-1950), Stanley Fowler (tropical Australia, 1948-1950), Rama (Gulf of Carpentaria, 1963-1965), Courageous (1975-1979), Soela (1979-1989) and Southern Surveyor (1990 to present).</methdesc>
</method>
<method>
<methtype>lab</methtype>
<methdesc>Resident taxonomic specialists are responsible for the taxonomic IDs.</methdesc>
</method>
<procstep>
<procdesc>unknown</procdesc>
<procdate>Unknown</procdate>
</procstep>
</lineage>
</dataqual>
<spdoinfo>
<direct>Point</direct>
</spdoinfo>
<eainfo>
<overview>
<eaover>Entity - Australian National Fish Collection; Attributes - taxonomy, specimens, collection details.</eaover>
<eadetcit>none</eadetcit>
</overview>
</eainfo>
<distinfo>
<distrib>
<cntinfo>
<cntperp>
<cntper>Tony Rees</cntper>
<cntorg>CSIRO Division of Marine Research-Hobart</cntorg>
</cntperp>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
<city>Hobart</city>
<country>Australia</country>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>unknown</cntvoice>
<cntfax>unknown</cntfax>
<cntemail>Tony.Rees@csiro.au</cntemail>
</cntinfo>
</distrib>
<distliab>You accept all risks and responsibility for losses, damages, costs and other consequences resulting directly or indirectly from using this site and andinformation or material available from it. To the maximum permitted by law, CSIRO excludes all liability to any person arising directly or indirectly from using this site and any information or material available from it.</distliab>
<stdorder>
<nondig>photographs (negatives and/or prints), vouchered specimens, biological</nondig>
<fees>unknown</fees>
</stdorder>
<custom>Please contact the distributor.</custom>
</distinfo>
<metainfo>
<metd>20010615</metd>
<metrd>20020930</metrd>
<metfrd>20030930</metfrd>
<metc>
<cntinfo>
<cntperp>
<cntper>Cheryl Solomon</cntper>
<cntorg>Science Systems and Applications, Inc.</cntorg>
</cntperp>
<cntpos>Metadata specialist</cntpos>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
<address>10210 Greenbelt Road, Suite 500</address>
<city>Lanham</city>
<state>Maryland</state>
<postal>20706</postal>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>301 867-2080</cntvoice>
<cntfax>301-867-2149.</cntfax>
<cntemail>solomon@gcmd.nasa.gov</cntemail>
</cntinfo>
</metc>
<metstdn>FGDC Biological Data Profile of the Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
<metstdv>FGDC-STD-001.1-1999</metstdv>
</metainfo>
<mercury><begdate>19400101</begdate><enddate>20090328</enddate><htmlurl>http://mercury.ornl.gov/metadata/nbii/html/nbii/www.nbii.gov_metadata_mdata_CSIRO_csiro_d_ausfishcollection.html</htmlurl><LTER-Site>nbii</LTER-Site></mercury></metadata>
