<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<metadata><Source>http://www.nbii.gov/metadata/mdata/brd-bib/usgs_brd_fresc_b_wiflfood.sgml</Source>
<idinfo>
<citation>
<citeinfo>
<origin>Drost, C.A., E.H. Paxton, M.K. Sogge, and M.J. Whitfield</origin>
<pubdate>Unpublished Material</pubdate>
<title>Food habits of the endangered southwestern willow flycatcher. Final report to the U.S. Bureau of Reclamation, Salt Lake City</title>
<geoform>unpublished report</geoform>
<pubinfo>
<pubplace>Flagstaff, AZ</pubplace>
<publish>USGS Forest and Rangeland Ecosystem Science Center, Colorado Plateau Field Station</publish>
</pubinfo>
<othercit>
Science Information System Project #: 75-3B
Publication Control #: 826
</othercit>
</citeinfo>
</citation>
<descript>
<abstract>The southwestern willow flycatcher (Empidonax traillii extimus) is a small insectivorous songbird that breeds in dense riparian habitats across the southwestern United States. Once locally common and widely distributed, the flycatcher has suffered dramatic population declines during the 20th century, primarily due to extensive riparian habitat loss and modification. Recent extensive surveys suggest that only 300-500 breeding pairs remain in the Southwest. Prior to being listed as an endangered species in 1995, the southwestern willow flycatcher was seldom studied, and as a result there was a dearth of information on the bird's basic ecology, natural history, distribution, and status. Prior to this study, there had been no research quantifying the composition of the diet of this insectivorous bird. The southwestern willow flycatcher food study is designed to answer questions directly related to the composition of its insect prey items, with emphasis on comparison of food habits in native vegetation versus exotic-dominated vegetation.</abstract>
<purpose>Reporting research results</purpose>
<supplinf>
Extent of item: 35pp
Illustrative Matter:  tables, graphs, maps, and photos
</supplinf>
</descript>
<timeperd>
<timeinfo>
<sngdate>
<caldate>2000</caldate>
</sngdate>
</timeinfo>
<current>publication date</current>
</timeperd>
<status>
<progress>Complete</progress>
<update>None planned</update>
</status>
<spdom>
<descgeog>Range of the southwestern willow flycatcher</descgeog>
<bounding>
<westbc>-114.82</westbc>
<eastbc>-109.17</eastbc>
<northbc>37.33</northbc>
<southbc>31.33</southbc>
</bounding>
</spdom>
<keywords>
<theme>
<themekt>Science Information System Controlled Vocabulary</themekt>
<themekey>Birds</themekey>
<themekey>Endangered Species</themekey>
<themekey>Populations</themekey>
<themekey>Ecosystem Science</themekey>
<themekey>Monitoring</themekey>
</theme>
</keywords>
<taxonomy>
<keywtax>
<taxonkt>none</taxonkt>
<taxonkey>birds</taxonkey>
<taxonkey>Empidonax traillii extimus</taxonkey>
<taxonkey>Southwestern Willow Flycatcher</taxonkey>
</keywtax>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Kingdom</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Animalia</taxonrv>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Phylum</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Chordata</taxonrv>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Sub Phylum</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Vertebrata</taxonrv>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Class</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Aves</taxonrv>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Order</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Passeriformes</taxonrv>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Family</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Tyrannidae</taxonrv>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Genus</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Empidonax</taxonrv>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Species</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Empidonax traillii extimus</taxonrv>
<common>Southwestern Willow Flycatcher</common>
</taxoncl>
</taxoncl>
</taxoncl>
</taxoncl>
</taxoncl>
</taxoncl>
</taxoncl>
</taxoncl>
</taxonomy>
<accconst>None</accconst>
<useconst>None</useconst>
<ptcontac>
<cntinfo>
<cntperp>
<cntper>Sogge, Mark</cntper>
<cntorg>USGS Forest and Rangeland Ecosystem Science Center; Colorado Plateau Field Station</cntorg>
</cntperp>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
<address>Northern Arizona University, PO Box 5614 BLDG 24</address>
<city>Flagstaff</city>
<state>AZ</state>
<postal>86011-5614</postal>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>520-556-7466</cntvoice>
<cntemail>mark.sogge@nau.edu</cntemail>
</cntinfo>
</ptcontac>
</idinfo>
<distinfo>
<distrib>
<cntinfo>
<cntorgp>
<cntorg>Olendorff Library</cntorg>
</cntorgp>
<cntpos>Librarian</cntpos>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
<address>
USGS FRESC Snake River Field Station
970 Lusk Street
</address>
<city>Boise</city>
<state>ID</state>
<postal>83706</postal>
<country>USA</country>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>208 426-5218</cntvoice>
<cntfax>208 426-5210</cntfax>
</cntinfo>
</distrib>
<resdesc>Publication Control #: 826</resdesc>
<distliab>
The USGS Forest and Rangeland Ecosystem Science Center and its research partners make every effort to provide and maintain accurate, complete, usable, and timely information. However, some USGS data and information may, of necessity, be preliminary in nature. These data and information are provided with the understanding that they are not guaranteed to be correct or complete. Users are cautioned to consider carefully the provisional nature of these data and information before using them for decisions that concern personal or public safety or the conduct of business that involves substantial monetary or operational consequences. It is also strongly recommended that careful attention be paid to the contents of the metadata file associated with these data and information. Conclusions drawn from, or actions undertaken on the basis of, such data and information are the sole responsibility of the user.
USGS-authored or produced data and information are in the public domain. Whereas the content of many USGS publications and other information resources are in the public domain, some USGS products contain material that is copyrighted by others and used by the USGS with permission. Users of this information may need to obtain permission from the copyright owner for other uses. Furthermore, some non-USGS data, products, and information referred to may be protected under U.S. and foreign copyright laws. Users may need to obtain permission from the copyright owner to acquire, use, reproduce, or distribute these materials. It is the sole responsibility of the user of the information to secure all necessary permission.
</distliab>
<stdorder>
<nondig>Publications are available as reprints, reports, pamphlets, or brochures.</nondig>
<fees>None</fees>
<ordering>Request specific publications by reference number.</ordering>
</stdorder>
</distinfo>
<metainfo>
<metd>20010530</metd>
<metc>
<cntinfo>
<cntorgp>
<cntorg>Olendorff Library</cntorg>
</cntorgp>
<cntpos>Librarian</cntpos>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
<address>
USGS FRESC Snake River Field Station
970 Lusk Street
</address>
<city>Boise</city>
<state>ID</state>
<postal>83706</postal>
<country>USA</country>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>208 426-5218</cntvoice>
<cntfax>208 426-5210</cntfax>
</cntinfo>
</metc>
<metstdn>FGDC Biological Data Profile of the Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
<metstdv>FGDC-STD-001.1-1999</metstdv>
</metainfo>
<mercury><begdate>20000101</begdate><enddate>20001231</enddate><htmlurl>http://mercury.ornl.gov/metadata/nbii/html/brd/www.nbii.gov_metadata_mdata_brd-bib_usgs_brd_fresc_b_wiflfood.html</htmlurl><LTER-Site>brd</LTER-Site></mercury></metadata>
