<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<metadata><Source>http://www.nbii.gov/metadata/mdata/brd-bib/usgs_brd_fresc_b_pub1052.sgml</Source>
<idinfo>
<citation>
<citeinfo>
<origin>Humphrey, L.D. and D.A. Pyke</origin>
<pubdate>2001</pubdate>
<title>Ramet spacing of Elymus lanceolatus (thickspike wheatgrass) in response to neighbor density</title>
<geoform>Journal article</geoform>
<serinfo>
<sername>Canadian Journal of Botany</sername>
<issue>73:1122-1126</issue>
</serinfo>
<othercit>
Science Information System Project #: 7023
Publication Control #: 1052
</othercit>
</citeinfo>
</citation>
<descript>
<abstract>When resources that plants depend on are scarce, many plants explore their surroundings for resource-rich patches.  Scientists have documented the ability of plants to selectively place ramets (offspring produced asexually or vegetatively) closer to the parent in resource-rich areas, while long exploratory spacers between the parent and offspring are produced in resource-poor patches.  This paper investigates whether or not thickspike wheatgrass (Elymus lanceolatus), a native to the western United States that reproduces by rhizomes (underground stems), would show the same foraging response to experimentally created high- and low-nutrient patches with varying neighbor densities. The results show that thickspike wheatgrass reduced spacing of ramets at higher densities, which was opposite of the expected response.  It is suggested that reduced spacing of exploratory rhizomes at high densities may have occurred because the availability of vacant soil patches was too low to provide sufficient resources for the production of exploratory rhizomes.</abstract>
<purpose>Reporting research results</purpose>
<supplinf>
Extent of item: 4pp
Illustrative Matter: graphs
</supplinf>
</descript>
<timeperd>
<timeinfo>
<sngdate>
<caldate>2001</caldate>
</sngdate>
</timeinfo>
<current>publication date</current>
</timeperd>
<status>
<progress>Complete</progress>
<update>None planned</update>
</status>
<spdom>
<descgeog>Plants were collected in Oregon, Washington, and Idaho</descgeog>
<bounding>
<westbc>-125</westbc>
<eastbc>-111</eastbc>
<northbc>49</northbc>
<southbc>42</southbc>
</bounding>
</spdom>
<keywords>
<theme>
<themekt>NBII Biocomplexity Thesaurus</themekt>
<themekey>Grasslands</themekey>
<themekey>Rangelands</themekey>
<themekey>Terrestrial ecosystems</themekey>
<themekey>Plants</themekey>
</theme>
</keywords>
<taxonomy>
<keywtax>
<taxonkt>None</taxonkt>
<taxonkey>Elymus lanceolatus</taxonkey>
<taxonkey>thickspike wheatgrass</taxonkey>
</keywtax>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Kingdom</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Plantae</taxonrv>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Division</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Magnoliophyta</taxonrv>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Class</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Liliopsida</taxonrv>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Order</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Cyperales</taxonrv>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Family</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Poaceae</taxonrv>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Genus</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Elymus</taxonrv>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Species</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Elymus lanceolatus</taxonrv>
<common>thickspike wheatgrass</common>
</taxoncl>
</taxoncl>
</taxoncl>
</taxoncl>
</taxoncl>
</taxoncl>
</taxoncl>
</taxonomy>
<accconst>None</accconst>
<useconst>None</useconst>
<ptcontac>
<cntinfo>
<cntorgp>
<cntorg>Olendorff Library</cntorg>
</cntorgp>
<cntpos>Librarian</cntpos>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
<address>
USGS FRESC Snake River Field Station
970 Lusk Street
</address>
<city>Boise</city>
<state>ID</state>
<postal>83706</postal>
<country>USA</country>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>208 426-5218</cntvoice>
<cntfax>208 426-5210</cntfax>
<cntemail>fresc_outreach@usgs.gov</cntemail>
</cntinfo>
</ptcontac>
</idinfo>
<distinfo>
<distrib>
<cntinfo>
<cntorgp>
<cntorg>Olendorff Library</cntorg>
</cntorgp>
<cntpos>Librarian</cntpos>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
<address>
USGS FRESC Snake River Field Station
970 Lusk Street
</address>
<city>Boise</city>
<state>ID</state>
<postal>83706</postal>
<country>USA</country>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>208 426-5218</cntvoice>
<cntfax>208 426-5210</cntfax>
<cntemail>fresc_outreach@usgs.gov</cntemail>
</cntinfo>
</distrib>
<resdesc>Publication Control #: 1052</resdesc>
<distliab>
The USGS Forest and Rangeland Ecosystem Science Center and its research partners make every effort to provide and maintain accurate, complete, usable, and timely information. However, some USGS data and information may, of necessity, be preliminary in nature. These data and information are provided with the understanding that they are not guaranteed to be correct or complete. Users are cautioned to consider carefully the provisional nature of these data and information before using them for decisions that concern personal or public safety or the conduct of business that involves substantial monetary or operational consequences. It is also strongly recommended that careful attention be paid to the contents of the metadata file associated with these data and information. Conclusions drawn from, or actions undertaken on the basis of, such data and information are the sole responsibility of the user.
USGS-authored or produced data and information are in the public domain. Whereas the content of many USGS publications and other information resources are in the public domain, some USGS products contain material that is copyrighted by others and used by the USGS with permission. Users of this information may need to obtain permission from the copyright owner for other uses. Furthermore, some non-USGS data, products, and information referred to may be protected under U.S. and foreign copyright laws. Users may need to obtain permission from the copyright owner to acquire, use, reproduce, or distribute these materials. It is the sole responsibility of the user of the information to secure all necessary permission.
</distliab>
<stdorder>
<nondig>Publications are available as reprints, reports, pamphlets, or brochures.</nondig>
<fees>None</fees>
<ordering>Request specific publications by reference number.</ordering>
</stdorder>
</distinfo>
<metainfo>
<metd>20050325</metd>
<metrd>20011221</metrd>
<metc>
<cntinfo>
<cntorgp>
<cntorg>Olendorff Library</cntorg>
</cntorgp>
<cntpos>Librarian</cntpos>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
<address>
USGS FRESC Snake River Field Station
970 Lusk Street
</address>
<city>Boise</city>
<state>ID</state>
<postal>83706</postal>
<country>USA</country>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>208 426-5218</cntvoice>
<cntfax>208 426-5210</cntfax>
<cntemail>fresc_outreach@usgs.gov</cntemail>
</cntinfo>
</metc>
<metstdn>FGDC Biological Data Profile of the Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
<metstdv>FGDC-STD-001.1-1999</metstdv>
</metainfo>
<mercury><begdate>20010101</begdate><enddate>20011231</enddate><htmlurl>http://mercury.ornl.gov/metadata/nbii/html/brd/www.nbii.gov_metadata_mdata_brd-bib_usgs_brd_fresc_b_pub1052.html</htmlurl><LTER-Site>brd</LTER-Site></mercury></metadata>
