<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<metadata><Source>http://www.nbii.gov/metadata/mdata/CBI/usgs_brd_cbi_d_efmofieldpoints.sgml</Source>
<idinfo>
<citation>
<citeinfo>
<origin>U.S. Geological Survey, Upper Midwest Environmental Sciences Center, 2630 Fanta Reed Road, La Crosse, Wisconsin 54603</origin>
<pubdate>20050131</pubdate>
<title>Vegetation Plot Sampling Spatial Database for the Effigy Mounds National Monument Vegetation Mapping Project</title>
<edition>Final</edition>
<geoform>maps data</geoform>
<serinfo>
<sername>USGS-NPS Vegetation Mapping Program</sername>
<issue>Effigy Mounds NM Vegetation Mapping Project</issue>
</serinfo>
<pubinfo>
<pubplace>Denver, Colorado</pubplace>
<publish>U.S. Geological Survey, Center for Biological Informatics</publish>
</pubinfo>
<othercit>This spatial database was prepared by the U.S. Geological Survey Upper Midwest Environmental Sciences Center for the USGS-NPS Vegetation Mapping Program. NatureServe provided ecological and vegetation classification support.</othercit>
<onlink>http://biology.usgs.gov/npsveg/efmo/fielddata.html</onlink>
</citeinfo>
</citation>
<descript>
<abstract>The U.S. Geological Survey Upper Midwest Environmental Sciences Center (UMESC) has produced a vegetation spatial database coverage (vegetation map) for the Effigy Mounds National Monument (EFMO) Vegetation Mapping Project, USGS-NPS Vegetation Mapping Program (VMP). The vegetation map shows the locations of plant communities (associations) at EFMO and immediate surroundings. To develop the plant community classification, vegetation samples were collected and analyzed, identifying 15 plant communities of the National Vegetation Classification System (NVCS). (2 more plant communities, however, were identified using accuracy assessment field data, making 17 total plant communities for the EFMO vegetation mapping project.) Ecologists and botanists from UMESC, under the direction of NatureServe, collected 63 vegetation plot samples, 55 collected in 2001 and 8 more in 2002. The UMESC and NatureServe performed ordination analysis to the sampling data. Plant communities of EFMO are defined and described at the local and global scale. (Local descriptions were written for only those 15 associations supported with plot data.) The UMESC has generated a spatial database showing the locations of all 63 vegetation plot samples. Selected field data items extracted from the project's PLOTS database are also included.</abstract>
<purpose>The vegetation plot sampling spatial database coverage provides spatially referenced locations of vegetation plot samples. These plot samples were collected to develop the vegetation classification for the EFMO Vegetation Mapping Project, USGS-NPS VMP (see Cross Reference at the end of this section for more information on the vegetation map, Project, and the VMP). This metadata report supports not only the vegetation field plot spatial database coverage, but also exported database sets (dBASE IV) from the project's PLOTS database of physical descriptions and species listing for each vegetation sample. For documentation, however, on the analysis methods and results, including the ordination process, see the EFMO Project Report.</purpose>
<supplinf>The vegetation plot sampling spatial database is a geo-spatial point coverage projected in Universal Transverse Mercator (UTM), Zone 15, using the North American Datum of 1983 (NAD83). Although only select fields from the PLOTS database are included, complete data for each vegetation sampling plot are included in the project's PLOTS database. --- The dBASE IV spreadsheet representing physical descriptions (exported from the project's PLOTS database) contains all items of the physical field data collected for each sample. Complete data for all vegetation samples are preserved on hard copy data sheets, and digitally within the project's PLOTS database.  (previous geoform was 'vector digital data')</supplinf>
</descript>
<timeperd>
<timeinfo>
<sngdate>
<caldate>200501</caldate>
</sngdate>
</timeinfo>
<current>publication date</current>
</timeperd>
<status>
<progress>Complete</progress>
<update>None planned</update>
</status>
<spdom>
<bounding>
<westbc>-91.230154</westbc>
<eastbc>-91.152381</eastbc>
<northbc>43.110846</northbc>
<southbc>42.936392</southbc>
</bounding>
<descgeog>Effigy Mounds National Monument in northeast Iowa, including the Yellow River and Sny Magill Units, and extended environs.</descgeog>
</spdom>
<keywords>
<theme>
<themekt>None</themekt>
<themekey>Digital Spatial Database</themekey>
<themekey>Vegetation Field Plot</themekey>
<themekey>Vegetation Sample</themekey>
<themekey>PLOTS Database System</themekey>
<themekey>Vegetation</themekey>
<themekey>Vegetation Map</themekey>
<themekey>National Vegetation Classification Standard</themekey>
<themekey>National Vegetation Classification System</themekey>
<themekey>U.S. National Vegetation Classification</themekey>
<themekey>International Vegetation Classification</themekey>
<themekey>NVCS</themekey>
<themekey>USNVC</themekey>
<themekey>National Park</themekey>
<themekey>GPS</themekey>
<themekey>GIS</themekey>
<themekey>Field Data</themekey>
<themekey>Effigy Mounds National Monument Vegetation Mapping Project</themekey>
<themekey>USGS-NPS Vegetation Mapping Program</themekey>
</theme>
<place>
<placekt>None</placekt>
<placekey>Effigy Mounds National Monument</placekey>
<placekey>EFMO</placekey>
<placekey>Yellow River</placekey>
<placekey>Sny Magill</placekey>
<placekey>Harpers Ferry</placekey>
<placekey>Marquette</placekey>
<placekey>Allamakee County</placekey>
<placekey>Clayton County</placekey>
<placekey>Iowa</placekey>
<placekey>USA</placekey>
</place>
</keywords>
<accconst>GIS software.</accconst>
<useconst>1) Those using the spatial database should understand the data and determine for themselves the fitness of the data prior to use. 2) For publication and dissemination, citations or credit should be given to the U.S. Geological Survey Center for Biological Informatics, the National Park Service, the U.S. Geological Survey Upper Midwest Environmental Sciences Center, and NatureServe. 3) Mention of trade names or commercial products in this metadata report does not constitute endorsement or recommendation for use by the U.S. Department of the Interior, U.S. Geological Survey.</useconst>
<ptcontac>
<cntinfo>
<cntorgp>
<cntorg>USGS-NPS Vegetation Mapping Program Coordinator</cntorg>
</cntorgp>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
<address>U.S. Geological Survey, Center for Biological Informatics, MS 302, Room 8000, Building 810, Denver Federal Center</address>
<city>Denver</city>
<state>Colorado</state>
<postal>80225</postal>
<country>USA</country>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>(303) 202-4220</cntvoice>
<cntfax>(303) 202-4219</cntfax>
<cntemail>gs-b-npsveg@usgs.gov</cntemail>
</cntinfo>
</ptcontac>
<browse>
<browsen>&lt;http://biology.usgs.gov/npsveg/efmo/images/efmoplot.jpg&gt;</browsen>
<browsed>Locations of accuracy assessment sites; low resolution for web browsing.</browsed>
<browset>JPG</browset>
</browse>
<datacred>The USGS Upper Midwest Environmental Sciences Center and NatureServe.</datacred>
<native>ESRI ArcView GIS 3.3; ESRI ArcInfo Workstation 9.0; ESRI ArcCatalog 9.0.0.535; Microsoft Windows 2000 Version 5.0 (Build 2195) Service Pack 4.</native>
<crossref>
<citeinfo>
<origin>U.S. Geological Survey, Upper Midwest Environmental Sciences Center, 2630 Fanta Reed Road, La Crosse, Wisconsin 54603</origin>
<pubdate>20050131</pubdate>
<title>Effigy Mounds National Monument Vegetation Mapping Project</title>
<geoform>document</geoform>
<serinfo>
<sername>USGS-NPS Vegetation Mapping Program</sername>
<issue>Effigy Mounds NM Vegetation Mapping Project</issue>
</serinfo>
<pubinfo>
<pubplace>Denver, Colorado</pubplace>
<publish>U.S. Geological Survey, Center for Biological Informatics</publish>
</pubinfo>
<othercit>The Effigy Mounds National Monument (EFMO) Vegetation Mapping Project is an initiative of the U.S. Geological Survey (USGS)-National Park Service (NPS) Vegetation Mapping Program (VMP). (For more information on VMP, see larger work citation below.) The goals of the project are to adequately describe and map plant communities of EFMO and immediate surroundings and to provide the NPS Inventory and Monitoring (I&amp;M) Program, resource managers, and biological researchers with useful baseline vegetation information. The USGS Upper Midwest Environmental Sciences Center (UMESC) in La Crosse, Wisconsin, and the Minneapolis Office of NatureServe in Minneapolis, Minnesota, have mapped and classified the existing plant communities at EFMO and extended surroundings. --- Common to all VMP mapping projects, the three major components of the EFMO Vegetation Mapping Project are vegetation classification, vegetation mapping, and map accuracy assessment. Two sets of aerial photographs were collected during summer and fall of 2000, and the mapping project was officially inaugurated spring 2001 with a scoping meeting where partners discussed the project's objectives, goals, and methods. Photointerpreters, ecologists, and botanists collaborated to describe National Vegetation Classification System (NVCS) plant associations (communities) and determine how best to map them using the aerial photographs. Plant community descriptions were derived from analyses of vegetation sampling data at EFMO. These plant communities, along with NVCS Formation vegetation units depicting human disturbance and cultivated lands and with units describing human-made structures, were interpreted and mapped using aerial photographs and mirror stereoscopes. Spatial database coverages were produced of the Yellow River and Sny Magill units and their respective environs using state-of-the-art photogrammetric and GIS software. An accuracy assessment of the map coverages were performed on map classes representing NVCS plant communities, with results exceeding VMP standards. --- The EFMO project delivers many geospatial and vegetation data products in hard copy and digital formats, including an in-depth project summary report discussing methods and results, plant community descriptions and dichotomous key, representative ground photos of plant communities, a database containing the plot samples and accuracy assessment, field data sheets, aerial photograph prints and images (including geo-referenced photo mosaics), map classification and descriptions, and spatial coverages and maps of plant communities, fieldwork locations, aerial photo indexes, and project boundaries (each supported with metadata reports). All geospatial products are in Universal Transverse Mercator projection, Zone 15, using North American Datum of 1983. More VMP information and products of completed park mapping projects are on the Internet at &lt;http://biology.usgs.gov/npsveg&gt;.</othercit>
<onlink>http://biology.usgs.gov/npsveg/efmo/</onlink>
<lworkcit>
<citeinfo>
<origin>U.S. Geological Survey, Center for Biological Information</origin>
<pubdate>200304</pubdate>
<title>USGS-NPS Vegetation Mapping Program (May 2003)</title>
<geoform>document</geoform>
<serinfo>
<sername>USGS-NPS Vegetation Mapping Program</sername>
<issue>Overview</issue>
</serinfo>
<pubinfo>
<pubplace>Denver, Colorado</pubplace>
<publish>U.S. Geological Survey, Center for Biological Informatics</publish>
</pubinfo>
<othercit>Overview of USGS - NPS Vegetation Mapping Program (taken from http://biology.usgs.gov/npsveg/overview.html, May 2003): The USGS-NPS Vegetation Mapping Program is a cooperative effort by the U.S. Geological Survey (USGS) and the National Park Service (NPS) to classify, describe, and map vegetation communities in more than 270 national park units across the United States. This landmark program is both the first to provide national-scale descriptions of vegetation for a federal agency and the first to create national vegetation standards for its data products. Its goal is to meet specific information needs identified by the National Park Service. --- The vegetation mapping program is an important part of the NPS Inventory and Monitoring Program, a long-term effort to develop baseline data for all national park units that have a natural resource component. It is managed by the USGS Center for Biological Informatics, a unique information center designed to help scientists, land managers, the public, and others locate and apply biological information. --- Program activities are based on peer-reviewed, objective science. Comprehensive vegetation information is provided at national and regional levels, while also serving local management needs of individual parks. Stringent quality control procedures ensure that products are accurate and consistent for initial inventory purposes and replicable for monitoring purposes. The spatially enabled digital products produced by the program are available on the World Wide Web. --- Program scientists have developed data collection procedures for classification, mapping, accuracy assessment, and use of existing data. Program products meet Federal Geographic Data Committee standards for vegetation classification and metadata, and national standards for spatial accuracy and data transfer. Standards include a minimum mapping unit of 0.5 hectares and classification accuracy of 80% for each map class. Nature Serve, an important partner in the USGS-NPS Vegetation Mapping program, is the caretaker of the National Vegetation Classification System, which is used by the program to classify vegetation communities. --- A report of project methods and results is provided at completion of individual projects. Project results include a rich set of data and information for each park project, as follows: --- Spatial Data: Aerial photography, Map classification, Map classification description and key, Spatial database of vegetation communities, Hardcopy maps of vegetation communities, Metadata for spatial databases, Complete accuracy assessment of spatial data, Vegetation Information. --- Vegetation classification: Dichotomous field key of vegetation classes, Formal description for each vegetation class, Ground photos of vegetation classes, Field data in database format.</othercit>
<onlink>http://biology.usgs.gov/npsveg/</onlink>
</citeinfo>
</lworkcit>
</citeinfo>
</crossref>
<taxonomy>
<keywtax>
<taxonkt>None</taxonkt>
<taxonkey>National Vegetation Classification Standard</taxonkey>
<taxonkey>National Vegetation Classification System</taxonkey>
<taxonkey>NVCS</taxonkey>
<taxonkey>U.S. National Vegetation Classification</taxonkey>
<taxonkey>USNVC</taxonkey>
<taxonkey>International Vegetation Classification</taxonkey>
<taxonkey>Association</taxonkey>
<taxonkey>Plant Community</taxonkey>
</keywtax>
<taxonsys>
<classsys>
<classcit>
<citeinfo>
<origin>US Department of Agriculture, Natural Resources Conservation Service</origin>
<pubdate>199612</pubdate>
<title>The PLANTS Database (1996)</title>
<geoform>database</geoform>
<serinfo>
<sername>The Plants Database</sername>
<issue>December 1996</issue>
</serinfo>
<pubinfo>
<pubplace>National Plant Data Center, Baton Rouge, Louisiana</pubplace>
<publish>USDA, NRCS</publish>
</pubinfo>
<othercit>The Plants Database as of December 1996. USDA Natural Resources Conservation Service. Web address: http://plants.usda.gov/plants. Version used in the PLOTS Database System (1997).</othercit>
<onlink>http://plants.usda.gov/plants</onlink>
</citeinfo>
</classcit>
<classmod>This is the version of The PLANTS Database that is used in The Nature Conservancy's PLOTS Database System (Version 1.1, 1997).</classmod>
</classsys>
<taxonpro>The plant community classification and descriptions for the EFMO Vegetation Mapping Project were developed through the analyses of vegetation sampling data using ordination and clustering techniques via computer software. Vegetation field plot data were entered into the PLOTS Database System (TNC 1997), which uses the USDA NRCS PLANTS Database. This database is available for download at the USGS-NPS VMP web site. A listing of vegetation species recorded with these field plots is provided in the EFMO Project Report, also available at the VMP web site.</taxonpro>
</taxonsys>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Kingdom</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Plantae</taxonrv>
</taxoncl>
</taxonomy>
</idinfo>
<dataqual>
<attracc>
<attraccr>The various attributes within the spatial database were reviewed and checked for consistency with their original sources (digital data, data sheets), using a combination of manual and digital means.</attraccr>
</attracc>
<logic>All point features are unique with their own site attribute and X-Y (Easting-Northing) coordinates. There are no duplicate points.</logic>
<complete>All 63 vegetation plot samples are included in the spatial point coverage. X-Y coordinates are projected in UTM, Zone 15, using NAD83.</complete>
<posacc>
<horizpa>
<horizpar>X-Y coordinates of field data locations were collected using a Rockwell Precision Lightweight GPS Receiver (PLGR). Most points were successfully collected with positional accuracies ranging from +/- 5 to +/- 10 meters.</horizpar>
</horizpa>
</posacc>
<lineage>
<method>
<methtype>Field</methtype>
<methodid>
<methkt>None</methkt>
<methkey>Vegetation Sample</methkey>
<methkey>Vegetation Plot</methkey>
<methkey>Vegetation Analysis</methkey>
<methkey>Vegetation Classification</methkey>
<methkey>PLOTS Database System</methkey>
</methodid>
<methdesc>Field Methods for Vegetation Mapping derived for the USGS-NPS VMP. Modified and adapted to unique circumstances presented with the EFMO Vegetation Mapping Project.</methdesc>
<methcite>
<citeinfo>
<origin>The Nature Conservancy and the Environmental Systems Research Institute</origin>
<pubdate>199412</pubdate>
<title>NBS/NPS Vegetation Mapping Program: Field Methods for Vegetation Mapping (1994b)</title>
<edition>Final Draft</edition>
<geoform>document</geoform>
<serinfo>
<sername>USGS-NPS Vegetation Mapping Program</sername>
<issue>Program Documents and Standards</issue>
</serinfo>
<pubinfo>
<pubplace>Denver, Colorado</pubplace>
<publish>U.S. Geological Survey, Center for Biological Informatics</publish>
</pubinfo>
<othercit>The Nature Conservancy and the Environmental Systems Research Institute. 1994b.  NBS/NPS Vegetation Mapping Program: Field Methods for Vegetation Mapping. Prepared for the U.S. Department of the Interior, National Biological Survey and National Park Service. -- Section 5 contains the procedures for vegetation field plot sampling, Methodology modified to match unique characteristics and challenges.</othercit>
<onlink>http://biology.usgs.gov/npsveg/fieldmethods/index.html</onlink>
</citeinfo>
</methcite>
</method>
<srcinfo>
<srccite>
<citeinfo>
<origin>U.S. Geological Survey, Upper Midwest Environmental Sciences Center, 2630 Fanta Reed Road, La Crosse, Wisconsin 54603</origin>
<pubdate>20050131</pubdate>
<title>Vegetation Plot Sampling Spatial Database for the Effigy Mounds National Monument Vegetation Mapping Project</title>
<edition>Final</edition>
<geoform>vector digital data</geoform>
<serinfo>
<sername>USGS-NPS Vegetation Mapping Program</sername>
<issue>Effigy Mounds NM Vegetation Mapping Project</issue>
</serinfo>
<pubinfo>
<pubplace>Denver, Colorado</pubplace>
<publish>U.S. Geological Survey, Center for Biological Informatics</publish>
</pubinfo>
<othercit>This spatial database was prepared by the U.S. Geological Survey Upper Midwest Environmental Sciences Center for the USGS-NPS Vegetation Mapping Program. NatureServe provided ecological and vegetation classification support.</othercit>
<onlink>http://biology.usgs.gov/npsveg/efmo/</onlink>
</citeinfo>
</srccite>
<typesrc>digital database file</typesrc>
<srctime>
<timeinfo>
<sngdate>
<caldate>20050131</caldate>
</sngdate>
</timeinfo>
<srccurr>publication date</srccurr>
</srctime>
<srccitea>EFMO Vegetation Field Plot Spatial Database</srccitea>
<srccontr>Geo-spatial product showing locations of vegetation field sampling locations.</srccontr>
</srcinfo>
<srcinfo>
<srccite>
<citeinfo>
<origin>NatureServe</origin>
<pubdate>2003</pubdate>
<title>International Vegetation Classification (2003a)</title>
<geoform>database</geoform>
<pubinfo>
<pubplace>Arlington, Virginia</pubplace>
<publish>NatureServe</publish>
</pubinfo>
<othercit>NatureServe. 2003a. International Ecological Classification Standard: International Vegetation Classification. Central Databases. NatureServe, Arlington, Virginia, USA.</othercit>
<onlink>http://www.natureserve.org/</onlink>
</citeinfo>
</srccite>
<typesrc>online</typesrc>
<srctime>
<timeinfo>
<sngdate>
<caldate>2003</caldate>
</sngdate>
</timeinfo>
<srccurr>publication date</srccurr>
</srctime>
<srccitea>NVCS Floristic Classes (NatureServe 2003a)</srccitea>
<srccontr>Vegetation classification (floristic association and alliance types, 2003) defining natural/semi-natural vegetation types in the EFMO Yellow River and Sny Magill vegetation spatial database coverages.</srccontr>
</srcinfo>
<srcinfo>
<srccite>
<citeinfo>
<origin>The Nature Conservancy</origin>
<pubdate>1997</pubdate>
<title>PLOTS Database System (1997)</title>
<edition>Version 1.1</edition>
<geoform>computer program</geoform>
<pubinfo>
<pubplace>Arlington, Virginia</pubplace>
<publish>The Nature Conservancy</publish>
</pubinfo>
<othercit>Plant species taxonomy extracted from the December 1996 version of The PLANTS Database (USDA).</othercit>
</citeinfo>
</srccite>
<typesrc>computer program</typesrc>
<srctime>
<timeinfo>
<sngdate>
<caldate>1997</caldate>
</sngdate>
</timeinfo>
<srccurr>publication date</srccurr>
</srctime>
<srccitea>PLOTS (1997)</srccitea>
<srccontr>Computer software program used for vegetation data entry and subsequent export for vegetation analysis.</srccontr>
</srcinfo>
<procstep>
<procdesc>INTRODUCTION: --- A number of steps were involved to classify the vegetation at EFMO: 1) a draft classification list as a starting point for classification work, 2) collection of plot sampling data, 3) subsequent analyses for plant community identification, and 4) development of NVCS plant community descriptions. Refer to the EFMO Project Report for these details. --- The vegetation plot sampling spatial database provides the locations of all sampling sites along with select sampling information. The following describes the development of the vegetation plot sampling spatial database.</procdesc>
<procdate>2001-2004</procdate>
<proccont>
<cntinfo>
<cntorgp>
<cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, Upper Midwest Environmental Sciences Center</cntorg>
</cntorgp>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
<address>2630 Fanta Reed Road</address>
<city>La Crosse</city>
<state>Wisconsin</state>
<postal>54603</postal>
<country>USA</country>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>(608) 781-6451</cntvoice>
<cntfax>(608) 783-8058</cntfax>
<cntemail>URL address: http://www.umesc.er.usgs.gov/umesc_home.html</cntemail>
<hours>7:30 AM - 4:00 PM, M-F</hours>
<cntinst>Ask receptionist for national park mapping contact in geospatial applications branch.</cntinst>
</cntinfo>
</proccont>
</procstep>
<procstep>
<procdesc>FIELD METHODS: --- Of the 63 plots, 55 were collected in 2001. The remaining 8 plots were collected in 2002 (during accuracy assessment field data collection). Methods were derived from those in Section 5 of the USGS-NPS VMP Field Methods for Vegetation Mapping manual (TNC et al. 1994b). X-Y coordinates of each plot were collected using a Rockwell Precision Lightweight GPS Receiver (PLGR) unit with projection in UTM (Zone 15) using NAD83. Field data were entered into the PLOTS Database System, which was used to produce plot vegetation summaries and associated environmental information. Through analysis, the vegetation classification derived and local descriptions were written.</procdesc>
<procdate>2001-2002</procdate>
<srcprod>NVCS Floristic Classes (NatureServe 2003a)</srcprod>
</procstep>
<procstep>
<procdesc>SPATIAL DATABASE: --- Vegetation plot samples with their corresponding X-Y coordinates and selected physical description information were exported from the PLOTS database. The exported file was imported into ArcView GIS (Version 3.3) as an Event Theme using X-Y coordinates, and then converted to a Shapefile. In ArcGIS (ArcInfo Workstation ArcTools 9.0), the Shapefile was converted to an ArcInfo coverage, converted from single to double precision, projection defined to UTM (Zone 15) NAD83, and lastly packaged into an ArcInfo Export (.e00) file (no compression).</procdesc>
<srcused>NVCS Floristic Classes (NatureServe 2003a)</srcused>
<procdate>2004</procdate>
<srcprod>EFMO Vegetation Field Plot Spatial Database</srcprod>
</procstep>
<procstep>
<procdesc>DBASE IV EXPORTS: --- The physical descriptions dBASE IV spreadsheet contains all items of physical descriptions for each vegetation plot sample that is in the PLOTS database. The physical descriptions were exported from the database's Plots Table. The species list dBASE IV spreadsheet contains all items of species listing for each vegetation plot sample that is in the PLOTS database. The species list was exported from the database's Plots-Species Table.</procdesc>
<procdate>2004</procdate>
</procstep>
</lineage>
</dataqual>
<spdoinfo>
<indspref>Located in northeastern Iowa in Allamakee and Clayton counties, EFMO is adjacent to the Mississippi River in a topographically unique area known as the Paleozoic Plateau region. The EFMO headquarters is 3 miles north of Marquette, Iowa. The main section of EFMO, the Yellow River Unit, envelops the Yellow River near its confluence with the Mississippi River. The Sny Magill Unit is approximately 16 km (10 miles) south of headquarters within the Mississippi River floodplain.</indspref>
<direct>Vector</direct>
<ptvctinf>
<sdtsterm>
<sdtstype>Entity point</sdtstype>
<ptvctcnt>63</ptvctcnt>
</sdtsterm>
<sdtsterm>
<sdtstype>Point</sdtstype>
<ptvctcnt>4</ptvctcnt>
</sdtsterm>
</ptvctinf>
</spdoinfo>
<spref>
<horizsys>
<planar>
<gridsys>
<gridsysn>Universal Transverse Mercator</gridsysn>
<utm>
<utmzone>15</utmzone>
<transmer>
<sfctrmer>0.9996</sfctrmer>
<longcm>-93</longcm>
<latprjo>0</latprjo>
<feast>500000</feast>
<fnorth>0</fnorth>
</transmer>
</utm>
</gridsys>
<planci>
<plance>Coordinate Pair</plance>
<coordrep>
<absres>0.000032</absres>
<ordres>0.000032</ordres>
</coordrep>
<plandu>meters</plandu>
</planci>
</planar>
<geodetic>
<horizdn>North American Datum of 1983</horizdn>
<ellips>Geodetic Reference System 80</ellips>
<semiaxis>6378137</semiaxis>
<denflat>298.257222</denflat>
</geodetic>
</horizsys>
</spref>
<eainfo>
<detailed>
<enttyp>
<enttypl>efmo_plot.pat</enttypl>
<enttypd>ArcInfo attribute tables from the EFMO vegetation plot spatial database coverage. (Numbers &amp; dashes in front of Attribute Labels are added for sorting purposes; Attribute Labels are listed in the order they appear in the spatial database sets.)</enttypd>
<enttypds>Attribute tables developed by the USGS UMESC to describe the EFMO vegetation plot spatial database coverage, USGS-NPS VMP.</enttypds>
</enttyp>
<attr>
<attrlabl>01 - SHAPE</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Feature geometry.</attrdef>
<attrdefs>ESRI.</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<udom>Coordinates defining the features.</udom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>02 - AREA</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Area of feature in internal units squared.</attrdef>
<attrdefs>ESRI.</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<udom>Area is always zero for point coverages. Values are automatically generated.</udom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>03 - PERIMETER</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Perimeter of feature in internal units.</attrdef>
<attrdefs>ESRI.</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<udom>Perimeter is always zero for point coverages. Values are automatically generated.</udom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>04 - EFMO_PLOT#</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Internal feature number.</attrdef>
<attrdefs>ESRI.</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<udom>Sequential unique whole numbers that are automatically generated.</udom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>05 - EFMO_PLOT-ID</attrlabl>
<attrdef>User-defined feature number.</attrdef>
<attrdefs>ESRI.</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<udom>Sequential unique whole numbers that are automatically generated.</udom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>06 - PLOT_SITE</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Vegetation plot sampling site number.</attrdef>
<attrdefs>USGS UMESC.</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<udom>Sequential unique whole numbers manually generated by field crew.</udom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>07 - ASSN_NAME</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Association scientific name.</attrdef>
<attrdefs>NatureServe. 2003a. International Ecological Classification Standard: International Vegetation Classification. Central Databases. NatureServe, Arlington, VA.</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Acer saccharum - Tilia americana / Ostrya virginiana - Carpinus caroliniana Forest Association</edomv>
<edomvd>North-central Maple - Basswood Forest (association synonym name). NVCS Code: I.B.2.N.a.8, CEGL002062.</edomvd>
<edomvds>NatureServe.</edomvds>
</edom>
<edom>
<edomv>Fraxinus pennsylvanica - Ulmus americana - (Juglans nigra, Celtis occidentalis) Forest Association</edomv>
<edomvd>Ash - Elm - Walnut - Hackberry Semi-natural Forest (association synonym name). NVCS Code: I.B.2.N.a.47, CEGL005239.</edomvd>
<edomvds>NatureServe.</edomvds>
</edom>
<edom>
<edomv>Quercus alba - Quercus rubra - Carya ovata Glaciated Forest Association</edomv>
<edomvd>Midwestern White Oak - Red Oak Forest (association synonym name). NVCS Code: I.B.2.N.a.27, CEGL002068.</edomvd>
<edomvds>NatureServe.</edomvds>
</edom>
<edom>
<edomv>Quercus muehlenbergii - Quercus (alba, velutina) - (Juniperus virginiana var. virginiana) Bluff Woodland Association</edomv>
<edomvd>Chinquapin Oak Bluff Woodland (association synonym name). NVCS Code: II.B.2.N.a.21, CEGL002144.</edomvd>
<edomvds>NatureServe.</edomvds>
</edom>
<edom>
<edomv>Acer saccharinum - Ulmus americana - (Populus deltoides) Forest Association</edomv>
<edomvd>Silver Maple - Elm - (Cottonwood) Forest (association synonym name). NVCS Code: I.B.2.N.d.4, CEGL002586.</edomvd>
<edomvds>NatureServe.</edomvds>
</edom>
<edom>
<edomv>Andropogon gerardii - Sorghastrum nutans - (Sporobolus heterolepis) - Liatris spp. - Ratibida pinnata Herbaceous Vegetation Association</edomv>
<edomvd>Central Mesic Tallgrass Prairie (association synonym name). NVCS Code: V.A.5.N.a.2, CEGL002203.</edomvd>
<edomvds>NatureServe.</edomvds>
</edom>
<edom>
<edomv>Populus deltoides - Salix nigra Forest Association</edomv>
<edomvd>Eastern Cottonwood - Black Willow Forest (association synonym name). NVCS Code:  I.B.2.N.d.15, CEGL002018.</edomvd>
<edomvds>NatureServe.</edomvds>
</edom>
<edom>
<edomv>Salix interior Temporarily Flooded Shrubland Association</edomv>
<edomvd>Sandbar Willow Shrubland (association synonym name). NVCS Code: III.B.2.N.d.6, CEGL008562.</edomvd>
<edomvds>NatureServe.</edomvds>
</edom>
<edom>
<edomv>Cephalanthus occidentalis / Carex spp. Northern Shrubland Association</edomv>
<edomvd>Buttonbush Shrubland (association synonym name). NVCS Code: III.B.2.N.f.1, CEGL002190.</edomvd>
<edomvds>NatureServe.</edomvds>
</edom>
<edom>
<edomv>Phalaris arundinacea Eastern Herbaceous Vegetation Association</edomv>
<edomvd>Reed Canary Grass Eastern Marsh (association synonym name). NVCS Code: V.A.5.N.k.20, CEGL006044.</edomvd>
<edomvds>NatureServe.</edomvds>
</edom>
<edom>
<edomv>Schoenoplectus fluviatilis - Schoenoplectus spp. Herbaceous Vegetation Association</edomv>
<edomvd>River Bulrush Marsh (association synonym name). NVCS Code: V.A.5.N.k.26, CEGL002221.</edomvd>
<edomvds>NatureServe.</edomvds>
</edom>
<edom>
<edomv>Schoenoplectus tabernaemontani - Typha spp. - (Sparganium spp., Juncus spp.) Herbaceous Vegetation Association</edomv>
<edomvd>Bulrush - Cattail - Burreed Shallow Marsh (association synonym name). NVCS Code: V.A.5.N.k.33, CEGL006044.</edomvd>
<edomvds>NatureServe.</edomvds>
</edom>
<edom>
<edomv>Sagittaria latifolia - Leersia oryzoides Herbaceous Vegetation Association</edomv>
<edomvd>Arrowhead - Rice Cutgrass Marsh (association synonym name). NVCS Code: V.B.2.N.e.7, CEGL005240.</edomvd>
<edomvds>NatureServe.</edomvds>
</edom>
<edom>
<edomv>Potamogeton spp. - Ceratophyllum spp. Midwest Herbaceous Vegetation Association Midwest</edomv>
<edomvd>Pondweed Submerged Wetland (association synonym name). NVCS Code: V.C.2.N.a.14, CEGL002282.</edomvd>
<edomvds>NatureServe.</edomvds>
</edom>
<edom>
<edomv>Nelumbo lutea Herbaceous Vegetation Association</edomv>
<edomvd>American Lotus Aquatic Wetland (association synonym name). NVCS Code: V.C.2.N.a.100, CEGL004323.</edomvd>
<edomvds>NatureServe.</edomvds>
</edom>
<edom>
<edomv>Nuphar lutea ssp. advena - Nymphaea odorata Herbaceous Vegetation Association</edomv>
<edomvd>
Water Lily Aquatic Wetland (association synonym name). NVCS Code: V.C.2.N.a.102, CEGL002286.
Water Lily Aquatic Wetland (association synonym name). NVCS Code: V.C.2.N.a.14, CEGL002282.
</edomvd>
<edomvds>NatureServe.</edomvds>
</edom>
<edom>
<edomv>River Mud Flats Sparse Vegetation</edomv>
<edomvd>River Mud Flats (association synonym name). NVCS Code: VII.C.4.N.c.1, CEGL002314.</edomvd>
<edomvds>NatureServe.</edomvds>
</edom>
<codesetd>
<codesetn>Associations (plant communities) of Effigy Mounds National Monument.</codesetn>
<codesets>Associations are listed &amp; described in Appendix C: Plant Community Descriptions of Effigy Mounds National Monument, Project Report - January 2005, Effigy Mounds National Monument, USGS-NPS Vegetation Mapping Program.</codesets>
</codesetd>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>08 - ASSN_SNAME</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Association synonym name.</attrdef>
<attrdefs>NatureServe. 2003a. International Ecological Classification Standard: International Vegetation Classification. Central Databases. NatureServe, Arlington, VA.</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<codesetd>
<codesetn>Associations (plant communities) of Effigy Mounds National Monument.</codesetn>
<codesets>See Enumerated Domain Value Definition for 07 - ASSN_NAME. Also, associations are listed &amp; described in Appendix C: Plant Community Descriptions of Effigy Mounds National Monument, Project Report - January 2005, Effigy Mounds National Monument, USGS-NPS Vegetation Mapping Program.</codesets>
</codesetd>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>09 - ASSN_CEGL</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Community Element Global code.</attrdef>
<attrdefs>NatureServe. 2003a. International Ecological Classification Standard: International Vegetation Classification. Central Databases. NatureServe, Arlington, VA.</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<codesetd>
<codesetn>Community Element Global codes of Effigy Mounds National Monument.</codesetn>
<codesets>See Enumerated Domain Value Definition for 07 - ASSN_NAME. Also, Community Element Global codes are listed &amp; described in Appendix C: Plant Community Descriptions of Effigy Mounds National Monument, Project Report - January 2005, Effigy Mounds National Monument, USGS-NPS Vegetation Mapping Program.</codesets>
</codesetd>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>10 - LOCATION</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Location in reference to EFMO unit.</attrdef>
<attrdefs>USGS UMESC.</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<udom>Project-derived location descriptions providing general location in and around EFMO.</udom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>11 - QUAD_24K</attrlabl>
<attrdef>USGS 7.5-minute quadrangle (1:24,000-scale) of the field site location.</attrdef>
<attrdefs>USGS.</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Clayton</edomv>
<edomvd>7.5-minute (1:24,000-scale) Quadrangle.</edomvd>
<edomvds>USGS.</edomvds>
</edom>
<edom>
<edomv>Harpers Ferry</edomv>
<edomvd>7.5-minute (1:24,000-scale) Quadrangle.</edomvd>
<edomvds>USGS.</edomvds>
</edom>
<edom>
<edomv>Prairie du Chien</edomv>
<edomvd>7.5-minute (1:24,000-scale) Quadrangle.</edomvd>
<edomvds>USGS.</edomvds>
</edom>
<codesetd>
<codesetn>7.5-minute quadrangles.</codesetn>
<codesets>USGS.</codesets>
</codesetd>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>12 - GPS_TECH</attrlabl>
<attrdef>GPS receiver used to collect the ground coordinates, the projection and datum GPS coordinates collected in, and the GPS accuracy.</attrdef>
<attrdefs>USGS UMESC.</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<udom>Global explanation of the GPS_TECH Attribute Label item.</udom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>13 - X_EASTING</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Easting coordinate of field site location.</attrdef>
<attrdefs>USGS UMESC.</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<udom>Easting coordinate collected during field sampling.</udom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>14 - Y_NORTHING</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Northing coordinate of field site location.</attrdef>
<attrdefs>USGS UMESC.</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<udom>Northing coordinate collected during field sampling.</udom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>15 - PLOT_DATE</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Date field data was collected</attrdef>
<attrdefs>USGS UMESC.</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<udom>MM/DD/YYYY</udom>
</attrdomv>
<begdatea>20010710</begdatea>
<enddatea>20020905</enddatea>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>16 - GRND_PHOTO</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Ground photos collected of the field site.</attrdef>
<attrdefs>USGS UMESC.</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<udom>Ground photo digital image file; VP#:N, where # is the plot sample site number, and N is a unique number for multiple pictures of site.</udom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>17 - AIR_PHOTO</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Aerial photograph (October 9, 2000 CIR, 1:8,000-scale) of the field site location.</attrdef>
<attrdefs>USGS UMESC.</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<udom>Reflects the frame number of the original film transparency.</udom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
</detailed>
<overview>
<eaover>Items within the spatial database attribute tables include: 1) SHAPE - Feature geometry. 2) AREA - Area of feature in internal units squared. 3) PERIMETER - Perimeter of feature in internal units. 4) EFMO_PLOT# - Internal feature number. 5) EFMO_PLOT-ID - User-defined feature number. 6) PLOT_SITE - Vegetation plot sampling site number. 7) ASSN_NAME - Association scientific name. 8) ASSN_SNAME - Association synonym name. 9) ASSN_CEGL - Community Element Global code. 10) LOCATION - Location in reference to EFMO unit. 11) QUAD_24K - USGS 7.5-minute quadrangle (1:24,000-scale) of the field site location. 12) GPS_TECH - GPS receiver used to collect the ground coordinates, the projection and datum GPS coordinates collected in, and the GPS accuracy. 13) X_EASTING - Easting coordinate of field site location. 14) Y_NORTHING - Northing coordinate of field site location. 15) PLOT_DATE - Date field data was collected (yyyy/mm/dd). 16) GRND_PHOTO - Ground photos collected of the field site.17) AIR_PHOTO - Aerial photograph (October 9, 2000 CIR, 1:8,000-scale) of the field site location.</eaover>
<eadetcit>Various citations referencing Attribute Label items. Refer to individual Attributes within the Detailed Description Entity Type section for citations.</eadetcit>
</overview>
</eainfo>
<distinfo>
<distrib>
<cntinfo>
<cntorgp>
<cntorg>USGS-NPS Vegetation Mapping Program Coordinator</cntorg>
</cntorgp>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
<address>U.S. Geological Survey, Center for Biological Informatics, MS 302, Room 8000, Building 810, Denver Federal Center</address>
<city>Denver</city>
<state>Colorado</state>
<postal>80225</postal>
<country>USA</country>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>(303) 202-4220</cntvoice>
<cntfax>(303) 202-4219</cntfax>
<cntemail>gs-b-npsveg@usgs.gov</cntemail>
</cntinfo>
</distrib>
<resdesc>Downloadable Data</resdesc>
<distliab>Although these data have been processed successfully on a computer system at the U.S. Geological Survey, no warranty expressed or implied is made regarding the accuracy or utility of the data on any other system or for general or scientific purposes, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty. This disclaimer applies both to individual use of the data and aggregate use with other data. It is strongly recommended that these data are directly acquired from a U.S. Geological Survey server, and not indirectly through other sources which may have changed the data in some way. It is also strongly recommended that careful attention be paid to the contents of the metadata file associated with these data. The U.S. Geological Survey shall not be held liable for improper or incorrect use of the data described and/or contained herein. Mention of trade names or commercial products in this metadata report does not constitute endorsement or recommendation for use by the U. S. Department of the Interior, U. S. Geological Survey.</distliab>
<stdorder>
<digform>
<digtinfo>
<formname>HTML</formname>
</digtinfo>
<digtopt>
<onlinopt>
<computer>
<networka>
<networkr>http://biology.usgs.gov/npsveg/efmo/fielddata.html</networkr>
</networka>
</computer>
</onlinopt>
</digtopt>
</digform>
<fees>none</fees>
</stdorder>
</distinfo>
<metainfo>
<metd>20050131</metd>
<metrd>20050307</metrd>
<metc>
<cntinfo>
<cntorgp>
<cntorg>USGS-NPS Vegetation Mapping Program Coordinator</cntorg>
</cntorgp>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
<address>U.S. Geological Survey, Center for Biological Informatics, MS 302, Room 8000, Building 810, Denver Federal Center</address>
<city>Denver</city>
<state>Colorado</state>
<postal>80225</postal>
<country>USA</country>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>(303) 202-4220</cntvoice>
<cntfax>(303) 202-4219</cntfax>
<cntemail>gs-b-npsveg@usgs.gov</cntemail>
</cntinfo>
</metc>
<metstdn>Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata, 1998, Part 1: Biological Data Profile, 1999 (FGDC-STD-001.1-1999)</metstdn>
<metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1999</metstdv>
</metainfo>
<mercury><begdate>20050101</begdate><enddate>20050131</enddate><htmlurl>http://mercury.ornl.gov/metadata/nbii/html/nbii/www.nbii.gov_metadata_mdata_CBI_usgs_brd_cbi_d_efmofieldpoints.html</htmlurl><LTER-Site>nbii</LTER-Site></mercury></metadata>
