<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<metadata><Source>http://www.nbii.gov/metadata/mdata/brd-bib/usgs_brd_fresc_b_horsegraze.sgml</Source>
<idinfo>
<citation>
<citeinfo>
<origin>Beever, Erik A., and  Peter F. Brussard</origin>
<pubdate>20000701</pubdate>
<title>Examining ecological consequences of feral horse grazing using exclosures</title>
<geoform>Journal article</geoform>
<serinfo>
<sername>Western North American Naturalist</sername>
<issue>Vol. 60, No. 3: 236-254</issue>
</serinfo>
<othercit>
Science Information System Project #: none
Publication Control #: 785
</othercit>
</citeinfo>
</citation>
<descript>
<abstract>Although feral horses have inhabited western North America since the end of the 16th century, there has been little synecological research to quantitatively characterize how they interact with ecosystem components.  Because feral horses exhibit watering behavior markedly different from that of domestic cattle, it is particularly important to evaluate response of ecosystem elements near water sources to horse use.  To assess this response, we performed live trapping of small mammals and two-tiered vegetative sampling in two mountain ranges in central Nevada in the interior Great Basin, USA.  At low elevations, plots around horse-excluded springs exhibited notably greater plant species richness, percent cover, and abundance of grasses and shrubs, as well as more small mammal burrow entrances than plots at horse-grazed springs.  At high elevations, meadows protected from grazing exhibited maximum vegetation heights 2.8 times greater than vegetation grazed by horses only and 4.5 times greater than vegetation grazed by horses and cattle.  Species richness in quadrats was most different between the horse- and cattle-grazed meadow and its ungrazed counterpart, suggesting the possibility of synergistic effects of horse and cattle grazing in the same location.  This is the first Great Basin study to quantitatively investigate ecosystem consequences of feral horse use with exclosures and represents a first step in identifying factors that determine the magnitude of horse grazing impacts.</abstract>
<purpose>Reporting research results</purpose>
<supplinf>
Extent of item: 16 pp
Illustrative Matter:  tables, maps, graphs, and photos
</supplinf>
</descript>
<timeperd>
<timeinfo>
<sngdate>
<caldate>2000</caldate>
</sngdate>
</timeinfo>
<current>publication date</current>
</timeperd>
<status>
<progress>Complete</progress>
<update>None planned</update>
</status>
<spdom>
<descgeog>Clan Alpine Mountains [Shoshone Creek canyon], Churchill Co., west-central Nevada (39 degrees, 48-51 min N, 117 deg, 39-43 min W); Seven Troughs Range [Cow Creek], Pershing Co., central Nevada (40 deg, 35 min N, 118 deg, 46 min W)</descgeog>
<bounding>
<westbc>-118.767</westbc>
<eastbc>-117.65</eastbc>
<northbc>40.583</northbc>
<southbc>39.8</southbc>
</bounding>
</spdom>
<keywords>
<theme>
<themekt>Science Information System Controlled Vocabulary</themekt>
<themekey>Ecosystem Science</themekey>
<themekey>Grassland/Rangeland</themekey>
<themekey>Mammals</themekey>
<themekey>Populations</themekey>
<themekey>Wildlife</themekey>
</theme>
<theme>
<themekt>none</themekt>
<themekey>exclosures</themekey>
<themekey>vegetative comparisons</themekey>
</theme>
<place>
<placekt>none</placekt>
<placekey>Great Basin</placekey>
<placekey>Nevada</placekey>
<placekey>United States</placekey>
</place>
</keywords>
<taxonomy>
<keywtax>
<taxonkt>none</taxonkt>
<taxonkey>Equus caballus</taxonkey>
<taxonkey>feral horses</taxonkey>
</keywtax>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Kingdom</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Animalia</taxonrv>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Division</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Chordata</taxonrv>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Subdivision</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Vertebrata</taxonrv>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Class</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Mammalia</taxonrv>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Subclass</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Theria</taxonrv>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Infraclass</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Eutheria</taxonrv>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Order</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Rodentia</taxonrv>
</taxoncl>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Order</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Perissodactyla</taxonrv>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Family</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Equidae</taxonrv>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Genus</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Equus</taxonrv>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Species</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Equus caballus</taxonrv>
</taxoncl>
</taxoncl>
</taxoncl>
</taxoncl>
</taxoncl>
</taxoncl>
</taxoncl>
</taxoncl>
</taxoncl>
</taxoncl>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Kingdom</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Plantae</taxonrv>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Division</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Magnoliophyta</taxonrv>
<common>angiosperms</common>
<common>flowering plants</common>
</taxoncl>
</taxoncl>
</taxonomy>
<accconst>None</accconst>
<useconst>None</useconst>
<ptcontac>
<cntinfo>
<cntperp>
<cntper>Beever, Erik A.</cntper>
<cntorg>USGS Forest and Rangeland Ecosystem Science Center</cntorg>
</cntperp>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
<address>3200 SW Jefferson Way</address>
<city>Corvallis</city>
<state>OR</state>
<postal>97331</postal>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>541-758-7785</cntvoice>
<cntemail>erik_beever@usgs.gov</cntemail>
</cntinfo>
</ptcontac>
</idinfo>
<distinfo>
<distrib>
<cntinfo>
<cntorgp>
<cntorg>USGS Forest &amp; Rangeland Ecosystem Science Center (FRESC)</cntorg>
<cntper>Headquarters</cntper>
</cntorgp>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>Mailing and Physical Address</addrtype>
<address>
U.S. Geological Survey
Forest and Rangeland Ecosystem Science Center
3200 SW Jefferson Way
</address>
<city>Corvallis</city>
<state>Oregon</state>
<postal>97331</postal>
<country>USA</country>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>(541) 750-7307</cntvoice>
<cntemail>FRESC_Outreach@usgs.gov</cntemail>
</cntinfo>
</distrib>
<resdesc>Publication Control #: 785</resdesc>
<distliab>
The USGS Forest and Rangeland Ecosystem Science Center and its research partners make every effort to provide and maintain accurate, complete, usable, and timely information. However, some USGS data and information may, of necessity, be preliminary in nature. These data and information are provided with the understanding that they are not guaranteed to be correct or complete. Users are cautioned to consider carefully the provisional nature of these data and information before using them for decisions that concern personal or public safety or the conduct of business that involves substantial monetary or operational consequences. It is also strongly recommended that careful attention be paid to the contents of the metadata file associated with these data and information. Conclusions drawn from, or actions undertaken on the basis of, such data and information are the sole responsibility of the user.
USGS-authored or produced data and information are in the public domain. Whereas the content of many USGS publications and other information resources are in the public domain, some USGS products contain material that is copyrighted by others and used by the USGS with permission. Users of this information may need to obtain permission from the copyright owner for other uses. Furthermore, some non-USGS data, products, and information referred to may be protected under U.S. and foreign copyright laws. Users may need to obtain permission from the copyright owner to acquire, use, reproduce, or distribute these materials. It is the sole responsibility of the user of the information to secure all necessary permission.
</distliab>
<stdorder>
<nondig>Publications are available as reprints, reports, pamphlets, or brochures.</nondig>
<fees>None</fees>
<ordering>Request specific publications by reference number.</ordering>
</stdorder>
</distinfo>
<metainfo>
<metd>20010122</metd>
<metrd>20020912</metrd>
<metc>
<cntinfo>
<cntorgp>
<cntorg>USGS FRESC Snake River Field Station Olendorff Library</cntorg>
</cntorgp>
<cntpos>Library</cntpos>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
<address>970 Lusk Street</address>
<city>Boise</city>
<state>Idaho</state>
<postal>83706</postal>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>208 426-5218</cntvoice>
<cntfax>208 426-5210</cntfax>
<cntemail>kathy_mccoy@usgs.gov</cntemail>
</cntinfo>
</metc>
<metstdn>FGDC Biological Data Profile of the Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
<metstdv>FGDC-STD-001.1-1999</metstdv>
</metainfo>
<mercury><begdate>20000101</begdate><enddate>20001231</enddate><htmlurl>http://mercury.ornl.gov/metadata/nbii/html/brd/www.nbii.gov_metadata_mdata_brd-bib_usgs_brd_fresc_b_horsegraze.html</htmlurl><LTER-Site>brd</LTER-Site></mercury></metadata>
