<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<metadata><Source>http://www.nbii.gov/metadata/mdata/EPA/epa_t_bass.sgml</Source>
<idinfo>
<citation>
<citeinfo>
<origin>Craig Barber</origin>
<pubdate>200207</pubdate>
<title>Bioaccumulation and Aquatic System Simulator (BASS)</title>
<geoform>tools software</geoform>
<pubinfo>
<pubplace>Athens, Georgia</pubplace>
<publish>U.S. Environmental Protection Agency</publish>
</pubinfo>
<othercit>Programming Language(s): Fortran 95 (available from author on request) .</othercit>
<onlink>ftp://ftp.epa.gov/erdathens/</onlink>
</citeinfo>
</citation>
<descript>
<abstract>The Bioaccumulation and Aquatic System Simulator (BASS) is a Fortran 90 simulation model  that predicts the population and bioaccumulation dynamics of age-structured fish assemblages which are exposed to hydrophobic organic pollutants and class B and borderline metals that complex with sulfhydryl groups (e.g., cadmium, copper, lead, mercury, nickel, silver, and zinc). BASS's bioaccumulation algorithms are based on diffusion kinetics and are coupled to a process-based model for the growth of individual fish. The model's exchange algorithms consider both biological attributes of fishes and physico-chemical properties of the chemicals of concern that determine diffusive exchange across gill membranes and intestinal mucosa. Biological characteristics used by the model include the fish's gill morphometry, feeding and growth rate, and proximate composition (i.e., its fractional aqueous, lipid, and structural organic content). Relevant physico-chemical properties are the chemical's aqueous diffusivity, n-octanol/water partition coefficient (K_{ow}), and, for metals, binding coefficients to proteins and other organic matter. bass simulates the growth of individual fish using a standard mass balance, bioenergetic model (i.e., growth = ingestion - egestion - respiration - specific dynamic action - excretion). A fish's realized ingestion is calculated from its maximum consumption rate adjusted for the availability of prey of the appropriate size and taxonomy. The community's food web is specified by defining one or more foraging classes for each fish species based on  either its body weight, body length, or age. The dietary composition of each of these feeding classes is specified as a combination of benthos, incidental terrestrial insects, periphyton/attached algae, phytoplankton, zooplankton, and one or more fish species. Population dynamics are generated by predatory mortalities defined by community's food web and standing stocks, size dependent physiological mortality rates, the maximum longevity of species, and toxicological responses to chemical exposures. The model's temporal and spatial scales of resolution are a day and a hectare, respectively. Currently, BASS ignores the migration of fish into and out of the simulated hectare.  Source of abstract: http://www.epa.gov/athens/staff/members/barbermahlonc/index.html.</abstract>
<purpose>The purpose of the BASS model is to predict the population and bioaccumulation dynamics of age-structured fish assemblages.</purpose>
<supplinf>BASS version 2.2 is now under development. The following features have now been incorporated into the BASS model software: 1) Monthly or seasonal diets can be specified for any or all dietary/foraging classes of a species. For example, a summer diet for 0.1 to 2 kg largemouth bass might be diet(100&lt;w[gram]&lt;2000, june-august) = {benthos=30, bluegill=45,redear=25} 2) The average prey length for piscivous fish can be specified either as a linear function or as a "complementary" exponential function of the fish's body length, i.e., lp[cm] = a + b*L[cm] or lp[cm] = a + b*exp(-c*L[cm])3) The maximum prey length consumed by piscivous fish can now be specified by the user. Like the fish's average prey length, this parameter can be specified either as linear or as a "complementary" exponential function of the fish's body length. If not specified, BASS 2.2 assumes, as did BASS 2.1, that lp_max[cm] = 0.5*L[cm]. 4) Benthos, periphyton/attached algae, phytoplankton, and zooplankton can now be specified either as community forcing functions or as simulated state variables. The compartmental dynamics of these nonfish compartments have been initially formulated very simplistically, i.e., dY/dt = A - R - M - PF = (a-r-m)*Y - PF Where    Y is the compartment's biomass; A is the compartment's assimilation/feeding/photosynthesis; R and M are the compartment's respiration and physiological "mortality" which may conceptually include migration/ transport/ emergence; and PF is predation by fish. The specific rates a, r, and m are assumed to be temperature dependent allometric functions of the average size of individuals within the compartment. These average body sizes can be specified by the user as time dependent forcing functions. Any comments or suggestions regarding this formulation or alternative formulations would be appreciated. During the summer of 2003, size dependent stocking and harvesting options will be incorporated into the BASS software to allow analysis and simulation of managed sport fisheries. Currently, BASS version 2.2 and its updated GUI are planned to be available for distribution by late fall 2003.  Because BASS is simply one of several widely available bioaccumulation models, an obvious question is how does BASS's performance compare to that of other models? Although addressing this issue in general is a formidable task, Craig Barber has completed a manuscript that represents an important step toward addressing this issue. In particular, how does the performance of BASS's gill exchange algorithm compare to other bioconcentration models? This manuscript, which has now been accepted for publication by Environmental Toxicology and Chemistry, reviews the construction and performance of ten of the most widely cited gill exchange models including BASS's algorithm. If one would like a prepublication version of this paper in PDF format, please drop Craig Barber a line and he will email you one. If you have any recommendations regarding either the model software or GUI, please do not hesitate to contact Craig Barber by email or phone.   Information was obtained from M. Craig Barber, from http://eco.wiz.uni-kassel.de/model_db/mdb/bass.html.  (previous geoform was 'model')</supplinf>
</descript>
<timeperd>
<timeinfo>
<sngdate>
<caldate>200207</caldate>
</sngdate>
</timeinfo>
<current>publication date</current>
</timeperd>
<status>
<progress>In Work</progress>
<update>Continually</update>
</status>
<keywords>
<theme>
<themekt>none</themekt>
<themekey>aquatic</themekey>
<themekey>ecotoxicology</themekey>
<themekey>biogechemistry</themekey>
<themekey>population</themekey>
<themekey>community fish assemblage</themekey>
<themekey>ordinary differential equations</themekey>
<themekey>age-structured population</themekey>
<themekey>fish</themekey>
<themekey>growth</themekey>
<themekey>population dynamics</themekey>
<themekey>predator-prey</themekey>
<themekey>bioaccumulation</themekey>
<themekey>organic chemicals</themekey>
<themekey>metals</themekey>
</theme>
</keywords>
<taxonomy>
<keywtax>
<taxonkt>none</taxonkt>
<taxonkey>fish</taxonkey>
</keywtax>
<taxonsys>
<classsys>
<classcit>
<citeinfo>
<origin>Agencies listed below</origin>
<pubdate>2002</pubdate>
<title>Integrated Taxonomic Information System</title>
<geoform>Database</geoform>
<pubinfo>
<pubplace>Washington, D.C.</pubplace>
<publish>U.S. Department of Agriculture</publish>
</pubinfo>
<othercit>Department of Commerce, National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration (NOAA),  Department of Interior (DOI), Geological Survey (USGS), Environmental Protection Agency (EPA), Department of Agriculture (USDA), Agriculture Research Service (ARS) Natural Resources Conservation Service (NRCS) Smithsonian Institution National Museum of Natural History (NMNH).</othercit>
<onlink>http://www.itis.usda.gov/</onlink>
</citeinfo>
</classcit>
<classmod>none</classmod>
</classsys>
</taxonsys>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Kingdom</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Animalia</taxonrv>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Phylum</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Chordata</taxonrv>
<common>chordates</common>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Subphylum</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>vertebrata</taxonrv>
<common>vertebrates</common>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Superclass</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Osteichthyes</taxonrv>
<common>bony fish</common>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Class</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Actinopterygii</taxonrv>
<common>ray-finned fishes</common>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Subclass</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Neopterygii</taxonrv>
</taxoncl>
</taxoncl>
</taxoncl>
</taxoncl>
</taxoncl>
</taxoncl>
</taxonomy>
<accconst>none</accconst>
<useconst>none</useconst>
<ptcontac>
<cntinfo>
<cntperp>
<cntper>M. Craig Barber</cntper>
<cntorg>U.S. Environmental Protection Agency, Office of Pollution Prevention and Toxics</cntorg>
</cntperp>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
<address>960 College Station Road</address>
<city>Athens</city>
<state>Georgia</state>
<postal>30605</postal>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>706 355-8110</cntvoice>
<cntfax>706 355-8104</cntfax>
<cntemail>barber.craig@epa.gov</cntemail>
</cntinfo>
</ptcontac>
<native>Operating System(s): DOS</native>
<crossref>
<citeinfo>
<origin>Barber, M.C., L.A. Su&amp;aacute;rez, and R.R. Lassiter.</origin>
<pubdate>1991</pubdate>
<title>Modelling bioaccumulation of organic pollutants in fish with an application to PCBs in Lake Ontario salmonids</title>
<geoform>Journal article</geoform>
<serinfo>
<sername>Can. J. Fish. Aquat. Sci.</sername>
<issue>48:318-337</issue>
</serinfo>
<othercit>Can. J. Fish. Aquat. Sci. 48:318-337.</othercit>
</citeinfo>
</crossref>
<crossref>
<citeinfo>
<origin>Barber, M.C.</origin>
<pubdate>2001</pubdate>
<title>Bioaccumulation and Aquatic System Simulator (BASS) User's Manual</title>
<edition>Beta Test Version 2.1</edition>
<geoform>publication</geoform>
<serinfo>
<sername>EPA Publication</sername>
<issue>EPA 600/R-01/035</issue>
</serinfo>
<pubinfo>
<pubplace>Athens, Georgia</pubplace>
<publish>U.S. Environmental Protection Agency, Exposure Research Laboratory, Ecosystems Research Division</publish>
</pubinfo>
<othercit>Beta Test Version 2.1. U.S. Environmental Protection Agency, National Exposure Research Laboratory, Ecosystems Research Division, Athens, GA. EPA 600/R-01/035.</othercit>
</citeinfo>
</crossref>
<crossref>
<citeinfo>
<origin>Press, W.H., S.A. Teukolsky, W.T. Vetterling, and B.P. Flannery.</origin>
<pubdate>1992</pubdate>
<title>Numerical Recipes in FORTRAN</title>
<geoform>book</geoform>
<pubinfo>
<pubplace>Cambridge, United Kingdom</pubplace>
<publish>Cambridge Univ. Press</publish>
</pubinfo>
<othercit>pp 963.</othercit>
</citeinfo>
</crossref>
<crossref>
<citeinfo>
<origin>M. Craig Barber, ERD/NERL/ORD/USEPA, Athens, Georgia; Mike Galvin, Benjamin Daniel, Lisa Phillips, Kevin Weinrich, and Allen Rowell, CSC Corporation</origin>
<pubdate>Unknown</pubdate>
<title>BASS Graphical User Interface (GUI) beta test version 1.0 for BASS version 2.1</title>
<geoform>manual</geoform>
<pubinfo>
<pubplace>Athens, Georgia and Research Triangle Park, North Carolina</pubplace>
<publish>U.S. Environmental Protection Agency, Ecosystems Research Division and U.S. Environmental Protection Agency, Office of Research and Development, National Exposure Research Laboratory</publish>
</pubinfo>
</citeinfo>
</crossref>
</idinfo>
<dataqual>
<logic>not applicable</logic>
<complete>Numerical integration of BASS's differential equations can be performed using either an Euler or Runge-Kutta integrator. These methods offer users two distinctly different options with respect to software performance and execution. Although Euler methods may often allow for fast model execution, they cannot assess the accuracy of their integration. Runge-Kutta methods, on the other hand, can monitor the accuracy of their integration but at the cost of increased execution time. Fortunately, however, this additional computational burden can often be significantly reduced by employing adaptive step sizing. BASS's Runge-Kutta integrator, which is the model's default integrator, is patterned on the fifth-order Cash-Karp Runge-Kutta algorithm outlined by Press et. al. (1992).</complete>
<lineage>
<procstep>
<procdesc>not applicable</procdesc>
<procdate>not applicable</procdate>
</procstep>
</lineage>
</dataqual>
<eainfo>
<overview>
<eaover>
Input variables are broadly classified into three categories: simulation control parameters, chemical parameters, and fish parameters. Simulation control parameters provide information that is applicable to the simulation as a whole, e.g., length of the simulation, the ambient water temperature, nonfish standing stocks, and user output options.
Chemical parameters specify the chemical's physico-chemical properties (e.g., the chemical's molecular weight, molecular volume, n-octanol/water partition coefficient, etc.) and exposure concentrations in the environment (i.e., in water, sediment, benthos, insects, etc.). Fish parameters identify the fish's taxonomy (i.e., genus and species), feeding and metabolic demands, dietary composition,  predator-prey relationships, gill morphometrics, body composition, initial weight, initial whole body concentrations for each chemical, and initial population sizes.
The model's output includes: 1) Summaries of all model input parameters and simulation controls.
2) Tabulated annual summaries for the bioenergetics of individual fish by species and age class.
3) Tabulated annual summaries for the chemical bioaccumulation within individual fish by species and age class.
4) Tabulated annual summaries for the community level consumption, production, and mortality of each fish species by age class. 5) Plotted annual dynamics of selected model variables as requested by the user.
</eaover>
<eadetcit>U.S. Environmental Protection Agency</eadetcit>
</overview>
</eainfo>
<distinfo>
<distrib>
<cntinfo>
<cntperp>
<cntper>M. Craig Barber</cntper>
<cntorg>U.S. Environmental Protection Agency, Office of Pollution Prevention and Toxics</cntorg>
</cntperp>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
<address>960 College Station Road</address>
<city>Athens</city>
<state>Georgia</state>
<postal>30605</postal>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>706 355-8110</cntvoice>
<cntfax>706 355-8104</cntfax>
<cntemail>barber.craig@epa.gov</cntemail>
</cntinfo>
</distrib>
<distliab>Although these data have been processed successfully on a computer system at the U.S. Environmental Protection Agency, no warranty expressed or implied is made regarding the accuracy or utility of the data on any other system or for general or scientific purposes, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty. This disclaimer applies both to individual use of the data and aggregate use with other data.  It is strongly recommended that these data are directly acquired from a U.S. Environmental Protection Agency server, and not indirectly through other sources which may have changed the data in some way.  It is also strongly recommended that careful attention be paid to the contents of the metadata file associated with these data.  The U.S. Environmental Protectio Agency shall not be held liable for improper or incorrect use of the data described and/or contained herein.</distliab>
<stdorder>
<digform>
<digtinfo>
<formname>exe</formname>
</digtinfo>
<digtopt>
<onlinopt>
<computer>
<networka>
<networkr>ftp://ftp.epa.gov/erdathens</networkr>
</networka>
</computer>
</onlinopt>
</digtopt>
</digform>
<fees>None, if available online.</fees>
</stdorder>
<custom>As of June 16, 2003, the BASS bioaccumulation and community model is available through the anonymous USEPA FTP site - ftp://ftp.epa.gov/erdathens.  It will also be soon available from the Center for Exposure Assessment Modeling (CEAM) website  http://www.epa.gov/ceampubl/.</custom>
</distinfo>
<metainfo>
<metd>20030527</metd>
<metrd>20040711</metrd>
<metfrd>20040711</metfrd>
<metc>
<cntinfo>
<cntperp>
<cntper>Cheryl Solomon</cntper>
<cntorg>Science Systems and Applications, Inc.</cntorg>
</cntperp>
<cntpos>Metadata specialist</cntpos>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
<address>10210 Greenbelt Road, Suite 500</address>
<city>Lanham</city>
<state>Maryland</state>
<postal>20706</postal>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>301 867-2080</cntvoice>
<cntfax>301-867-2149.</cntfax>
<cntemail>solomon@gcmd.nasa.gov</cntemail>
</cntinfo>
</metc>
<metstdn>FGDC Biological Data Profile of the Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
<metstdv>FGDC-STD-001.1-1999</metstdv>
</metainfo>
<mercury><begdate>20020701</begdate><enddate>20020731</enddate><htmlurl>http://mercury.ornl.gov/metadata/nbii/html/nbii/www.nbii.gov_metadata_mdata_EPA_epa_t_bass.html</htmlurl><LTER-Site>nbii</LTER-Site></mercury></metadata>
