<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<metadata><Source>http://www.nbii.gov/metadata/mdata/brd-bib/usgs_brd_fresc_b_hnatbird.sgml</Source>
<idinfo>
<citation>
<citeinfo>
<origin>van Riper III, Charles, J. M. Scott</origin>
<pubdate>2001</pubdate>
<title>Limiting factors affecting Hawaiian native birds</title>
<geoform>Book chapter</geoform>
<othercit>
Science Information System Project #:5004126
Publication Control #:902
</othercit>
<lworkcit>
<citeinfo>
<origin>Scott, J.M., Shelia Conant, Charles van Riper</origin>
<pubdate>2001</pubdate>
<title>Evolution, ecology, conservation, and management of Hawaiian birds: a vanishing avifauna</title>
<geoform>book</geoform>
<pubinfo>
<pubplace>Lawrence, Kansas</pubplace>
<publish>Cooper Ornithological Society</publish>
</pubinfo>
<othercit>
Science Information System Project #:5004126
Publication Control #:960
</othercit>
</citeinfo>
</lworkcit>
</citeinfo>
</citation>
<descript>
<abstract>Hawaii is one of the most unique ecosystems on the planet, and the native birds personify that uniqueness. The role of disease is now being clearly elucidated in relationship to its impact on native Hawaiian birds. The most extensively studied protozoan parasites of birds are those that infect the blood. These include the genera Haemoproteus, Plasmodium, Leucocytozoon, and Trypanosoma. The effect of these protozoan parasites on the bird populations in Hawaii Islands is just starting to be known. The principal vector of avian malaria is known today to be Culex pipiens fatigans. This form of the night-flying mosquito was introduced into Hawaii Islands in 1827. Hippoboscid flies, almost worldwide in distribution, are known vectors of avian blood diseases. The flies feed on the blood of the host and are involved in the transmission of certain diseases, including Trypanosoma avium and Haemoproteus columbae. The role hippoboscid flies play in disease transmission to native avifauna in Hawaii Islands has never been determined. Acarina have frequently been found on birds in Hawaii Islands, a known vectors of avian maladies. They settle in the feathers, on exposed skin parts, and in nasal passages. 10 families of mites have also been reported parasitizing avian hosts. Objectives: 1. To determine susceptibility of native Hawaiian birds to malarial parasites. 2. To determine if the night-flying mosquito (Culex pipiens) is the vector of avian malaria 3. To determine methods of transmission and potential vectors of other avian blood parasites in the Hawaii Islands. 4. To determine what portion of the avifauna in the Hawaii Islands is affected by malaria. 5. To determine if introduced bird species can act as potential reservoirs of avian blood parasites in the Hawaii Islands.</abstract>
<purpose>Reporting research results</purpose>
<supplinf>
Extent of item: 13 pp
Illustrative Matter:  none
</supplinf>
</descript>
<timeperd>
<timeinfo>
<sngdate>
<caldate>2000</caldate>
</sngdate>
</timeinfo>
<current>publication date</current>
</timeperd>
<status>
<progress>Complete</progress>
<update>None planned</update>
</status>
<spdom>
<descgeog>Hawaii</descgeog>
<bounding>
<westbc>-160.5</westbc>
<eastbc>-145.7</eastbc>
<northbc>22.3</northbc>
<southbc>18.75</southbc>
</bounding>
</spdom>
<keywords>
<theme>
<themekt>none</themekt>
<themekey>disease</themekey>
<themekey>endangered species</themekey>
<themekey>management</themekey>
<themekey>predation</themekey>
</theme>
<theme>
<themekt>Science Information System Controlled Vocabulary</themekt>
<themekey>Birds</themekey>
<themekey>Invasive Species</themekey>
<themekey>Populations</themekey>
</theme>
<place>
<placekt>none</placekt>
<placekey>Hawaii</placekey>
</place>
</keywords>
<taxonomy>
<keywtax>
<taxonkt>none</taxonkt>
<taxonkey>honeycreeper</taxonkey>
</keywtax>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Kingdom</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Animalia</taxonrv>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Division</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Chordata</taxonrv>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Subdivision</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Vertebrata</taxonrv>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Class</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Aves</taxonrv>
</taxoncl>
</taxoncl>
</taxoncl>
</taxoncl>
</taxonomy>
<accconst>None</accconst>
<useconst>None</useconst>
<ptcontac>
<cntinfo>
<cntperp>
<cntper>van Riper III, Charles</cntper>
<cntorg>USGS FRESC Colorado Plateau Field Station</cntorg>
</cntperp>
<cntpos>Station Leader</cntpos>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
<address>Northern Arizona University, PO Box 5614 BLDG 24</address>
<city>Flagstaff</city>
<state>AZ</state>
<postal>86011-5614</postal>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>928-556-7466 ext 228</cntvoice>
<cntfax>928-556-7500</cntfax>
<cntemail>charles_van_riper@usgs.gov</cntemail>
</cntinfo>
</ptcontac>
</idinfo>
<distinfo>
<distrib>
<cntinfo>
<cntorgp>
<cntorg>USGS Forest &amp; Rangeland Ecosystem Science Center (FRESC)</cntorg>
<cntper>Headquarters</cntper>
</cntorgp>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>Mailing and Physical Address</addrtype>
<address>
U.S. Geological Survey
Forest and Rangeland Ecosystem Science Center
3200 SW Jefferson Way
</address>
<city>Corvallis</city>
<state>Oregon</state>
<postal>97331</postal>
<country>USA</country>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>(541) 750-7307</cntvoice>
<cntemail>FRESC_Outreach@usgs.gov</cntemail>
</cntinfo>
</distrib>
<resdesc>Publication Control #:902</resdesc>
<distliab>
The USGS Forest and Rangeland Ecosystem Science Center and its research partners make every effort to provide and maintain accurate, complete, usable, and timely information. However, some USGS data and information may, of necessity, be preliminary in nature. These data and information are provided with the understanding that they are not guaranteed to be correct or complete. Users are cautioned to consider carefully the provisional nature of these data and information before using them for decisions that concern personal or public safety or the conduct of business that involves substantial monetary or operational consequences. It is also strongly recommended that careful attention be paid to the contents of the metadata file associated with these data and information. Conclusions drawn from, or actions undertaken on the basis of, such data and information are the sole responsibility of the user.
USGS-authored or produced data and information are in the public domain. Whereas the content of many USGS publications and other information resources are in the public domain, some USGS products contain material that is copyrighted by others and used by the USGS with permission. Users of this information may need to obtain permission from the copyright owner for other uses. Furthermore, some non-USGS data, products, and information referred to may be protected under U.S. and foreign copyright laws. Users may need to obtain permission from the copyright owner to acquire, use, reproduce, or distribute these materials. It is the sole responsibility of the user of the information to secure all necessary permission.
</distliab>
<stdorder>
<nondig>Publications are available as reprints, reports, pamphlets, or brochures.</nondig>
<fees>None</fees>
<ordering>Request specific publications by reference number.</ordering>
</stdorder>
</distinfo>
<metainfo>
<metd>20020912</metd>
<metrd>20020917</metrd>
<metc>
<cntinfo>
<cntorgp>
<cntorg>USGS FRESC Snake River Field Station Olendorff Library</cntorg>
</cntorgp>
<cntpos>Library</cntpos>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
<address>970 Lusk Street</address>
<city>Boise</city>
<state>Idaho</state>
<postal>83706</postal>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>208 426-5218</cntvoice>
<cntfax>208 426-5210</cntfax>
<cntemail>kathy_mccoy@usgs.gov</cntemail>
</cntinfo>
</metc>
<metstdn>FGDC Biological Data Profile of the Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
<metstdv>FGDC-STD-001.1-1999</metstdv>
</metainfo>
<mercury><begdate>20000101</begdate><enddate>20001231</enddate><htmlurl>http://mercury.ornl.gov/metadata/nbii/html/brd/www.nbii.gov_metadata_mdata_brd-bib_usgs_brd_fresc_b_hnatbird.html</htmlurl><LTER-Site>brd</LTER-Site></mercury></metadata>
