<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<metadata><Source>http://www.nbii.gov/metadata/mdata/brd-bib/usgs_brd_fresc_b_astragalusdiv.sgml</Source>
<idinfo>
<citation>
<citeinfo>
<origin>J. Andrew Alexander</origin>
<pubdate>2001</pubdate>
<title>Genetic diversity of populations of Astragalus oniciformis using inter-simple sequence repeat (ISSR) markers</title>
<geoform>M.S. Thesis</geoform>
<pubinfo>
<pubplace>Corvallis, OR</pubplace>
<publish>Oregon State University</publish>
</pubinfo>
<othercit>
Science Information System Project #: 7016
Publication Control #: 1030
</othercit>
</citeinfo>
</citation>
<descript>
<abstract>Plant ecologists are becoming more and more concerned that the genetic diversity of many plant species is being altered by human-induced threats such as habitat alteration from livestock grazing, habitat loss from agricultural development, and changing fire patterns.  In a recently completed USGS-funded project, J. Andrew Alexander studied the genetic diversity within and among populations of Astragalus oniciformis.  This species is only found in a narrow range of the upper Snake River Plains where it inhabits stabilized, wind-created sand deposits over old lava flows.  Two discontinuous populations selected for the study have been separated from a population to the west for 3600 years by an eight-mile wide, inhospitable lava flow.  The results demonstrate that the three populations were not differentiated from one another, indicating that the genetic diversity found in Astragalus oniciformis will not decrease if the existing large populations are preserved.</abstract>
<purpose>Reporting research results</purpose>
<supplinf>
Extent of item: 90pp
Illustrative Matter:  tables, maps, graphs
</supplinf>
</descript>
<timeperd>
<timeinfo>
<sngdate>
<caldate>2001</caldate>
</sngdate>
</timeinfo>
<current>publication date</current>
</timeperd>
<status>
<progress>Complete</progress>
<update>None planned</update>
</status>
<spdom>
<descgeog>Snake River Plains, Idaho</descgeog>
<bounding>
<westbc>-115.42</westbc>
<eastbc>-110.32</eastbc>
<northbc>45.4</northbc>
<southbc>41.18</southbc>
</bounding>
</spdom>
<keywords>
<theme>
<themekt>Science Information System Controlled Vocabulary</themekt>
<themekey>Desert and Arid Lands</themekey>
<themekey>Genetics</themekey>
<themekey>Stock Assessment</themekey>
<themekey>Plants</themekey>
</theme>
<theme>
<themekt>None</themekt>
<themekey>distribution</themekey>
<themekey>comparison</themekey>
<themekey>disjunct populations</themekey>
<themekey>polymorphic</themekey>
</theme>
<place>
<placekt>none</placekt>
<placekey>Idaho</placekey>
<placekey>USA</placekey>
<placekey>ID</placekey>
</place>
</keywords>
<taxonomy>
<keywtax>
<taxonkt>None</taxonkt>
<taxonkey>plants</taxonkey>
<taxonkey>sagebrush</taxonkey>
</keywtax>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Kingdom</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Plantae</taxonrv>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Division</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Magnoliophyta</taxonrv>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Class</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Magnoliopsida</taxonrv>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Order</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Fabales</taxonrv>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Family</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Fabaceae</taxonrv>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Genus</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Astragalus</taxonrv>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Species</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Astragalus oniciformis</taxonrv>
</taxoncl>
</taxoncl>
</taxoncl>
</taxoncl>
</taxoncl>
</taxoncl>
</taxoncl>
</taxonomy>
<accconst>None</accconst>
<useconst>None</useconst>
<ptcontac>
<cntinfo>
<cntperp>
<cntper>Pyke, David</cntper>
<cntorg>USGS Forest and Rangeland Ecosystem Science Center</cntorg>
</cntperp>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
<address>3200 SW Jefferson Way</address>
<city>Corvallis</city>
<state>OR</state>
<postal>97331</postal>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>541/750/7334</cntvoice>
<cntemail>david_a_pyke@usgs.gov</cntemail>
</cntinfo>
</ptcontac>
</idinfo>
<distinfo>
<distrib>
<cntinfo>
<cntorgp>
<cntorg>Olendorff Library</cntorg>
</cntorgp>
<cntpos>Librarian</cntpos>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
<address>
USGS FRESC Snake River Field Station
970 Lusk Street
</address>
<city>Boise</city>
<state>ID</state>
<postal>83706</postal>
<country>USA</country>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>208 426-5218</cntvoice>
<cntfax>208 426-5210</cntfax>
</cntinfo>
</distrib>
<resdesc>Publication Control #: 1030</resdesc>
<distliab>
The USGS Forest and Rangeland Ecosystem Science Center and its research partners make every effort to provide and maintain accurate, complete, usable, and timely information. However, some USGS data and information may, of necessity, be preliminary in nature. These data and information are provided with the understanding that they are not guaranteed to be correct or complete. Users are cautioned to consider carefully the provisional nature of these data and information before using them for decisions that concern personal or public safety or the conduct of business that involves substantial monetary or operational consequences. It is also strongly recommended that careful attention be paid to the contents of the metadata file associated with these data and information. Conclusions drawn from, or actions undertaken on the basis of, such data and information are the sole responsibility of the user.
USGS-authored or produced data and information are in the public domain. Whereas the content of many USGS publications and other information resources are in the public domain, some USGS products contain material that is copyrighted by others and used by the USGS with permission. Users of this information may need to obtain permission from the copyright owner for other uses. Furthermore, some non-USGS data, products, and information referred to may be protected under U.S. and foreign copyright laws. Users may need to obtain permission from the copyright owner to acquire, use, reproduce, or distribute these materials. It is the sole responsibility of the user of the information to secure all necessary permission.
</distliab>
<stdorder>
<nondig>Publications are available as reprints, reports, pamphlets, or brochures.</nondig>
<fees>None</fees>
<ordering>Request specific publications by reference number.</ordering>
</stdorder>
</distinfo>
<metainfo>
<metd>20011213</metd>
<metrd>20011220</metrd>
<metc>
<cntinfo>
<cntorgp>
<cntorg>Olendorff Library</cntorg>
</cntorgp>
<cntpos>Librarian</cntpos>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
<address>
USGS FRESC Snake River Field Station
970 Lusk Street
</address>
<city>Boise</city>
<state>ID</state>
<postal>83706</postal>
<country>USA</country>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>208 426-5218</cntvoice>
<cntfax>208 426-5210</cntfax>
</cntinfo>
</metc>
<metstdn>FGDC Biological Data Profile of the Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
<metstdv>FGDC-STD-001.1-1999</metstdv>
</metainfo>
<mercury><begdate>20010101</begdate><enddate>20011231</enddate><htmlurl>http://mercury.ornl.gov/metadata/nbii/html/brd/www.nbii.gov_metadata_mdata_brd-bib_usgs_brd_fresc_b_astragalusdiv.html</htmlurl><LTER-Site>brd</LTER-Site></mercury></metadata>
