<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<metadata><Source>http://www.nbii.gov/metadata/mdata/frames/nbii_frames_d_BraidedCave.sgml</Source>
<idinfo>
<citation>
<citeinfo>
<origin>D. Lewis (collector and crossdater)</origin>
<origin>H.D. Grissino-Mayer (collector and crossdater)</origin>
<origin>E. Atchley (collector)</origin>
<origin>M. Armbrister (collector)</origin>
<pubdate>200106</pubdate>
<title>Braided Cave Fire History_fhx2</title>
<geoform>maps data</geoform>
<othercit>file name: brc.fhx</othercit>
<onlink>http://web.utk.edu/~grissino/jfsp013329/data.html</onlink>
<onlink>http://web.utk.edu/~grissino/jfsp013329/brc.fhx</onlink>
<lworkcit>
<citeinfo>
<origin>Daniel B. Lewis</origin>
<pubdate>2003</pubdate>
<title>Fire regimes of kipuka forests in El Malpais National Monument, New Mexico, USA</title>
<pubinfo>
<pubplace>Knoxville, TN</pubplace>
<publish>The University of Tennessee</publish>
</pubinfo>
<othercit>
This dataset is part of the project with FRAMES resource id {E4211B5D-4B1D-4EEA-8262-BD97E5FE8E95} and part of the thesis cited below:
Daniel B. Lewis, 2003. Fire regimes of kipuka forests in El Malpais National Monument, New Mexico, USA. M.S. thesis, The University of Tennessee, Knoxville. 145 pp.  -- {8797FC16-90F4-4BFB-AC2B-2D49317316D6}
</othercit>
<onlink>http://web.utk.edu/~grissino/jfsp013329/thesis.html</onlink>
</citeinfo>
</lworkcit>
</citeinfo>
</citation>
<descript>
<abstract>
Braided Cave Fire History dataset as part of the thesis -- Daniel B. Lewis, 2003. Fire regimes of kipuka forests in El Malpais National Monument, New Mexico, USA. M.S. thesis, The University of Tennessee, Knoxville. 145 pp.
Currently, ecosystem processes that maintain the forests of the American Southwest are operating outside the historical range of variation that existed prior to Euro-American settlement. Areas that have been minimally disturbed by humans should be targeted for research because they contain valuable information about past ecological processes. In El Malpais National Monument, islands of older substrate material are surrounded by younger lava flows. These areas, known as kipukas, likely preserve presettlement forest structure and contain trees old enough to provide information on past ecological processes.
</abstract>
<purpose>The purpose of this study is to reconstruct fire history on minimally disturbed kipukas in El Malpais National Monument, New Mexico. Eight sites were sampled and 105 fire-scarred samples were collected. Increment cores were taken from living ponderosa pine (Pinus ponderosa Dougl. ex. Laws) trees on two kipukas to examine the age structure of the kipuka forests and to determine whether fire suppression away from the kipukas may be allowing ponderosa pines to encroach onto areas not in their local distribution in the monument.</purpose>
<supplinf>
The Braided Cave site is located ca. 0.5 km west of the Logging Road site. The area sampled represents ca. 0.08 km2 (350 m x 240 m). Elevation is around 2307 m asl throughout the entire area. Braided Cave is part of the very long lava tube system that extends through the monument. These tubes are around 8-10 meters high in some areas, and are much cooler than the surrounding areas on the surface. The samples were taken between the access road and the caves themselves. The sample area looks much like that of the Logging Road site, with open ponderosa pine forest andminimal grass cover. Douglas-fir seedlings and juvenile trees were observed in this area. This location exceeds the southernmost extent for this species in the monument according  to Bleakly (1997). The presence of young Douglas-fir trees at this site could indicate that fires have been excluded in this area for quite some time.
Seedling and sapling numbers were comparable with that of the Logging Road site. It is possible that widespread livestock grazing has impeded fire spread at both of these sites, allowing the high numbers of seedlings and the subsequent establishment of Douglas-firs.
taken from section 3.5.3 of Daniel B. Lewis, 2003. Fire regimes of kipuka forests in El Malpais National Monument, New Mexico, USA. M.S. thesis, The University of Tennessee, Knoxville. 145 pp.
(previous geoform was 'maps or data')</supplinf>
</descript>
<timeperd>
<timeinfo>
<sngdate>
<caldate>200106</caldate>
</sngdate>
</timeinfo>
<current>as indicated by dataset</current>
</timeperd>
<status>
<progress>Complete</progress>
<update>Unknown</update>
</status>
<spdom>
<bounding>
<westbc>-108.1</westbc>
<eastbc>-107.8</eastbc>
<northbc>34.9</northbc>
<southbc>34.68</southbc>
</bounding>
</spdom>
<keywords>
<theme>
<themekt>FRAMES Resource ID</themekt>
<themekey>{48FEC371-1070-4C58-BE35-DB1D8F98B696}</themekey>
</theme>
<theme>
<themekt>GACC Regions</themekt>
<themekey>Southwest</themekey>
</theme>
<theme>
<themekt>FRAMES Subject Categories</themekt>
<themekey>fire history</themekey>
</theme>
<theme>
<themekt>none</themekt>
<themekey>pinus ponderosa</themekey>
<themekey>lava flow</themekey>
<themekey>douglas fir</themekey>
</theme>
</keywords>
<accconst>none</accconst>
<useconst>Please provide the appropriate citation/credit to the roiginator(s) or individual/organization(s) that should receive recognition for their contribution to the data set.</useconst>
<ptcontac>
<cntinfo>
<cntperp>
<cntper>Henri D. Grissino-Mayer</cntper>
<cntorg>Department of Geography, The University of Tennessee</cntorg>
</cntperp>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>physical address</addrtype>
<address>Department of Geography, The University of Tennessee</address>
<city>Knoxville</city>
<state>Tennessee</state>
<postal>37996</postal>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>865.974.6029</cntvoice>
<cntfax>865.974.6025</cntfax>
<cntemail>grissino at utk.edu</cntemail>
</cntinfo>
</ptcontac>
<native>Microsoft Windows XP Version 5.1 (Build 2600) Service Pack 2; ESRI ArcCatalog 9.1.0.780</native>
<crossref>
<citeinfo>
<origin>Henri D. Grissino-Mayer, Department of Geography, The University of Tennessee, Knoxville, TN</origin>
<origin>Herschel Schulz, El Malpais National Monument, Grants, NM</origin>
<pubdate>2001</pubdate>
<title>Assessing Anthropogenic Changes in Fire Regimes Using Relict Areas in El Malpais National Monument, New Mexico -- JFSP 01-3-3-29 {E4211B5D-4B1D-4EEA-8262-BD97E5FE8E95}</title>
<othercit>This dataset is part of the project with FRAMES resource id {E4211B5D-4B1D-4EEA-8262-BD97E5FE8E95}.</othercit>
<onlink>http://web.utk.edu/~grissino/jfsp013329/proposal.html</onlink>
</citeinfo>
</crossref>
<crossref>
<citeinfo>
<origin>Daniel B. Lewis</origin>
<pubdate>2003</pubdate>
<title>Fire regimes of kipuka forests in El Malpais National Monument, New Mexico, USA -- {8797FC16-90F4-4BFB-AC2B-2D49317316D6}</title>
<othercit>
This dataset is part of the thesis cited below:
Daniel B. Lewis, 2003. Fire regimes of kipuka forests in El Malpais National Monument, New Mexico, USA. M.S. thesis, The University of Tennessee, Knoxville. 145 pp.  -- {8797FC16-90F4-4BFB-AC2B-2D49317316D6}
</othercit>
<onlink>http://web.utk.edu/~grissino/jfsp013329/thesis.html</onlink>
</citeinfo>
</crossref>
</idinfo>
<dataqual>
<attracc>
<attraccr>none</attraccr>
</attracc>
<logic>Unknown</logic>
<complete>unknown</complete>
<lineage>
<procstep>
<procdesc>UNKNOWN</procdesc>
<procdate>UNKNOWN</procdate>
</procstep>
</lineage>
</dataqual>
<spref>
<horizsys>
<geograph>
<latres>34.9</latres>
<longres>108.1</longres>
<geogunit>Decimal degrees</geogunit>
</geograph>
</horizsys>
</spref>
<eainfo>
<overview>
<eaover>More about FHX2 format (standard format for fire history data) can be found at the International Multiproxy Paleofire Database (IMPD) as described under Tree-Ring Fire Event Data Description available at http://www.ncdc.noaa.gov/paleo/impd/tree_event_info.html.</eaover>
<eadetcit>UNKNOWN</eadetcit>
</overview>
</eainfo>
<distinfo>
<distrib>
<cntinfo>
<cntperp>
<cntper>Henri D. Griussino-Mayer</cntper>
<cntorg>Dept. of Geography, The University of Tennessee</cntorg>
</cntperp>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>physical address</addrtype>
<address>Dept. of Geography, The University of Tennessee</address>
<city>Knoxville</city>
<state>Tennessee</state>
<postal>37996</postal>
<country>USA</country>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>865.974.6029</cntvoice>
<cntfax>865.974.6025</cntfax>
<cntemail>grissino@utk.edu</cntemail>
</cntinfo>
</distrib>
<resdesc>Downloadable Data</resdesc>
<distliab>UNKNOWN</distliab>
<custom>Data in FHX2 format is available for viewing at http://web.utk.edu/~grissino/jfsp013329/data.html</custom>
</distinfo>
<metainfo>
<metd>20061002</metd>
<metc>
<cntinfo>
<cntperp>
<cntper>Christopher C. Szell</cntper>
<cntorg>National Biological Inventory Infrastructure (NBII) Fire Research and Management Exchange System (FRAMES) The Nature Conservancy (TNC)</cntorg>
</cntperp>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
<address>6114 Fayetteville Rd.</address>
<address>suite 109</address>
<city>Durham</city>
<state>NC</state>
<postal>27713</postal>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>919.484.7857</cntvoice>
<cntemail>cszell@tnc.org</cntemail>
</cntinfo>
</metc>
<metstdn>FGDC Content Standards for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
<metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
<mettc>local time</mettc>
<metextns>
<onlink>http://www.esri.com/metadata/esriprof80.html</onlink>
<metprof>ESRI Metadata Profile</metprof>
</metextns>
</metainfo>
<mercury><begdate>20010601</begdate><enddate>20010631</enddate><htmlurl>http://mercury.ornl.gov/metadata/nbii/html/frames/www.nbii.gov_metadata_mdata_frames_nbii_frames_d_BraidedCave.html</htmlurl><LTER-Site>frames</LTER-Site></mercury></metadata>
