<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<metadata><Source>http://www.nbii.gov/metadata/mdata/CBI/usgs_brd_cbi_d_folafieldpoints.sgml</Source>
<idinfo>
<citation>
<citeinfo>
<origin>U.S. Geological Survey Department of the Interior</origin>
<pubdate>199808</pubdate>
<title>
Fort Laramie National Historic Site, Field Plots Data Base for
Vegetation Mapping
</title>
<geoform>maps data</geoform>
<serinfo>
<sername>USGS-NPS Vegetation Mapping Program</sername>
<issue>Fort Laramie National Historic Site</issue>
</serinfo>
<pubinfo>
<pubplace>Denver, CO</pubplace>
<publish>USGS, Biological Resources Division, Center for Biological Informatics</publish>
</pubinfo>
<othercit>
Created by Environmental Systems Research Institute, Inc.,
Redlands, CA under contract from USGS/BRD/CBI.
</othercit>
<onlink>http://biology.usgs.gov/npsveg/fola/fielddata.html</onlink>
</citeinfo>
</citation>
<descript>
<abstract>
Vegetation field plots at Fort Laramie NHS were visited, described, and
documented in a digital database. The database consists of two parts - (1)
Physical Descriptive and Stratum Data, and (2) Species Listings.
</abstract>
<purpose>
Provide National Parks with the necessary tools to effectively manage
their natural resources. Plot data is collected and analyzed to develop a
classification (using the Standardized National Vegetation Classification
System) and description of vegetation types in preparation for
photointerpretation and mapping of the monument's vegetation types.
</purpose>
<supplinf>(previous geoform was 'Database')</supplinf>
</descript>
<timeperd>
<timeinfo>
<rngdates>
<begdate>19970621</begdate>
<enddate>19970629</enddate>
</rngdates>
</timeinfo>
<current>Ground Condition</current>
</timeperd>
<status>
<progress>Complete</progress>
<update>none planned</update>
</status>
<spdom>
<bounding>
<westbc>-104.13276</westbc>
<eastbc>-104.34382</eastbc>
<northbc>42.13276</northbc>
<southbc>42.11212</southbc>
</bounding>
<descgeog>
Fort Laramie National Historic Site and
environs.
</descgeog>
</spdom>
<keywords>
<theme>
<themekt>None</themekt>
<themekey>National Park Service</themekey>
<themekey>U.S. Geological Survey</themekey>
<themekey>The Nature Conservancy</themekey>
<themekey>Aerial Information Systems</themekey>
<themekey>Center for Biological Informatics</themekey>
<themekey>land cover</themekey>
<themekey>vegetation</themekey>
<themekey>association</themekey>
<themekey>Environmental System Research Institute</themekey>
</theme>
<place>
<placekt>None</placekt>
<placekey>Wyoming</placekey>
<placekey>WY</placekey>
<placekey>Fort Laramie</placekey>
<placekey>Goshen County</placekey>
</place>
</keywords>
<taxonomy>
<keywtax>
<taxonkt>None</taxonkt>
<taxonkey>vegetation classification</taxonkey>
<taxonkey>Standardized National Vegetation Classification System</taxonkey>
<taxonkey>alliance</taxonkey>
<taxonkey>community association</taxonkey>
</keywtax>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Kingdom</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Plantae</taxonrv>
</taxoncl>
</taxonomy>
<accconst>None</accconst>
<useconst>
Any person using the information presented here should fully understand the
data collection and compilation procedures, as described in these metadata,
before beginning analyses. The burden for determining fitness for use lies
entirely with the user. For purposes of publication or dissemination, citations
or credit should be given to the U.S. Geological Survey and the National Park Service.
</useconst>
<ptcontac>
<cntinfo>
<cntperp>
<cntper>USGS-NPS Vegetation Mapping Program Coordinator</cntper>
<cntorg>
USGS Biological Resources Division, Center for Biological
Informatics
</cntorg>
</cntperp>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>Physical Address</addrtype>
<address>USGS</address>
<address>Biological Resources Division, CBI</address>
<address>Building 810, Room 8000</address>
<city>Denver</city>
<state>Colorado</state>
<postal>80225-0046</postal>
<country>USA</country>
</cntaddr>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>Mailing Address</addrtype>
<address>USGS</address>
<address>Biological Resources Division, CBI</address>
<address>PO BOX 25046, DFC, MS302</address>
<city>Denver</city>
<state>Colorado</state>
<postal>80225-0046</postal>
<country>USA</country>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>(303) 202-4220</cntvoice>
<cntfax>303-202-4229</cntfax>
<cntfax>303-202-4219 (org)</cntfax>
<cntemail>gs-b-npsveg@usgs.gov</cntemail>
</cntinfo>
</ptcontac>
<browse>
<browsen>&lt;http://biology.usgs.gov/npsveg/fola/images/folaplot.jpg&gt;</browsen>
<browsed>Locations of vegetation plot samples; low resolution for web browsing.</browsed>
<browset>JPG</browset>
</browse>
<datacred>
Hollis Marriot, in cooperation with The Nature Conservancy, collected field
data
</datacred>
<native>DB4</native>
</idinfo>
<dataqual>
<attracc>
<attraccr>
Descriptive plot data were collected for 49 sites whose vegetation
represents a full spectrum of alliance types present within Fort Laramie
National Historic Site and its immediate surroundings. Physical description -
Attributes collected for each site include: a plot number, a unique plot
identification code, community name, field name, state, park name, quad
name, map projection, datum, GPS file name, raw UTM coordinates ,
differentially corrected UTM coordinates, plot survey date, name(s) of
surveyors, length, width, photo type, elevation, slope, aspect,
topographic position, landform, surface geology, Cowardin System category,
hydrology, surface material description, soil texture, soil drainage, leaf
phenology, leaf type, physiognomy type, plant height and animal use
evidence. Species - Individual species described at each of 49 plots is
listed, one line per species, with the following information: Plot
Identification Code, Numeric Species Code, Species Name, Species Cover (
0=trace, 1=&lt; 1%, 2=1-5%, 3=5-25%, 4=25-50%, 5=50-75%, 6=75-100%),
Plantcode, and Strata Code (T1=emergent, T2=canopy, T3=sub-canopy, S1=tall
shrub, S2=short shrub, H=herbaceous, N=non-vascular, V=vinae/liana,
E=epiphyte).
evidence. Species -
</attraccr>
</attracc>
<logic>
Physical description - Entries for each of the listed attributes are in the
form of consistent groupings of either textual or numerical descriptors.
Species - Entries for each of the listed attributes are in the form of
consistent groupings of either textual or numerical descriptors, as defined
above under "Attribute Accuracy Report". NOTE 1: The significance of numbers
appended to some of the Plant Codes is not known.
</logic>
<complete>
Physical description: Comprehensive descriptions exist for each of the 49
plots, but some do not contain entries under headings which are not applicable.
Species - One species is entered per line, by plot code, with multiple species
listed for each plot, one per row. Plot codes and species names are complete
for  each row, but some species codes, cover and strata information is missing
</complete>
<posacc>
<horizpa>
<horizpar>
X,Y UTM coordinates representing each of the 49 plots were collected via
GPS under selective availability with post processing for differential
correction. The differentially correted GPS coordinates have accuracies
in the X and Y direction of +/- 3 to 11 meters.
</horizpar>
</horizpa>
<vertacc>
<vertaccr>Not applicable</vertaccr>
</vertacc>
</posacc>
<lineage>
<method>
<methtype>Field</methtype>
<methodid>
<methkt>None</methkt>
<methkey>releve</methkey>
<methkey>plot</methkey>
<methkey>sampling</methkey>
</methodid>
<methdesc>Field sampling using releve plots</methdesc>
</method>
<srcinfo>
<srccite>
<citeinfo>
<origin>National Biological Survey (Now USGS/Biological Resources Division)</origin>
<origin>and National Park Service</origin>
<pubdate>199411</pubdate>
<title>
Standardized National Vegetation Classification System; protocol
document for the USGS-NPS Vegetation mapping Program (unpublished
report)
</title>
<geoform>document</geoform>
<edition>Final Draft</edition>
<serinfo>
<sername>USGS-NPS Vegetation Mapping Program</sername>
<issue>Protocol documents</issue>
</serinfo>
<pubinfo>
<pubplace>Denver, CO</pubplace>
<publish>USGS/BRD, Center for Biological Informatics</publish>
</pubinfo>
<othercit>
Report prepared under contract by The Nature Conservancy, 1815 N.
Lynn Street, Arlington, Virginia 22209 and Environmental Systems
Research Institute, 380 New York Street, Redlands, California 92373
</othercit>
<onlink>http://biology.usgs.gov/npsveg/classification/index.html</onlink>
</citeinfo>
</srccite>
<typesrc>Online</typesrc>
<srctime>
<timeinfo>
<rngdates>
<begdate>199411</begdate>
<enddate>2010</enddate>
</rngdates>
</timeinfo>
<srccurr>Publication Date and indefinitely</srccurr>
</srctime>
<srccitea>SNVCS protocol document</srccitea>
<srccontr>
This document describes and defines the vegetation classification system
which is to be used for describing and mapping the vegetation at Fort
Laramie National Historic Site
</srccontr>
</srcinfo>
<srcinfo>
<srccite>
<citeinfo>
<origin>USGSBRD, Center for Biological Informatics</origin>
<pubdate>19980223</pubdate>
<title>Classification of the Vegetation of Fort Laramie National Historic Site</title>
<geoform>report</geoform>
<serinfo>
<sername>USGS-NPS Vegetation Mapping Program</sername>
<issue>Fort Laramie National Historic Site</issue>
</serinfo>
<pubinfo>
<pubplace>Denver, CO</pubplace>
<publish>USGS/BRD, Center for Biological Informatics</publish>
</pubinfo>
<othercit>
This report was generated by The Nature Conservancy under contract
to the USGS/BRD, Center for Biological Informatics
</othercit>
<onlink>http://biology.usgs.gov/npsveg/fola/methods.pdf</onlink>
</citeinfo>
</srccite>
<typesrc>Online</typesrc>
<srctime>
<timeinfo>
<sngdate>
<caldate>199712</caldate>
</sngdate>
</timeinfo>
<srccurr>Ground Condition, 1997</srccurr>
</srctime>
<srccitea>FOLA sample and classification</srccitea>
<srccontr>Report summarizing plot data collection effort</srccontr>
</srcinfo>
<srcinfo>
<srccite>
<citeinfo>
<origin>
United States Dept. of the Interior, National Biological Survey (no
USGS Biological Resources Division) and the National Park Service
</origin>
<pubdate>199412</pubdate>
<title>Field Methods for Vegetation Mapping</title>
<geoform>document</geoform>
<pubinfo>
<pubplace>Denver, CO</pubplace>
<publish>
USGS/Biological Resources Division, Center for Biological
Informatics
</publish>
</pubinfo>
<othercit>
This report was generated by The Nature Conservancy under contract
to the USGS/BRD, CBI
</othercit>
<onlink>http://biology.usgs.gov/npsveg/fieldmethods/index.html</onlink>
</citeinfo>
</srccite>
<typesrc>Online</typesrc>
<srctime>
<timeinfo>
<rngdates>
<begdate>199412</begdate>
<enddate>2010</enddate>
</rngdates>
</timeinfo>
<srccurr>Publication Date and indefinitely</srccurr>
</srctime>
<srccitea>field methods protocol document</srccitea>
<srccontr>
This document defines the methods and protocols for field data
collection to be used as part of the USGS-NPS Vegetation Mapping Program
</srccontr>
</srcinfo>
<procstep>
<procdesc>
The following describes the tasks performed by The Nature Conservancy
to produce descriptive data for 49 vegetation sampling plots in two
separate database files. Physical description - The first of the two
contains general descriptive and stratum information at each of the
plots. Plot sites were selected subjectively because of the heterogeneity
of the vegetation and the small number of samples per type. Since aerial
photos were not available at the time of plot selection, visual
reconnaissance was conducted at the summit of the site to examine
vegetation patterns for the purpose of plot placement. Site physical
parameters, species types, and vegetation strata were then described at
each site. The PLOT DATA database contains tabulations of site physical
factors, listed under the ATTRIBUTE ACCURACY REPORT for each of the 49
plots. Plot data were manually recorded on field forms on-site, and
subsequently keyed into the database files described herein. Information
in the plot database was then used to develop the classification system
and plant identification keys contained in the FORT LARAMIE SAMPLING AND
CLASSIFICATION REPORT. Species - The second of the two contains listings
of individual species found in each plot, along with height and cover
estimates, and strata delineations. The SPECIES LISTING database
contains line entries for each species including the Plot Code, Numeric
species code, full scientific species name, common names, cover
estimate, a unique alphnumeric species identifier (plant code), and
Plant Strata delineation. Plot sites were selected subjectively because
of the heterogeneity of the vegetation and the small number of samples
per type. Since aerial photos were not available at the time of plot
selection, visual reconnaissance was conducted at the summit of the
bluff to examine vegetation patterns for determining plot placement.
Plot data were manually recorded on field forms on-site, and
subsequently keyed into the database files described herein. Information
in the plot database was then used to develop the classification system
and plant identification keys contained in the FORT LARAMIE SAMPLING AND
CLASSIFICATION REPORT.
</procdesc>
<srcused>SNVCS protocol document</srcused>
<srcused>Field Methods for Vegetation Mapping</srcused>
<procdate>199508</procdate>
<srcprod>fola sample and classification</srcprod>
<srcprod>FOLA Vegetation Descriptions</srcprod>
<proccont>
<cntinfo>
<cntperp>
<cntper>Jim Drake</cntper>
<cntorg>The Nature Conservancy</cntorg>
</cntperp>
<cntpos>Regional Chief Ecologist, The Nature Conservancy</cntpos>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>Physical Address</addrtype>
<address>1313 5th Street SE</address>
<address>Suite 314</address>
<city>Minneapolis</city>
<state>MN</state>
<postal>55414</postal>
<country>USA</country>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>(612)331-0729</cntvoice>
<cntemail>jdrake@tnc.org</cntemail>
</cntinfo>
</proccont>
</procstep>
</lineage>
</dataqual>
<spdoinfo>
<indspref>
Fort Laramie National Historic Site is located in Goshen County, Wyoming.
The Historic Site is 2 miles south of Fort Laramie, Wyoming.
</indspref>
<direct>Point</direct>
<ptvctinf>
<sdtsterm>
<sdtstype>Point</sdtstype>
</sdtsterm>
</ptvctinf>
</spdoinfo>
<spref>
<horizsys>
<planar>
<gridsys>
<gridsysn>Universal Transverse Mercator</gridsysn>
<utm>
<utmzone>13</utmzone>
<transmer>
<longcm>-105</longcm>
<latprjo>0</latprjo>
<feast>500000</feast>
<fnorth>0</fnorth>
<sfctrmer>.9996</sfctrmer>
</transmer>
</utm>
</gridsys>
<planci>
<plance>coordinate pair</plance>
<coordrep>
<absres>1</absres>
<ordres>1</ordres>
</coordrep>
<plandu>Meters</plandu>
</planci>
</planar>
<geodetic>
<horizdn>North American Datum of 1983</horizdn>
<ellips>Geodedic Reference System 80</ellips>
<semiaxis>6378137</semiaxis>
<denflat>298.257</denflat>
</geodetic>
</horizsys>
</spref>
<eainfo>
<overview>
<eaover>
Each of 49 vegetation mapping plot sites contains the attributes of
species found. Physical description - General plot information is
described by identification codes, locational information (including
state, park name, and USGS 7 1/2' topographic quad name). Physical
factors tabulated in the database include UTM_X, UTM_Y, UTM Zone, map
projection, survey date, name of surveyors, plot length and width, type
of photos used, plot elevation, slope aspect, topographic position,
landform type, surface geology, Cowardin system descriptor, hydrology,
rock size, surface material type, soil texture and drainage, leaf
phenology, leaf type, physiognomy type, plant height and animal use
evidence. Species - (sp_code is a project specific code for  each
species found, species is the scientific name for that  species, spcover
is the species present and the percent cover for each species, plant
code is the first two letters of the  genus and first two letters of
the species. If the code are not unique a number is added to make the
code unique). This includes strata cover  which is an average percent
cover of that particular species, 1 = 0-10%, 2 = 10-25%, 3 = 25-60%
and 4 = 60-100%,  pstrata is the type of vegetation, T1 = emergent,
T2 = canopy, T3  = sub-canopy, S1 = tall shrub, S2 = short shrub,
H = herbaceous, N = non-vascular, V = vine/liana, and E = epiphyte).
</eaover>
<eadetcit>
Field Methods for Vegetation mapping, December 1994. Prepared for: the
United States Department of the Interior, National Biological Survey (now
the USGS Biological Resources Division) and the National Park Service.
Prepared by: The Nature Conservancy, and Environmental Systems Research
Institute. (http://biology.usgs.gov/npsveg/fieldmethods/index.html) .
</eadetcit>
</overview>
</eainfo>
<distinfo>
<distrib>
<cntinfo>
<cntorgp>
<cntorg>USGS-NPS Vegetation Mapping Program Coordinator</cntorg>
</cntorgp>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
<address>U.S. Geological Survey, Center for Biological Informatics, MS 302, Room 8000, Building 810, Denver Federal Center</address>
<city>Denver</city>
<state>Colorado</state>
<postal>80225</postal>
<country>USA</country>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>(303) 202-4220</cntvoice>
<cntfax>(303) 202-4219</cntfax>
<cntemail>gs-b-npsveg@usgs.gov</cntemail>
</cntinfo>
</distrib>
<resdesc>Physical Descriptive and Strata Data and Species Listing Data</resdesc>
<distliab>
Although these data have been processed successfully on a computer system at
the Biological Resources Division, no warranty expressed or implied is made
regarding the accuracy or utility of the data on any other system or for
general or scientific purposes, nor shall the act of distribution constitute
any such warranty. This disclaimer applies both to individual use of the
data and aggregate use with other data. It is strongly recommended that
these data are directly acquired from a Biological Resources Division
server, and not indirectly through other sources which may have changed the
data in some way. It is also strongly recommended that careful attention be
paid to the contents of the metadata file associated with these data. The
Biological Resources Division shall not be held liable for improper or
incorrect use of the data described and/or contained herein.
</distliab>
<stdorder>
<digform>
<digtinfo>
<formname>HTML</formname>
</digtinfo>
<digtopt>
<onlinopt>
<computer>
<networka>
<networkr>http://biology.usgs.gov/npsveg/fola/fielddata.html</networkr>
</networka>
</computer>
</onlinopt>
</digtopt>
</digform>
<fees>None</fees>
</stdorder>
</distinfo>
<metainfo>
<metd>20011022</metd>
<metrd>20050519</metrd>
<metc>
<cntinfo>
<cntorgp>
<cntorg>USGS-NPS Vegetation Mapping Program Coordinator</cntorg>
</cntorgp>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
<address>
U.S. Geological Survey, Center for Biological Informatics, MS 302,
Room 8000, Building 810, Denver Federal Center
</address>
<city>Denver</city>
<state>Colorado</state>
<postal>80225</postal>
<country>USA</country>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>(303) 202-4220</cntvoice>
<cntfax>(303) 202-4219</cntfax>
<cntemail>gs-b-npsveg@usgs.gov</cntemail>
</cntinfo>
</metc>
<metstdn>FGDC-STD-001.1-1999 Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata, 1998 Part 1: Biological Data Profile, 1999</metstdn>
<metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
<metextns>
<onlink>http://biology.usgs.gov/fgdc.bio/bionwext.txt</onlink>
<metprof>Biological Data Profile FGDC-STD-001.1-1999</metprof>
</metextns>
</metainfo>
<mercury><begdate>19970621</begdate><enddate>19970629</enddate><htmlurl>http://mercury.ornl.gov/metadata/nbii/html/nbii/www.nbii.gov_metadata_mdata_CBI_usgs_brd_cbi_d_folafieldpoints.html</htmlurl><LTER-Site>nbii</LTER-Site></mercury></metadata>
