<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<metadata><Source>http://www.nbii.gov/metadata/mdata/frames/nbii_frames_d_carolina.sgml</Source>
<idinfo>
<citation>
<citeinfo>
<origin>Kenneth Outcalt, Dale Wade, David Combs</origin>
<pubdate>Unpublished Material</pubdate>
<title>Dormant-Season Prescription Fires to Reduce Hazardous Fuel Loads on the South Carolina Coastal Plain</title>
<othercit>FRAMES Resource ID = {860B7C20-E5A5-44F1-B7E1-4C821BFDFD41}</othercit>
<geoform>maps data</geoform>
<lworkcit>
<citeinfo>
<origin>Dale Wade</origin>
<pubdate>Unpublished Material</pubdate>
<title>Dormant-Season Prescription Fires to Reduce Hazardous Fuel Loads on the South Carolina Coastal Plain: Establishing</title>
<geoform>unknown</geoform>
<othercit>FRAMES Resource ID = {77A23112-A613-47A7-BE23-F0D29B353195}</othercit>
</citeinfo>
</lworkcit>
</citeinfo>
</citation>
<descript>
<abstract>In 1958 the Southeastern Forest Experiment Station, Macon Fire Lab established a 40-acre study on the Francis Marion National Forest to compare the effectiveness of four fire return intervals, namely every 1-, 2-, 3-, or 4-years (along with an unburned check treatment), to reduce the hazardous buildup of fuels on Lower Coastal Plain sites. These 5 treatments were replicated 4 times, each 2-acre replicate separated by either a plowed fire break or a Forest Service road. Over the ensuing 47 years, one replicate of each treatment has been discarded for various reasons. The remaining 3 replicates of each treatment have, to date, been burned as scheduled, and the plan is to continue to maintain this schedule into the foreseeable future.</abstract>
<purpose>In 1958 the Southeastern Forest Experiment Station, Macon Fire Lab established a 40-acre study on the Francis Marion National Forest to compare the effectiveness of four fire return intervals, namely every 1-, 2-, 3-, or 4-years (along with an unburned check treatment), to reduce the hazardous buildup of fuels on Lower Coastal Plain sites. These 5 treatments were replicated 4 times, each 2-acre replicate separated by either a plowed fire break or a Forest Service road. Over the ensuing 47 years, one replicate of each treatment has been discarded for various reasons. The remaining 3 replicates of each treatment have, to date, been burned as scheduled, and the plan is to continue to maintain this schedule into the foreseeable future.</purpose>
</descript>
<timeperd>
<timeinfo>
<rngdates>
<begdate>1958</begdate>
<enddate>2005</enddate>
</rngdates>
</timeinfo>
<current>ground condition</current>
</timeperd>
<status>
<progress>In work</progress>
<update>As needed</update>
</status>
<spdom>
<descgeog>South Carolina coastal plain</descgeog>
<bounding>
<westbc>-79.817</westbc>
<eastbc>-79.783</eastbc>
<northbc>34.375</northbc>
<southbc>33.25</southbc>
</bounding>
</spdom>
<keywords>
<theme>
<themekt>FRAMES Subject categories</themekt>
<themekey>prescribed fire</themekey>
</theme>
<theme>
<themekt>GACC Region</themekt>
<themekey>Southern</themekey>
</theme>
<theme>
<themekt>NBII Resource Type</themekt>
<themekey>Dataset</themekey>
</theme>
<theme>
<themekt>None</themekt>
<themekey>Study No. FS-SE-2101-(1)-1)</themekey>
<themekey>southern fuels</themekey>
<themekey>loblolly pine</themekey>
<themekey>longleaf pine</themekey>
<themekey>Francis Marion National Forest</themekey>
</theme>
<theme>
<themekt>FRAMES Resource ID</themekt>
<themekey>{860B7C20-E5A5-44F1-B7E1-4C821BFDFD41}</themekey>
</theme>
<place>
<placekt>none</placekt>
<placekey>South Carolina coastal plain</placekey>
</place>
</keywords>
<accconst>Data is collected with government funding and thus is in the public domain. However, until data has been published, the owners and principal investigators have the right to restrict access. Any use before this time must be arranged with the principal investigator.</accconst>
<useconst>Data is collected with government funding and thus is in the public domain. However, until data has been published, the owners and principal investigators have the right to restrict access. Any use before this time must be arranged with the principal investigator.</useconst>
<ptcontac>
<cntinfo>
<cntperp>
<cntper>Kenneth Outcalt</cntper>
<cntorg>USDA FOREST SERVICE, SOUTHERN RESEARCH STATION, RWU-4104</cntorg>
</cntperp>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
<address>
320 Green Street
Forestry Sciences Lab
</address>
<city>Athens</city>
<state>GA</state>
<postal>30602-2044</postal>
<country>USA</country>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>706-559-4309</cntvoice>
<cntfax>706-559-4317</cntfax>
<cntemail>koutcalt@fs.fed.us</cntemail>
</cntinfo>
</ptcontac>
<native>Microsoft Windows XP Version 5.1 (Build 2600) Service Pack 2; ESRI ArcCatalog 9.1.0.722</native>
</idinfo>
<dataqual>
<logic>Unknown</logic>
<complete>Unknown</complete>
<lineage>
<procstep>
<procdesc>Overstory Tree Measurements: All trees larger than 10 centimeters were tagged and measured on one 0.2-acre (1/5-acre) circular plot per treatment plot in February of 2005. Measurements included DBH to the nearest 0.1 centimeter of every tree and total height to the nearest 0.1 meter of a subsample of trees. These plots will be remeasured periodically.</procdesc>
<procdate>2005</procdate>
<proccont>
<cntinfo>
<cntperp>
<cntper>Kenneth Outcalt</cntper>
<cntorg>USDA FOREST SERVICE, SOUTHERN RESEARCH STATION, RWU-4104</cntorg>
</cntperp>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
<address>
320 Green Street
Forestry Sciences Lab
</address>
<city>Athens</city>
<state>GA</state>
<postal>30602-2044</postal>
<country>USA</country>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>706-559-4309</cntvoice>
<cntfax>706-559-4317</cntfax>
<cntemail>koutcalt@fs.fed.us</cntemail>
</cntinfo>
</proccont>
</procstep>
<procstep>
<procdesc>
Midstory Tree Measurements
All trees less than 10 centimeters DBH but at least 1.37 meters tall (breast height) were counted on ten 1/300-acre circular plots on each treatment plot. Plots were positioned at the ends of the vegetation transects. Counts of stems were recorded by diameter class (0-1" , 1-2" , 2-3" , 3-4" ). An estimate of total height was made for diameter class.
</procdesc>
<procdate>2005</procdate>
<proccont>
<cntinfo>
<cntperp>
<cntper>Kenneth Outcalt</cntper>
<cntorg>USDA FOREST SERVICE, SOUTHERN RESEARCH STATION, RWU-4104</cntorg>
</cntperp>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
<address>
320 Green Street
Forestry Sciences Lab
</address>
<city>Athens</city>
<state>GA</state>
<postal>30602-2044</postal>
<country>USA</country>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>706-559-4309</cntvoice>
<cntfax>706-559-4317</cntfax>
<cntemail>koutcalt@fs.fed.us</cntemail>
</cntinfo>
</proccont>
</procstep>
<procstep>
<procdesc>
Understory Vegetation Measurements
Five 50-foot transects are laid out on each treatment plot. The transects are oriented perpendicular to Tiger Corner Road and are 10 meters apart. The beginning point of the first transect is located on a 45 degree angle (NOT AN AZIMUTH OF 45 DEGREES) from the lower left corner of each plot if you're standing on Tiger Corner Road looking into the plot for a distance of 42.4 meters. This allows for a 20-meter buffer strip between the transects and the fireline. Transect #1 runs on 57 degrees (for plots on the northeast side of Tiger Corner Road- 237 degrees for plots on the opposite side of the road) for 50 feet. The beginning point of Transect #2 is located 10 meters on an azimuth of 147 degrees (for plots on the northeast side of Tiger Corner Road - 327 degrees for plots on the opposite side of the road). Transect #2 runs parallel to Transect #1. Transects 3-5 are located in the same fashion. The transect ends closer to the road are labeled as such: 1S, 2S, 3S, 4S, and 5S. The ends further away from the road are labeled: 1N, 2N, 3N, 4N, and 5N. During vegetation measurement a tape is stretched from the S end to the N end of a transect. The number of 1/2-foot segments in which each species occurs is recorded. If a species is found more than once in a segment, it is still only counted as "1". Since there are 100 1/2-foot segments in each transect, this species count translates to percentage. Species recorded are less than breast height. Each transect end (marked with an aluminum conduit stake) also serves as the center point for the sapling or midstory 1/300-acre plots. 3N serves as the center of the 1/5-acre overstory measurement plot.
</procdesc>
<procdate>2005</procdate>
<proccont>
<cntinfo>
<cntperp>
<cntper>Kenneth Outcalt</cntper>
<cntorg>USDA FOREST SERVICE, SOUTHERN RESEARCH STATION, RWU-4104</cntorg>
</cntperp>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
<address>
320 Green Street
Forestry Sciences Lab
</address>
<city>Athens</city>
<state>GA</state>
<postal>30602-2044</postal>
<country>USA</country>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>706-559-4309</cntvoice>
<cntfax>706-559-4317</cntfax>
<cntemail>koutcalt@fs.fed.us</cntemail>
</cntinfo>
</proccont>
</procstep>
<procstep>
<procdesc>
Forest Floor Measurements
Samples of the forest floor are taken each year before burning. A square meter PVC frame is placed 3 meters from the ends of each transect. From 1S you would measure 3 meters from the stake (along the same axis as the transect) and drop the frame to your right as you look along the transect toward 1N. Subsequent samples are located the same way at each transect end stake. At each square meter sample estimations of percent cover for live woody, dead woody, vines, herbaceous (grass, forbs, etc.) are made. Also the percentage of herbaceous that is swithcane is recorded. Average heights in meters are estimated for live woody and live herbaceous. Number of cones is recorded. Litter (L+F) is measured at each of the four sides of the frame and averaged. Litter is measured to the nearest 0.1 centimeter. Two additional samples will be likewise estimated but these two will also be clipped and brought back to the lab for oven drying and weighing to determine pre-burn fuel loading. The two clip plots will be located 6 meters from the end stakes of different transects each year. Following burning, the samples will be revisited to record percentage of the area burned and to measure the remaining litter depth.
</procdesc>
<procdate>2005</procdate>
<proccont>
<cntinfo>
<cntperp>
<cntper>Kenneth Outcalt</cntper>
<cntorg>USDA FOREST SERVICE, SOUTHERN RESEARCH STATION, RWU-4104</cntorg>
</cntperp>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
<address>
320 Green Street
Forestry Sciences Lab
</address>
<city>Athens</city>
<state>GA</state>
<postal>30602-2044</postal>
<country>USA</country>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>706-559-4309</cntvoice>
<cntfax>706-559-4317</cntfax>
<cntemail>koutcalt@fs.fed.us</cntemail>
</cntinfo>
</proccont>
</procstep>
</lineage>
</dataqual>
<eainfo>
<overview>
<eaover>Entity - hazardous fuel loads</eaover>
<eadetcit>unknown</eadetcit>
</overview>
</eainfo>
<distinfo>
<distrib>
<cntinfo>
<cntperp>
<cntper>Kenneth Outcalt</cntper>
<cntorg>USDA FOREST SERVICE, SOUTHERN RESEARCH STATION, RWU-4104</cntorg>
</cntperp>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
<address>
320 Green Street
Forestry Sciences Lab
</address>
<city>Athens</city>
<state>GA</state>
<postal>30602-2044</postal>
<country>USA</country>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>706-559-4309</cntvoice>
<cntfax>706-559-4317</cntfax>
<cntemail>koutcalt@fs.fed.us</cntemail>
</cntinfo>
</distrib>
<resdesc>Spreadsheet</resdesc>
<distliab>No warranty expressed or implied is made regarding the accuracy or utility of the data for general or scientific purposes, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty. This disclaimer applies both to individual use of the data and aggregate use with other data.  It is strongly recommended that these data are directly acquired from the originator(s) of the data, and not indirectly through other sources which may have changed the data in some way.  It is also strongly recommended that careful attention be paid to the contents of the metadata file associated with these data.  The distributor(s) shall not be held liable for improper or incorrect use of the data described and/or contained herein.</distliab>
</distinfo>
<metainfo>
<metd>20051221</metd>
<metc>
<cntinfo>
<cntorgp>
<cntorg>NBII - Southern Appalachian Information Node</cntorg>
<cntper>Fred Rascoe</cntper>
</cntorgp>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
<address>1009 Commerce Park Dr, #150</address>
<city>Oak Ridge</city>
<state>TN</state>
<postal>37830</postal>
<country>USA</country>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>865-298-1227</cntvoice>
<cntemail>frascoe@iiaweb.com</cntemail>
</cntinfo>
</metc>
<metstdn>Biological Data Profile of the FGDC Content Standards for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
<metstdv>FGDC-STD-001.1-1999</metstdv>
<mettc>local time</mettc>
<metac>none</metac>
<metuc>none</metuc>
</metainfo>
<mercury><begdate>19580101</begdate><enddate>20051231</enddate><htmlurl>http://mercury.ornl.gov/metadata/nbii/html/frames/www.nbii.gov_metadata_mdata_frames_nbii_frames_d_carolina.html</htmlurl><LTER-Site>frames</LTER-Site></mercury></metadata>
