<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<metadata><Source>http://www.nbii.gov/metadata/mdata/FloridaFWC/fwc_fwri_d_roads.sgml</Source>
<idinfo>
<citation>
<citeinfo>
<origin>United States Department of Commerce, Economics and Statistics Administration, Bureau of the Census, Geography Division, Data User Services Division, Topologically Integrated Geographic Encoding and Referencing system (TIGER) staff</origin>
<pubdate>2000</pubdate>
<pubtime>Unknown</pubtime>
<title>Florida Detailed Roads</title>
<geoform>maps data</geoform>
</citeinfo>
</citation>
<descript>
<abstract>This GIS data set represents the roads in Florida as lines.  These data were created from the US Census Bureau's Topologically Integrated Geographic Encoding and Referencing system (TIGER) files by Environmental Systems Research Institute (ESRI).  This data set also contains information that will allow it to be used for geocoding (address matching).</abstract>
<purpose>This data set represents that road features of the state of Florida.  These data are good for the visual display of local roads, however coordinate accuracy is only 1:100000 scale.</purpose>
<supplinf>
Prior to July 1, 2004, the Fish and Wildlife Research Institute (FWRI) was known as the Florida Marine Research Institute (FMRI). The institute name has not been changed in historical data sets or references to work completed by the Florida Marine Research Institute. The institute name has been changed in references to ongoing research, new research, and contact information.
The positional accuracy varies with the source materials used, but generally the information is no better than the established National Map Accuracy Standards for 1:100,000-scale maps from the U.S. Geological Survey (USGS).
(previous geoform was 'vector digital data')</supplinf>
</descript>
<timeperd>
<timeinfo>
<sngdate>
<caldate>2000</caldate>
<time>Unknown</time>
</sngdate>
</timeinfo>
<current>publication date</current>
</timeperd>
<status>
<progress>Complete</progress>
<update>As needed</update>
</status>
<spdom>
<bounding>
<westbc>-87.636209</westbc>
<eastbc>-79.872207</eastbc>
<northbc>31.042372</northbc>
<southbc>24.506823</southbc>
</bounding>
</spdom>
<keywords>
<theme>
<themekt>FWRItheme</themekt>
<themekey>GIS</themekey>
<themekey>mapping</themekey>
<themekey>transportation</themekey>
<themekey>census</themekey>
</theme>
<theme>
<themekt>ISO 19115 Topic Category</themekt>
<themekey>transportation</themekey>
</theme>
<place>
<placekt>FWRIplace</placekt>
<placekey>Florida</placekey>
<placekey>northeast Florida</placekey>
<placekey>northwest Florida</placekey>
<placekey>southwest Florida</placekey>
<placekey>statewide</placekey>
<placekey>southeast Florida</placekey>
<placekey>south Florida</placekey>
<placekey>north Florida</placekey>
<placekey>east coast of Florida</placekey>
<placekey>west coast of Florida</placekey>
</place>
<place>
<placekt>FWC Region</placekt>
<placekey>FWC Region-North Central</placekey>
<placekey>FWC Region-Northeast</placekey>
<placekey>FWC Region-Northwest</placekey>
<placekey>FWC Region-South</placekey>
<placekey>FWC Region-Southwest</placekey>
</place>
<place>
<placekt>Water Management Districts</placekt>
<placekey>Northwest Florida Water Management District</placekey>
<placekey>South Florida Water Management District</placekey>
<placekey>Southwest Florida Water Management District</placekey>
<placekey>St. Johns River Water Management District</placekey>
<placekey>Suwannee River Water Management District</placekey>
</place>
</keywords>
<accconst>All data must be verified by Principal Investigator or Group Database Analyst prior to release.  It is strongly recommended that this data is directly acquired from FWC and not indirectly through other sources which may have changed the data in some way. FWC makes no claims as to the data's suitability for other purposes.</accconst>
<useconst>FWC-FWRI and the originator of the data must be credited. This is not a survey data set and should not be utilized as such. These data are not to be used for navigation. Acknowledgement of the FWC-FWRI (Florida Fish and Wildlife Conservation Commission-Fish and Wildlife Research Institute) as the data source would be appreciated in any products developed from these data, and such acknowledgment as is standard for citation and legal practices for data source is expected by users of this data.  Please cite the original metadata when using portions of the record to create a similar record of slightly altered data, such as reprojection. If any data are modified or adjusted, please share the edited information with FWC. Users should be aware that comparison with other data sets for the same area from other time periods may be inaccurate due to inconsistencies resulting from changes in mapping conventions, data collection, and computer processes over time. FWC shall not be liable for improper or incorrect use of this data. These data are not legal documents and are not to be used as such.  This is not a survey data set and should not be utilized as such. These data are not to be used for navigation.</useconst>
<ptcontac>
<cntinfo>
<cntperp>
<cntper>GIS Data Librarian</cntper>
<cntorg>FWC-FWRI (Florida Fish and Wildlife Conservation Commission-Fish and Wildlife Research Institute)</cntorg>
</cntperp>
<cntpos>GIS Data Librarian</cntpos>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
<address>
Fish and Wildlife Research Institute
100 Eighth Avenue Southeast
</address>
<city>St. Petersburg</city>
<state>Florida</state>
<postal>33701</postal>
<country>USA</country>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>727-896-8626</cntvoice>
<cntfax>727-893-1679</cntfax>
<cntemail>GISLibrarian@MyFWC.com</cntemail>
<hours>8:00 a.m.-5:00 p.m. Eastern time</hours>
</cntinfo>
</ptcontac>
<datacred>ESRI, US Census Bureau</datacred>
<secinfo>
<secsys>FWRI-DC</secsys>
<secclass>Available without restriction.</secclass>
<sechandl>Available without restriction.</sechandl>
</secinfo>
<native>Microsoft Windows 2000 Version 5.0 (Build 2195) Service Pack 2; ESRI ArcCatalog 8.1.2.671</native>
</idinfo>
<dataqual>
<attracc>
<attraccr>All entities and attributes have been identified and documented.  The accuracy of the attributes has not been verified by FWRI.</attraccr>
</attracc>
<logic>unknown</logic>
<complete>unknown</complete>
<posacc>
<horizpa>
<horizpar>Positional accuracy has not been verified by FWRI.</horizpar>
</horizpa>
</posacc>
<lineage>
<srcinfo>
<srccite>
<citeinfo>
<origin>US Census Bureau</origin>
<pubdate>2000</pubdate>
<title>TIGER/Line Files, 2000</title>
<othercit>904/487-0400</othercit>
</citeinfo>
</srccite>
<srcscale>100000</srcscale>
<typesrc>Tiger line files</typesrc>
<srctime>
<timeinfo>
<sngdate>
<caldate>2000</caldate>
<time>Unknown</time>
</sngdate>
</timeinfo>
<srccurr>publication date</srccurr>
</srctime>
<srccitea>Census data</srccitea>
<srccontr>unknown</srccontr>
</srcinfo>
<procstep>
<procdesc>The data were downloaded from ESRI's Web site as county shapefiles, then merged into a statewide roads data set.  The data were them projected form geographic to Albers NAD 83.  FWRI corrected the positional accuracy of the Skyway Bridge based on 1999 DOQQs.  Then the data were loaded into ArcSDE.</procdesc>
<srcused>Census data</srcused>
<procdate>2002-2003</procdate>
<proccont>
<cntinfo>
<cntperp>
<cntper>GIS Data Librarian</cntper>
<cntorg>FWC-FWRI (Florida Fish and Wildlife Conservation Commission-Fish and Wildlife Research Institute)</cntorg>
</cntperp>
<cntpos>GIS Data Librarian</cntpos>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
<address>
Fish and Wildlife Research Institute
100 Eighth Avenue Southeast
</address>
<city>St. Petersburg</city>
<state>Florida</state>
<postal>33701</postal>
<country>USA</country>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>727-896-8626</cntvoice>
<cntfax>727-893-1679</cntfax>
<cntemail>GISLibrarian@MyFWC.com</cntemail>
<hours>8:00 a.m.-5:00 p.m. Eastern time</hours>
</cntinfo>
</proccont>
</procstep>
</lineage>
</dataqual>
<spdoinfo>
<direct>Vector</direct>
<ptvctinf>
<sdtsterm>
<sdtstype>String</sdtstype>
<ptvctcnt>1369388</ptvctcnt>
</sdtsterm>
</ptvctinf>
</spdoinfo>
<spref>
<horizsys>
<planar>
<mapproj>
<mapprojn>Albers Conical Equal Area</mapprojn>
<albers>
<stdparll>24</stdparll>
<stdparll>31.5</stdparll>
<longcm>-84</longcm>
<latprjo>24</latprjo>
<feast>400000</feast>
<fnorth>0</fnorth>
</albers>
</mapproj>
<planci>
<plance>Coordinate Pair</plance>
<coordrep>
<absres>0.002048</absres>
<ordres>0.002048</ordres>
</coordrep>
<plandu>meters</plandu>
</planci>
</planar>
<geodetic>
<horizdn>North American Datum of 1983</horizdn>
<ellips>Geodetic Reference System 80</ellips>
<semiaxis>6378137</semiaxis>
<denflat>298.257222</denflat>
</geodetic>
</horizsys>
</spref>
<eainfo>
<detailed>
<enttyp>
<enttypl>FMRI.roads_tiger_100k_2000</enttypl>
<enttypd>Road data in line format.</enttypd>
<enttypds>Producer defined</enttypds>
</enttyp>
<attr>
<attrlabl>CENSUS1</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Unknown field.  All features have '0' in this field.</attrdef>
<attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<udom>Unknown field.  All features have '0' in this field.</udom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>CENSUS2</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Unknown field.  All features have '0' in this field.</attrdef>
<attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<udom>Unknown field.  All features have '0' in this field.</udom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>CFCC</attrlabl>
<attrdef>
A census feature class code (CFCC) is used to identify the most noticeable characteristic of a feature.  The CFCC, as used in the TIGER/Line ® files, is a three-character code. The first character is a letter describing the feature class; the second character is a number describing the major category; and the third character is a number describing the minor category.
A11 = Primary road with limited access or interstate highway, unseparated
A12 = Primary road with limited access or interstate highway, unseparated, in tunnel
A13 = Primary road with limited access or interstate highway, unseparated, underpassing
A14 = Primary road with limited access or interstate highway, unseparated, with rail line in center
A15 = Primary road with limited access or interstate highway, separated
A21 = Primary road without limited access, US highways, unseparated
A22 = Primary road without limited access, US highways, unseparated, in tunnel
A23 = Primary road without limited access, US highways, unseparated, underpassing
A24 = Primary road without limited access, US highways, unseparated, with rail line in center
A25 = Primary road without limited access, US highways, separated
A31 = Secondary and connecting road, state highways, unseparated
A32 = Secondary and connecting road, state highways, unseparated, in tunnel
A33 = Secondary and connecting road, state highways, unseparated, underpassing
A35 = Secondary and connecting road, state highways, separated
A38 = Secondary and connecting road, state and county highway, separated, with rail line in center
A41 = Local, neighborhood, and rural road, city street, unseparated
A42 = Local, neighborhood, and rural road, city street, unseparated, in tunnel
A43 = Local, neighborhood, and rural road, city street, unseparated, underpassing
A44 = Local, neighborhood, and rural road, city street, unseparated, with rail line in center
A45 = Local, neighborhood, and rural road, city street, separated
A46 = Local, neighborhood, and rural road, city street, separated, in tunnel
A47 = Local, neighborhood, and rural road, city street, separated, underpassing
A48 = Local, neighborhood, and rural road, city street, separated, with rail line in center
A51 = Vehicular trail, road passable only by 4WD vehicle, unseparated
A60 = Special road feature, major category used when the minor category could not be determined
A62 = Traffic circle, the portion of a road or intersection of roads forming a roundabout
A63 = Access ramp, the portion of a road that forms a cloverleaf or limited-access interchange
A64 = Service drive, the road or portion of a road that provides access to businesses, facilities, and rest areas along a limited-access highway; this frontage road may intersect other roads and be named
A65 = Ferry crossing, the representation of a route over water that connects roads on opposite shores; used by ships carrying automobiles or people
A70 = Other thoroughfare, major category used when the minor category could not be determined
A71 = Walkway or trail for pedestrians, usually unnamed
A73 = Alley, road for service vehicles, usually unnamed, located at the rear of buildings and property
A74 = Driveway or service road, usually privately owned and unnamed, used as access to residences, trailer parks, and apartment complexes, or as access to logging areas, oil rigs, ranches, farms, and park lands
P21 = Provisional primary road without limited access, US highways, unseparated
P41 = Provisional local, neighborhood, and rural road, city street, unseparated
P63 = Provisional access ramp, the portion of a road that forms a cloverleaf or limited-access interchange
P74 = Provisional driveway or service road, usually privately owned and unnamed, used as access to residences, trailer parks, and apartment complexes, or as access to logging areas, oil rigs, ranches, farms, and park lands
</attrdef>
<attrdefs>For more information about the meanings of these codes refer to the U.S. Census Bureau's TIGER/Line Files Redistricting 2000 Technical Documentation</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<udom>See Attribute definition</udom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>CFCC1</attrlabl>
<attrdef>First letter of CFCC code.  The first character is a letter describing the feature class.</attrdef>
<attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>A</edomv>
<edomvd>Roads</edomvd>
<edomvds>U.S. Census Bureau</edomvds>
</edom>
<edom>
<edomv>P</edomv>
<edomvd>Provisional features are those streets that were added from reference sources or other programs in preparation for Census 2000, but were not field verified by census staff during field operations or through the use of aerial photography or imagery.</edomvd>
<edomvds>U.S. Census Bureau</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>CFCC2</attrlabl>
<attrdef>
First and second digits of the CFCC code.
The first character is a letter describing the feature class and the second character is a number describing the major category.
</attrdef>
<attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>A1</edomv>
<edomvd>
Interstate highways and some toll highways are in this category (A1) and are distinguished by the presence of
interchanges. These highways are accessed by way of ramps and have multiple lanes of traffic. The opposing traffic lanes are divided by a median strip. The TIGER/Line ® files may depict these opposing traffic lanes as two distinct lines in which case, the road is called separated.
</edomvd>
<edomvds>U.S. Census Bureau</edomvds>
</edom>
<edom>
<edomv>A2</edomv>
<edomvd>
This category (A2) includes nationally and regionally important highways that do not have limited access
as required by category A1. It consists mainly of US highways, but may include some state highways and county highways that connect cities and larger towns. A road in this category must be hard-surface (concrete or asphalt). It has intersections with other roads, may be divided or undivided, and have multi-lane or single-lane characteristics.
</edomvd>
<edomvds>U.S. Census Bureau</edomvds>
</edom>
<edom>
<edomv>A3</edomv>
<edomvd>This category (A3) includes mostly state highways, but may include some county highways that connect smaller towns, subdivisions, and neighborhoods. The roads in this category generally are smaller than roads in Category A2, must be hard-surface (concrete or asphalt), and are usually undivided with single-lane characteristics. These roads usually have a local name along with a route number and intersect with many other roads and driveways.</edomvd>
<edomvds>U.S. Census Bureau</edomvds>
</edom>
<edom>
<edomv>A4</edomv>
<edomvd>
A road in this category (A4) is used for local traffic and usually has a single lane of traffic in each direction. In
an urban area, this is a neighborhood road and street that is not a thoroughfare belonging in categories A2 or A3. In a rural area, this is a short-distance road connecting the smallest towns; the road may or may not have a state or county route number. Scenic park roads, unimproved or unpaved roads, and industrial roads are included in this category. Most roads in the Nation are classified as A4 roads.
</edomvd>
<edomvds>U.S. Census Bureau</edomvds>
</edom>
<edom>
<edomv>A5</edomv>
<edomvd>A road in this category (A5) is usable only by four-wheel drive vehicles, is usually a one-lane dirt trail, and is found almost exclusively in very rural areas. Sometimes the road is called a fire road or logging road and may include an abandoned railroad grade where the tracks have been removed. Minor, unpaved roads usable by ordinary cars and trucks belong in category A4, not A5.</edomvd>
<edomvds>U.S. Census Bureau</edomvds>
</edom>
<edom>
<edomv>A6</edomv>
<edomvd>This category (A6) includes roads, portions of a road, intersections of a road, or the ends of a road that are parts of the vehicular highway system and have separately identifiable characteristics.</edomvd>
<edomvds>U.S. Census Bureau</edomvds>
</edom>
<edom>
<edomv>A7</edomv>
<edomvd>
A road in this category (A7) is not part of the vehicular highway system. It is used by bicyclists or pedestrians, and is
typically inaccessible to mainstream motor traffic except for private-owner and service vehicles. This category includes foot and hiking trails located on park and forest land, as well as stairs or walkways that follow a road right-of-way and have names similar to road names.
</edomvd>
<edomvds>U.S. Census Bureau</edomvds>
</edom>
<edom>
<edomv>P2</edomv>
<edomvd>Provisional category 2 roads.</edomvd>
<edomvds>U.S. Census Bureau</edomvds>
</edom>
<edom>
<edomv>P4</edomv>
<edomvd>Provisional category 4 roads.</edomvd>
<edomvds>U.S. Census Bureau</edomvds>
</edom>
<edom>
<edomv>P6</edomv>
<edomvd>Provisional category 6 roads.</edomvd>
<edomvds>U.S. Census Bureau</edomvds>
</edom>
<edom>
<edomv>P7</edomv>
<edomvd>Provisional category 7 roads.</edomvd>
<edomvds>U.S. Census Bureau</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>FEDIRP</attrlabl>
<attrdef>
Direction (Prefix)
Direction consists of a 2-character abbreviation, left-justified in the data fields, and is used for road features only.
Abbreviation Explanations:
( blank) = No Direction
N = North
S = South
E = East
W = West
NE = Northeast
NW = Northwest
SE = Southeast
SW = Southwest
NO = Northwest
SO = Southwest
O = West
EX = Extension
</attrdef>
<attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>(blank)</edomv>
<edomvd>No direction</edomvd>
<edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
</edom>
<edom>
<edomv>N</edomv>
<edomvd>North</edomvd>
<edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
</edom>
<edom>
<edomv>S</edomv>
<edomvd>South</edomvd>
<edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
</edom>
<edom>
<edomv>E</edomv>
<edomvd>East</edomvd>
<edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
</edom>
<edom>
<edomv>W</edomv>
<edomvd>West</edomvd>
<edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
</edom>
<edom>
<edomv>NE</edomv>
<edomvd>Northeast</edomvd>
<edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
</edom>
<edom>
<edomv>NW</edomv>
<edomvd>Northwest</edomvd>
<edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
</edom>
<edom>
<edomv>SE</edomv>
<edomvd>Southeast</edomvd>
<edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
</edom>
<edom>
<edomv>SW</edomv>
<edomvd>Southwest</edomvd>
<edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
</edom>
<edom>
<edomv>NO</edomv>
<edomvd>Northwest</edomvd>
<edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
</edom>
<edom>
<edomv>SO</edomv>
<edomvd>Southwest</edomvd>
<edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
</edom>
<edom>
<edomv>O</edomv>
<edomvd>West</edomvd>
<edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
</edom>
<edom>
<edomv>EX</edomv>
<edomvd>Extension</edomvd>
<edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>FEDIRS</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Unknown</attrdef>
<attrdefs>U.S. Census Bureau</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<udom>Unknown</udom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>FENAME</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Feature names consist of a 30-character text string with words separated by blanks. Feature names contain upper- and lower-case characters. The feature name is truncated if it is over 30 characters long.</attrdef>
<attrdefs>U.S. Census Bureau</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<udom>Feature names consist of a 30-character text string with words separated by blanks. Feature names contain upper- and lower-case characters. The feature name is truncated if it is over 30 characters long.</udom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>FETYPE</attrlabl>
<attrdef>The feature type field for road features consists of a 4-character text string.</attrdef>
<attrdefs>U.S. Census Bureau</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<udom>The feature type field for road features consists of a 4-character text string.</udom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>FRADDL</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Start number of address range on the left side of the street.</attrdef>
<attrdefs>U.S. Census Bureau</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<udom>Start number of address range on the left side of the street.</udom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>FRADDR</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Start number of address range on the right side of the street.</attrdef>
<attrdefs>U.S. Census Bureau</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<udom>Start number of address range on the right side of the street.</udom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>OBJECTID</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Internal feature number.</attrdef>
<attrdefs>ESRI</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<udom>Sequential unique whole numbers that are automatically generated.</udom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Shape</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Feature geometry.</attrdef>
<attrdefs>ESRI</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<udom>Coordinates defining the features.</udom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Shape.LEN</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Length of line (in meters).  Automatically calculated by SDE.</attrdef>
<attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<udom>Length of line (in meters).  Automatically calculated by SDE.</udom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>SOURCE</attrlabl>
<attrdef>
Original source of the data.
A = Updated 1980 GBF/DIME-File
B = USGS 1:100,000-Scale DLG-3 File
J = Pre-1990 Census Updates
K = Post-1990 Census Updates (1990-1994)
L = Pre-Census 2000 Local Official Updates (1995-Census 2000)
M = Pre-Census 2000 field Operations (1995-Census 2000)
N = Pre-Census 2000 Office Update Operations (1995-Census 2000)
O = Post-Census 2000 (2000-2002)
</attrdef>
<attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>A</edomv>
<edomvd>Updated 1980 GBF/DIME-File</edomvd>
<edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
</edom>
<edom>
<edomv>B</edomv>
<edomvd>USGS 1:100,000-Scale DLG-3 File</edomvd>
<edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
</edom>
<edom>
<edomv>J</edomv>
<edomvd>Pre-1990 Census Updates</edomvd>
<edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
</edom>
<edom>
<edomv>K</edomv>
<edomvd>Post-1990 Census Updates (1990-1994)</edomvd>
<edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
</edom>
<edom>
<edomv>L</edomv>
<edomvd>Pre-Census 2000 Local Official Updates (1995-Census 2000)</edomvd>
<edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
</edom>
<edom>
<edomv>M</edomv>
<edomvd>Pre-Census 2000 field Operations (1995-Census 2000)</edomvd>
<edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
</edom>
<edom>
<edomv>N</edomv>
<edomvd>Pre-Census 2000 Office Update Operations (1995-Census 2000)</edomvd>
<edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
</edom>
<edom>
<edomv>O</edomv>
<edomvd>Post-Census 2000 (2000-2002)</edomvd>
<edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>TLID</attrlabl>
<attrdef>
The TIGER/Line ® files store address range information in two record types. Record Type 1 contains the basic complete chain attributes, including one basic address range. Record Type 6 stores the additional ranges when the complete chain has more than one range on one or both sides.
The TLID field links Record Types 1 and 6. Since a complete chain can have more than one set of address ranges, multiple Type 6 records can exist with the same TLID.
</attrdef>
<attrdefs>U.S. Census Bureau</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<udom>
The TIGER/Line ® files store address range information in two record types. Record Type 1 contains the basic complete chain attributes, including one basic address range. Record Type 6 stores the additional ranges when the complete chain has more than one range on one or both sides.
The TLID field links Record Types 1 and 6. Since a complete chain can have more than one set of address ranges, multiple Type 6 records can exist with the same TLID.
</udom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>TOADDL</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Ending number of address range on the left side of the street.</attrdef>
<attrdefs>U.S. Census Bureau</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<udom>Ending number of address range on the left side of the street.</udom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>TOADDR</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Ending number of address range on the right side of the street.</attrdef>
<attrdefs>U.S. Census Bureau</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<udom>Ending number of address range on the right side of the street.</udom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>ZIPL</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Zip code on the left side of the street.</attrdef>
<attrdefs>U.S. Census Bureau</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<udom>Zip code on the left side of the street.</udom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>ZIPR</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Zip code on the right side of the street.</attrdef>
<attrdefs>U.S. Census Bureau</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<udom>Zip code on the right side of the street.</udom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
</detailed>
<overview>
<eaover>Attributes describe the name and type of roads.  Attributes for geocoding are also present.</eaover>
<eadetcit>Attributes describe the name and type of roads.  Attributes for geocoding are also present.</eadetcit>
</overview>
</eainfo>
<distinfo>
<distrib>
<cntinfo>
<cntperp>
<cntper>GIS Data Librarian</cntper>
<cntorg>FWC-FWRI (Florida Fish and Wildlife Conservation Commission-Fish and Wildlife Research Institute)</cntorg>
</cntperp>
<cntpos>GIS Data Librarian</cntpos>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
<address>
Fish and Wildlife Research Institute
100 Eighth Avenue Southeast
</address>
<city>St. Petersburg</city>
<state>Florida</state>
<postal>33701</postal>
<country>USA</country>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>727-896-8626</cntvoice>
<cntfax>727-893-1679</cntfax>
<cntemail>GISLibrarian@MyFWC.com</cntemail>
<hours>8:00 a.m.-5:00 p.m. Eastern time</hours>
</cntinfo>
</distrib>
<resdesc>FMRI.roads_tiger_100k_2000</resdesc>
<distliab>This data set is in the public domain, and the recipient may not assert any proprietary rights thereto nor represent it to anyone as other than a FWC-FWRI produced data set; it is provided "as-is" without warranty of any kind, including, but not limited to, the implied warranties of merchantability and fitness for a particular purpose. The user assumes all responsibility for the accuracy and suitability of this data set for a specific application. In no event will the staff of the Fish and Wildlife Research Institute be liable for any damages, including lost profits, lost savings, or other incidental or consequential damages arising from the use of or the inability to use this data set.</distliab>
<stdorder>
<digform>
<digtinfo>
<formname>SHP</formname>
</digtinfo>
<digtopt>
<onlinopt>
<computer>
<networka>
<networkr>http://ocean.floridamarine.org/mrgis</networkr>
</networka>
</computer>
</onlinopt>
</digtopt>
</digform>
<fees>None. However, persons or organizations requesting information must provide transfer media if FTP is not available and must pay express shipping costs if express shipping is required.</fees>
<ordering>Contact GIS Librarian by e-mail, telephone, or letter explaining which products are needed and providing a brief description of how the products will be used. Also, provide name and address of the person or organization requesting the products.</ordering>
<turnarnd>Usually within 10 business days, although, complex requests may take longer</turnarnd>
</stdorder>
<custom>Contact GIS Librarian</custom>
</distinfo>
<metainfo>
<metd>20030205</metd>
<metrd>20051129</metrd>
<metc>
<cntinfo>
<cntperp>
<cntper>GIS Data Librarian</cntper>
<cntorg>FWC-FWRI (Florida Fish and Wildlife Conservation Commission-Fish and Wildlife Research Institute)</cntorg>
</cntperp>
<cntpos>GIS Data Librarian</cntpos>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
<address>
Fish and Wildlife Research Institute
100 Eighth Avenue Southeast
</address>
<city>St. Petersburg</city>
<state>Florida</state>
<postal>33701</postal>
<country>USA</country>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>727-896-8626</cntvoice>
<cntfax>727-893-1679</cntfax>
<cntemail>GISLibrarian@MyFWC.com</cntemail>
<hours>8:00 a.m.-5:00 p.m. Eastern time</hours>
</cntinfo>
</metc>
<metstdn>FGDC Content Standards for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
<metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
<mettc>local time</mettc>
<metac>No restrictions on metadata.</metac>
<metuc>Metadata must be distributed with the data set.</metuc>
<metsi>
<metscs>FWRI-MC</metscs>
<metsc>Available</metsc>
<metshd>Metadata must be distributed with the data set.</metshd>
</metsi>
</metainfo>
<mercury><begdate>20000101</begdate><enddate>20001231</enddate><htmlurl>http://mercury.ornl.gov/metadata/nbii/html/ffwc/www.nbii.gov_metadata_mdata_FloridaFWC_fwc_fwri_d_roads.html</htmlurl><LTER-Site>ffwc</LTER-Site></mercury></metadata>
