<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<metadata><Source>http://www.nbii.gov/metadata/mdata/brd-bib/usgs_brd_fresc_b_sagrfood.sgml</Source>
<idinfo>
<citation>
<citeinfo>
<origin>Troy A. Wirth</origin>
<pubdate>2000</pubdate>
<title>Emergence, survival and reproduction of three species of forbs important to sage grouse nutrition in response to fire, microsite, and method of establishment</title>
<geoform>M.S. Thesis</geoform>
<pubinfo>
<pubplace>Corvallis, Oregon</pubplace>
<publish>Oregon State University</publish>
</pubinfo>
<othercit>
Science Information System Project #: 7028
Publication Control #: 695
</othercit>
</citeinfo>
</citation>
<descript>
<abstract>Since the turn of the century, the abundance, productivity, and range of the western subspecies of the sage grouse (Centrocercus urophasianus ssp. phaios) has declined. The US Fish and Wildlife Service listed the subspecies as a candidate for threatened and endangered status in 1985. The primary reasons for the species' decline include: (1) permanent loss of habitat because of agriculture, road building, reservoirs and mining operations; and (2) habitat degradation because of fire suppression, abusive livestock grazing, invasions of exotic annual plants plus reseeding of exotic perennial grasses. The optimum sage grouse habitat is an area dominated by sagebrush with significant cover of tall perennial grasses and forbs. Two field studies conducted in Oregon have shown that higher availability of forbs in the environment is correlated with higher reproductive success of sage grouse. This study will assess the revegetation suitability of Crepis occidentalis, Crepis modocensis and Astragalus purshii, highly favored sage grouse foods. We will evaluate each species' success in establishing using eight different planting treatments. We will measure emergence, survival and reproduction of each forb species to determine establishment success. The planting treatments will include all combinations of prescribed fire (burned, unburned), establishment method (seeding, transplanting) and microsite (mound, interspace).</abstract>
<purpose>Reporting research results</purpose>
<supplinf>
Extent of item: 99pp
Illustrative Matter:  tables, graphs, and maps
</supplinf>
</descript>
<timeperd>
<timeinfo>
<sngdate>
<caldate>2000</caldate>
</sngdate>
</timeinfo>
<current>publication date</current>
</timeperd>
<status>
<progress>Complete</progress>
<update>None planned</update>
</status>
<spdom>
<descgeog>Hart Mountain National Antelope Refuge</descgeog>
<bounding>
<westbc>-119.58</westbc>
<eastbc>-119.5</eastbc>
<northbc>42.61</northbc>
<southbc>42.53</southbc>
</bounding>
</spdom>
<keywords>
<theme>
<themekt>none</themekt>
<themekey>microsite</themekey>
<themekey>survival</themekey>
<themekey>forbs</themekey>
</theme>
<theme>
<themekt>Science Information System Controlled Vocabulary</themekt>
<themekey>Fire</themekey>
<themekey>Harvest Management</themekey>
<themekey>Grassland/Rangeland</themekey>
<themekey>Birds</themekey>
<themekey>National Wildlife Refuges</themekey>
<themekey>Sage grouse</themekey>
</theme>
<place>
<placekt>None</placekt>
<placekey>Hart Mountain National Antelope Refuge</placekey>
<placekey>Oregon</placekey>
<placekey>OR</placekey>
</place>
</keywords>
<taxonomy>
<keywtax>
<taxonkt>none</taxonkt>
<taxonkey>Plants</taxonkey>
</keywtax>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Kingdom</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Plantae</taxonrv>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Division</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Magnoliophyta</taxonrv>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Class</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Magnoliopsida</taxonrv>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Sub Class</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Asteridae</taxonrv>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Order</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Asterales</taxonrv>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Family</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Asteraceae</taxonrv>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Genus</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Crepis</taxonrv>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Species</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Crepis occidentalis</taxonrv>
<common>western hawksbeard</common>
</taxoncl>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Species</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Crepis modocensis</taxonrv>
<common>common hawksbeard</common>
</taxoncl>
</taxoncl>
</taxoncl>
</taxoncl>
</taxoncl>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Sub Class</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Rosidae</taxonrv>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Order</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Fabales</taxonrv>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Family</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Fabaceae</taxonrv>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Genus</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Astragalus</taxonrv>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Species</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Astragalus purshii</taxonrv>
<common>Pursh's milkvetch</common>
</taxoncl>
</taxoncl>
</taxoncl>
</taxoncl>
</taxoncl>
</taxoncl>
</taxoncl>
</taxoncl>
</taxonomy>
<accconst>None</accconst>
<useconst>None</useconst>
<ptcontac>
<cntinfo>
<cntperp>
<cntper>Pyke, David</cntper>
<cntorg>USGS Forest and Rangeland Ecosystem Science Center</cntorg>
</cntperp>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
<address>3200 SW Jefferson Way</address>
<city>Corvallis</city>
<state>OR</state>
<postal>97331</postal>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>541/750/7334</cntvoice>
<cntemail>david_a_pyke@usgs.gov</cntemail>
</cntinfo>
</ptcontac>
</idinfo>
<distinfo>
<distrib>
<cntinfo>
<cntorgp>
<cntorg>Olendorff Library</cntorg>
</cntorgp>
<cntpos>Librarian</cntpos>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
<address>
USGS FRESC Snake River Field Station
970 Lusk Street
</address>
<city>Boise</city>
<state>ID</state>
<postal>83706</postal>
<country>USA</country>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>208 426-5218</cntvoice>
<cntfax>208 426-5210</cntfax>
</cntinfo>
</distrib>
<resdesc>Publication Control #: 695</resdesc>
<distliab>
The USGS Forest and Rangeland Ecosystem Science Center and its research partners make every effort to provide and maintain accurate, complete, usable, and timely information. However, some USGS data and information may, of necessity, be preliminary in nature. These data and information are provided with the understanding that they are not guaranteed to be correct or complete. Users are cautioned to consider carefully the provisional nature of these data and information before using them for decisions that concern personal or public safety or the conduct of business that involves substantial monetary or operational consequences. It is also strongly recommended that careful attention be paid to the contents of the metadata file associated with these data and information. Conclusions drawn from, or actions undertaken on the basis of, such data and information are the sole responsibility of the user.
USGS-authored or produced data and information are in the public domain. Whereas the content of many USGS publications and other information resources are in the public domain, some USGS products contain material that is copyrighted by others and used by the USGS with permission. Users of this information may need to obtain permission from the copyright owner for other uses. Furthermore, some non-USGS data, products, and information referred to may be protected under U.S. and foreign copyright laws. Users may need to obtain permission from the copyright owner to acquire, use, reproduce, or distribute these materials. It is the sole responsibility of the user of the information to secure all necessary permission.
</distliab>
<stdorder>
<nondig>Publications are available as reprints, reports, pamphlets, or brochures.</nondig>
<fees>None</fees>
<ordering>Request specific publications by reference number.</ordering>
</stdorder>
</distinfo>
<metainfo>
<metd>20010523</metd>
<metc>
<cntinfo>
<cntorgp>
<cntorg>USGS Forest and Rangeland Ecosystem Science Center (FRESC)</cntorg>
</cntorgp>
<cntpos>Library</cntpos>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
<address>
777 NW 9th St.
Suite 100
</address>
<city>Corvallis</city>
<state>OR</state>
<postal>97330</postal>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>541-750-1030</cntvoice>
<cntfax>541-750-1069</cntfax>
<cntemail>fresc_outreach@usgs.gov</cntemail>
</cntinfo>
</metc>
<metstdn>FGDC Biological Data Profile of the Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
<metstdv>FGDC-STD-001.1-1999</metstdv>
</metainfo>
<mercury><begdate>20000101</begdate><enddate>20001231</enddate><htmlurl>http://mercury.ornl.gov/metadata/nbii/html/brd/www.nbii.gov_metadata_mdata_brd-bib_usgs_brd_fresc_b_sagrfood.html</htmlurl><LTER-Site>brd</LTER-Site></mercury></metadata>
