<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<metadata><Source>http://www.nbii.gov/metadata/mdata/CBI/usgs_brd_cbi_d_detoveg.sgml</Source>
<idinfo>
<citation>
<citeinfo>
<origin>
U.S. Bureau of Reclamation, Remote Sensing and GIS Group,
and The Nature Conservancy
</origin>
<pubdate>19980310</pubdate>
<title>
Devils Tower National Monument Spatial Vegetation Data; Cover Type /
Association level of the National Vegetation Classification System
</title>
<geoform>maps data</geoform>
<serinfo>
<sername>USGS-NPS Vegetation Mapping Program</sername>
<issue>Devils Tower National Monument</issue>
</serinfo>
<pubinfo>
<pubplace>Denver CO</pubplace>
<publish>USGS, Biological Resources Division, Center for Biological Informatics</publish>
</pubinfo>
<othercit>Created under contract to USGS-BRD-CBI.</othercit>
<onlink>http://biology.usgs.gov/npsveg/deto/images/detoveg.gif</onlink>
<onlink>http://biology.usgs.gov/npsveg/ftp/vegmapping/deto/deto.exe</onlink>
<onlink>http://biology.usgs.gov/npsveg/ftp/vegmapping/deto/detosdts.exe</onlink>
<onlink>http://biology.usgs.gov/npsveg/ftp/vegmapping/deto/detobdy.exe</onlink>
<onlink>http://biology.usgs.gov/npsveg/ftp/vegmapping/deto/detobdysdts.exe</onlink>
</citeinfo>
</citation>
<descript>
<abstract>
The National Park Service (NPS), in conjunction with the Biological
Resources Division (BRD) of the U.S. Geological Survey (USGS), has
implemented a program to "develop a uniform hierarchical vegetation
methodology" at a national level. The program will also create
a geographic information system (GIS) database for the parks under its
management. The purpose of the data is to document the state of
vegetation within the NPS service area during the 1990's, thereby
providing a baseline study for further analysis at the Regional or
Service-wide level. The vegetation at Devils Tower National Monument
was mapped using 1:16,000 scale U.S. Forest Service Color Aerial
Photography acquired July 29, 1993. The mapping classification used
two separate classification systems. All natural vegetation used the
National Vegetation Classification System (NVCS) as a base. The vegetation
classification was created after extensive on site sampling and numerical
analysis. The vegetation map units were derived from the vegetation
classification. Other non-natural or cultural mapping units used the
Anderson Level II classification system. The mapped area includes a
buffer around the Monument boundary.
</abstract>
<purpose>
This mapping effort originates from a long-term vegetation monitoring
program that is part of a larger Inventory and Monitoring (I&amp;M) program
started by the National Park Service (NPS). I&amp;M goals are, among others,
to map the vegetation of all national parks and monuments and provide a
baseline inventory of vegetation. The I&amp;M program currently works in
close cooperation with the Biological Resources Division (BRD) of the
United States Geological Survey (USGS). The USGS/BRD continues overall
management and oversight of all ongoing mapping efforts in close
cooperation with the NPS.
</purpose>
<supplinf>
The purposes of the mapping effort are varied and include the
following: Provides support for NPS Resources Management. Promotes
vegetation-related research for both NPS and USGS/BRD. Provides
support for NPS Planning and Compliance. Adds to the information base
for NPS Interpretation. Assists in NPS Operations.
(previous geoform was 'map')</supplinf>
</descript>
<timeperd>
<timeinfo>
<sngdate>
<caldate>19950912</caldate>
</sngdate>
</timeinfo>
<current>Source photography date</current>
</timeperd>
<status>
<progress>Complete</progress>
<update>not applicable</update>
</status>
<spdom>
<bounding>
<westbc>-104.75</westbc>
<eastbc>-104.63</eastbc>
<northbc>44.63</northbc>
<southbc>44.5</southbc>
</bounding>
<descgeog>
Devils Tower National Monument and
about a 2 mile environ Wyoming, around Monument Boundaries - Black Hills,USA
</descgeog>
</spdom>
<keywords>
<theme>
<themekt>none</themekt>
<themekey>National Park Service</themekey>
<themekey>U.S. Geological Service</themekey>
<themekey>The Nature Conservancy</themekey>
<themekey>Aerial Information Systems</themekey>
<themekey>Center for Biological Informatics</themekey>
<themekey>land cover</themekey>
<themekey>vegetation</themekey>
<themekey>alliance</themekey>
<themekey>association</themekey>
<themekey>land use</themekey>
<themekey>Environmental System Research Institute</themekey>
</theme>
<place>
<placekt>None</placekt>
<placekey>Devils Tower National Monument</placekey>
<placekey>Black Hills</placekey>
<placekey>Wyoming</placekey>
<placekey>USA</placekey>
</place>
</keywords>
<taxonomy>
<keywtax>
<taxonkt>None</taxonkt>
<taxonkey>Plant Communities</taxonkey>
</keywtax>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Kingdom</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Plantae</taxonrv>
</taxoncl>
</taxonomy>
<accconst>None</accconst>
<useconst>
No warranty, expressed or implied, is made regarding the accuracy or
utility of the data on any other system or for general or scientific purposes.
Any person using the information presented here should fully understand
the data collection and compilation procedures, as described in the
metadata, before beginning analysis. The burden for determining fitness
for use lies entirely with the user.
</useconst>
<ptcontac>
<cntinfo>
<cntorgp>
<cntorg>
USGS Biological Resources Division, Center for Biological
Informatics
</cntorg>
<cntper>USGS-NPS Vegetation Mapping Program Coordinator</cntper>
</cntorgp>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>Physical Address</addrtype>
<address>USGS</address>
<address>Biological Resources Division, CBI</address>
<address>Building 810, Room 8000</address>
<city>Denver</city>
<state>Colorado</state>
<postal>80225-0046</postal>
<country>USA</country>
</cntaddr>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>Mailing Address</addrtype>
<address>USGS</address>
<address>Biological Resources Division, CBI</address>
<address>PO BOX 25046, DFC, MS302</address>
<city>Denver</city>
<state>Colorado</state>
<postal>80225-0046</postal>
<country>USA</country>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>(303) 202-4220</cntvoice>
<cntfax>303-202-4229</cntfax>
<cntfax>303-202-4219 (org)</cntfax>
<cntemail>gs-b-npsveg@usgs.gov</cntemail>
</cntinfo>
</ptcontac>
<browse>
<browsen>http://biology.usgs.gov/npsveg/deto/images/detoveg.gif</browsen>
<browsed>
52 Kbyte graphic in map composition
layout
</browsed>
<browset>GIF</browset>
</browse>
<datacred>USGS, NPS, U.S. BOR, TNC</datacred>
<native>UNIX-ARC/INFO</native>
</idinfo>
<dataqual>
<attracc>
<attraccr>
These data have a combined total accuracy of 81.6% (confidence interval
75.5% - 86.0%). Individual class accuracies range from 44.4 % to 100% in
both errors of commission and omission.
</attraccr>
</attracc>
<logic>
All polygon features are checked for topology using the ARC/INFO software.
Each polygon begins and ends at the same point with the node feature. All
nodes are checked for error so that there are no dangling features. There
are no duplicate lines or polygons. All nodes will snap together and close
polygons based on a specified tolerance. If the node is not with the
tolerance it is adjusted manually. The tests for logical consistency are
performed in ARC/INFO using certain commands.
</logic>
<complete>
All data that can be photo-interpreted is also digitized. This includes
features that fall into the NVCS vegetation classification and the Anderson
Level II classification. Minimum mapping unit is ostensibly .5 hectares but
some low frequency classes below the MMU are included.
</complete>
<posacc>
<horizpa>
<horizpar>
The horizontal positional accuracy is tested by visual comparison of digital
data to the source materials and verifying the location of the data
on-screen relative to other data layers in the same geographic area. The
base used for this mapping effort is a scanned and registered paper
orthophotograph. Visual examination of these data shows them to comply
(usually exceed) with national map accuracy standards for 1:24,000 scale
products. See Analysis of Accuracy Assessment Procedures.
</horizpar>
</horizpa>
<vertacc>
<vertaccr>There is no accuracy assessment for vertical position.</vertaccr>
</vertacc>
</posacc>
<lineage>
<method>
<methtype>Field</methtype>
<methodid>
<methkt>Ground truthing</methkt>
<methkey>GPS</methkey>
<methkey>field plots</methkey>
</methodid>
<methdesc>
Developmental of Programmatic and Technical Team:
This project required the combined expertise and oversight of several
organizations. Oversight and programmatic considerations are managed
by the Center for Biological Informatics of the Biological Resources
Division of the U.S. Geological Survey. The National Park Service
provided additional guidance. The technical responsibilities for the
mapping effort were divided between TNC and BOR. TNC responsibilities
and deliverables included the following: Create a vegetation
classification system based upon field species level data and
consistent with the Standard National Classification System at the
Alliance or Community Element level Provide documentation that
describes the national classes at the local and global levels, with
field keys, and field data in a *.dbf format. Provide technical
opinion to BOR as the mapping portion of the project proceeds. Provide
field notes and site descriptions BOR responsibilities and
deliverables included the following: Digital files of vegetation on
Compact (CD); including topology and labeling for height, density, and
pattern subclasses; location of field sample sites; and locations of
sites used for accuracy assessment in Arc/Info format Any ancillary
digital files developed during the mapping process Digital FGDC
compliant metadata file for each digital file delivered Annotated
field site photographs Original mylar overlays of interpreted
photographs Hard copy vegetation map Accuracy assessment Final report
describing all procedures used in developing the final map and
accuracy assessment Planning and Review Meeting An initial meeting was
held with all interested parties to discuss several aspects of the
mapping effort. Foremost among these was the mapping extent.
Vegetation issues particular to the park were addressed. Devils Tower
National Monument was responsible for obtaining permission from
adjacent land owners for property access for sampling purposes. Most
of the private lands were under some form of grazing or farming.
Consequently, sampling on these lands was not necessary. The remainder
of the lands within the mapping area are U.S. Forest Service Lands so
permission was not necessary. Preliminary Data Collection and Review
of Existing Information To reduce duplicating previous work and to
help in our effort we collected existing vegetation reports and maps
from the staff at Devils Tower National Monument. These materials were
referenced during the mapping process and the information contained in
them was incorporated where it was deemed useful. Because soils also
affect the distribution of vegetation, soil maps and soil descriptions
were also obtained as reference. These were not converted to a digital
file. Digital elevation models (DEM) were obtained to create slope and
aspect maps that helped in determining vegetation community
distribution. Vegetation Sampling The sampling approach used in this
mapping effort was typical of small park sampling, where all polygons
within the park boundary are sampled. Two levels of field data
gathering were conducted in this park; plots and observations. Plots
represented the most intensive sampling of the landscape and used
TNC's 'Plot Form'. Observations consisted of brief descriptions and
were designed to obtain a quick overview of the landscape without
spending a large amount of time at each sample site. Observation
points used the 'Observation Form' data sheet. Examples of both 'Plot'
and 'Observation' forms are included in the companion report by TNC.
Initially, plots were used to describe the vegetation of the park. A
total of 28 plots were obtained from August 20 through August 24,
1996. These plots were used by TNC to describe the vegetation
associations found within the park. These descriptions are in the
companion report by TNC. Map Validation A field trip was conducted
in June of 1997 to assess the initial mapping effort and to refine map
class.
</methdesc>
</method>
<srcinfo>
<srccite>
<citeinfo>
<origin>Kenny Aerial Mapping Company, Phoenix, AZ</origin>
<pubdate>19930729</pubdate>
<title>
Aerial photography (CIR and true color) of Devils Tower National
Monument
</title>
<geoform>photography</geoform>
<pubinfo>
<pubplace>Denver, CO</pubplace>
<publish>USGS Center for Biological Informatics</publish>
</pubinfo>
<othercit>
Aerial photography was taken at a scale of 1:24,000. Original media
are in the form of positive transparencies. Photointerpretation was
done on contact prints of the true color photos.
</othercit>
<onlink>http://biology.usgs.gov/npsveg/deto/photos.html</onlink>
</citeinfo>
</srccite>
<srcscale>12000</srcscale>
<typesrc>Contact paper prints of film transparencies</typesrc>
<srctime>
<timeinfo>
<sngdate>
<caldate>19930729</caldate>
</sngdate>
</timeinfo>
<srccurr>Imagery date</srccurr>
</srctime>
<srccitea>deto Aerial Photos</srccitea>
<srccontr>These aerial photographs were the basis for the photointerpretation process</srccontr>
</srcinfo>
<srcinfo>
<srccite>
<citeinfo>
<origin>Unknown</origin>
<pubdate>Unknown</pubdate>
<title>Digital Orthophotograph of Devils Tower National Monument</title>
<geoform>Remote-Sensing Image</geoform>
<pubinfo>
<pubplace>Unknown</pubplace>
<publish>Unknown</publish>
</pubinfo>
<othercit>The digital orthophotograph is a 1:2400 scale image.</othercit>
</citeinfo>
</srccite>
<typesrc>Cartridge Tape</typesrc>
<srctime>
<timeinfo>
<sngdate>
<caldate>Unknown</caldate>
</sngdate>
</timeinfo>
<srccurr>Imagery date</srccurr>
</srctime>
<srccitea>deto orthophoto</srccitea>
<srccontr>This digital orthophoto provided the project basemap</srccontr>
</srcinfo>
<srcinfo>
<srccite>
<citeinfo>
<origin>USGS,BRD,Center for Biological Informatics</origin>
<pubdate>19960405</pubdate>
<title>Devils Tower National Monument Sampling and Classification</title>
<geoform>report</geoform>
<pubinfo>
<pubplace>Denver, CO</pubplace>
<publish>USGS, BRD, Center for Biological Informatics</publish>
</pubinfo>
<othercit>
This report was generated by the Nature Conservancy under contract to
the USGS, BRD, CBI.
</othercit>
<onlink>http://biology.usgs.gov/npsveg/deto/methods.pdf</onlink>
</citeinfo>
</srccite>
<typesrc>Online</typesrc>
<srctime>
<timeinfo>
<sngdate>
<caldate>199510</caldate>
</sngdate>
</timeinfo>
<srccurr>Ground Condition</srccurr>
</srctime>
<srccitea>deto sample and classification</srccitea>
<srccontr>Report summarizing plot data collection effort</srccontr>
</srcinfo>
<srcinfo>
<srccite>
<citeinfo>
<origin>USGS/BRD, Center for Biological Informatics</origin>
<pubdate>199411</pubdate>
<title>Accuracy Assessment Procedures, NBS/NPS Vegetation Mapping Program</title>
<geoform>report</geoform>
<serinfo>
<sername>USGS-NPS Vegetation Mapping Program</sername>
<issue>Devils Tower National Monument</issue>
</serinfo>
<pubinfo>
<pubplace>Denver, CO</pubplace>
<publish>USGS/BRD, Center for Biological Informatics</publish>
</pubinfo>
<othercit>
This report was prepared by Environmental Systems Research Institute;
Redlands, CA,  National Center for Geographic Information and Analysis,
University of California, Santa Barbara, CA and The Nature Conservancy,
Arlington, VA under contract from the U.S. Department of Interior National
Biological Survey and National Park Service.
</othercit>
<onlink>http://biology.usgs.gov/npsveg/aa/aa.html</onlink>
</citeinfo>
</srccite>
<typesrc>electronic document</typesrc>
<srctime>
<timeinfo>
<sngdate>
<caldate>199411</caldate>
</sngdate>
</timeinfo>
<srccurr>publication date</srccurr>
</srctime>
<srccitea>Accuracy Assessment Procedures Documents</srccitea>
<srccontr>This document established the procedures and protocols for the accuracy assessment at Devils Tower National Monument.</srccontr>
</srcinfo>
<srcinfo>
<srccite>
<citeinfo>
<origin>U.S. Geological Survey</origin>
<origin>Department of the Interior</origin>
<pubdate>19980510</pubdate>
<title>
Devils Tower National Monument Photo Interpretation
and Map Generation Procedures
</title>
<geoform>report</geoform>
<serinfo>
<sername>USGS-NPS Vegetation Mapping Program</sername>
<issue>Devils Tower National Monument</issue>
</serinfo>
<pubinfo>
<pubplace>Denver, CO</pubplace>
<publish>
USGS, Biological Resources Division, Center for Biological
Informatics
</publish>
</pubinfo>
<othercit>
Created in large part by Aerial Information Systems, Inc.
under contract from USGS/BRD/CBI.
</othercit>
<onlink>http://biology.usgs.gov/npsveg/deto/pi_rpt.pdf</onlink>
</citeinfo>
</srccite>
<typesrc>digital</typesrc>
<srctime>
<timeinfo>
<sngdate>
<caldate>19980510</caldate>
</sngdate>
</timeinfo>
<srccurr>Report date</srccurr>
</srctime>
<srccitea>deto mapping report</srccitea>
<srccontr>
Photo interpretation was done by trained interpreters familiar with
the vegetation communities of the Monument on overlays registered to
the aerial photographs under a stereoscope.  Vegetation communities
were identified on the basis of their color, pattern, texture, and
location on the landscape and lines were drawn around the communities.
The photo interpreters had visited the monument and conferred with the
ecologists who performed the vegetation classification and were familiar
with the vegetation communities. Not all vegetation associations could be
identified on the photography due to size constraints and complexity of
the vegetation.  Map classes were assigned in these cases and a cross-
walk was made to the vegetation classification.
</srccontr>
</srcinfo>
<procstep>
<procdesc>
Air Photo Interpretation All map classes were interpreted from
existing 1:16,000 scale, color photography taken on July 29, 1993. The
photographs were acquired from the U.S. Forest Service (USFS).
Photointerpretation used the standard identification features such as
tone, texture, color, pattern, topographic position, and shadow. In
addition, field sample locations and their vegetation descriptions
aided in assigning map class to each polygon. All photographs were
examined using a stereoscope. Digital elevation models (DEM's) were
processed and converted to slope and aspect coverages. These helped to
provide additional perspectives of the landscape. Seven photographs
were interpreted for the entire mapping area. Digital scans of these
photographs are included as .tif files on the CD included with this
report.
</procdesc>
<procdate>199510</procdate>
<proccont>
<cntinfo>
<cntorgp>
<cntorg>Bureau of Reclamations</cntorg>
</cntorgp>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>Physical Address</addrtype>
<city>Redlands</city>
<state>CA</state>
<postal>Unknown</postal>
<country>USA</country>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>Unknown</cntvoice>
</cntinfo>
</proccont>
</procstep>
<procstep>
<procdesc>
In conjunction with the photo verification and field sampling effort,
NBS (now USGS, BRD, CBI) personnel performed a locational accuracy
test comparing the accuracy of a global positioning system (GPS)
versus manual location techniques. The TNC biologist "pin-pricked" all
of the sample site locations onto the aerial photos while the NBS
staff captured the location using GPS. The "pin-pricked" locations
were subsequently input into the GIS database for comparison against
the GPS locations for the same site.
</procdesc>
<procdate>199510</procdate>
<srcused>DETO CIR Aerial Photography</srcused>
<srcprod>
Analysis of Accuracy Assessment Procedures at Devils Tower National
Monument
</srcprod>
<proccont>
<cntinfo>
<cntorgp>
<cntorg>
USGS Biological Resources Division, Center for Biological
Informatics
</cntorg>
<cntper>Karl Brown</cntper>
</cntorgp>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>Mailing Address</addrtype>
<address>USGS</address>
<address>Biological Resources Division, Center for Biological Informatics</address>
<address>PO Box 25046 DFC, MS302</address>
<city>Denver</city>
<state>Colorado</state>
<postal>80225</postal>
<country>USA</country>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>(303)202-4240 (Karl Brown)</cntvoice>
<cntfax>(303)202-4219</cntfax>
<cntemail>karl_brown@usgs.gov</cntemail>
</cntinfo>
</proccont>
</procstep>
</lineage>
</dataqual>
<spdoinfo>
<indspref>
Devils Tower National Monument is in Crook County in northeast Wyoming and
is part of the western most Black Hills. The monument lies 10 miles east of
the Bear Lodge Mountains and 10 miles south west of the town of Hulett,
Wyoming
</indspref>
<direct>Vector</direct>
</spdoinfo>
<spref>
<horizsys>
<planar>
<gridsys>
<gridsysn>Universal Transverse Mercator</gridsysn>
<utm>
<utmzone>13</utmzone>
<transmer>
<longcm>-105</longcm>
<latprjo>0</latprjo>
<feast>500000</feast>
<fnorth>0</fnorth>
<sfctrmer>.9996</sfctrmer>
</transmer>
</utm>
</gridsys>
<planci>
<plance>Coordinate Pair</plance>
<coordrep>
<absres>1</absres>
<ordres>1</ordres>
</coordrep>
<plandu>Meters</plandu>
</planci>
</planar>
<geodetic>
<ellips>Geodedic Reference System 80</ellips>
<semiaxis>6378137</semiaxis>
<denflat>298.257</denflat>
</geodetic>
</horizsys>
</spref>
<eainfo>
<overview>
<eaover>
The database contains two separate classification systems. The two systems
represent vegetation map units and land cover map units. The vegetation
map units are usually combinations of vegetation associations described in
the TNC companion report. The vegetation map units have also been
categorized into 5 general vegetation classes. The land use map units use
the Anderson Level II classification system. The vegetation attributes
contain character codes and descriptors. The land use contain numeric
codes. The descriptors are available in two look-up tables provided with
this data set. These are map.lut and anderson.lut. Modifiers also exist
representing percent of vegetation cover and tree height. These modifiers
are available in the look-up table structure.lut. Contact David Salas at
the Bureau of Reclamation Remote Sensing and Geographic Information Group
D-8260 for more information about the classification system.
National Park Service/Biological Resources Division Vegetation
Inventory and Mapping Program for Devils Tower National Monument,
Wyoming, Final Community Association Classification, May 1, 1998.
Alliance/Community  BB=Wyoming Big Sagebrush / Bluebrush Wheatgrass
Shrub Herbaceous Vegetation  BU=Green Ash - American Elm / Wolfberry
Forest  CP=Eastern Cottonwood Peach Leaf Willow / Narrow Leaf Willow
Woodland  GH=Grassland Complex  MK=Mosaic - Kentucky Bluegrass / Little
Bluestem Grassland  MW=Mosaic - Western Wheatgrass / Little Bluestem
Grassland  PB=Ponderosa Pine / Bur Oak Woodland  PJ=Ponderosa Pine /
Common Juniper Woodland  PP1=Ponderosa Pine Complex 1  PP2=Ponderosa
Pine Complex II  SC=Silver Sage Brush / Western - Wheat Grass Herbaceous
Vegetation.
HEIGHT
2 = 0.5 - 1 meters
3 = 1 - 5 meters
4 = 5 - 15 meters
5 = 15 - 30 meters
6 = &gt; 30 meters
DENSITY
1 = Closed/Continuous   &lt; 60%
2 = Discontinuous   40% - 60%
3 = Dispersed    25% - 40%
4 = Sparse     10% - 25%
PATTERN
1,'Evenly Dispersed'
2,'Clumped/Bunched'
3,'Gradational/Transitional'
4,'Alternating'
ANDERSON CODE
11 = Residential
12 = Commercial and Services
14 = Transportation, Communications and Utilities
17 = Other Urban or Built-up Land
21 = Cropland and Pasture
51 = Streams and Canals
53 = Reservoirs
62 = Nonforested Wetland
74 = Bare Exposed Rock
VEGETATION CODE
arte   = Silver Sagebrush / Western-Wheat Grass Shrub Herbaceous Vegetation
bbwg   = Skunkbush Sumac / Bluebunch Wheatgrass Shrub Herbaceous Vegetation
cpwf   = Eastern Cottonwood - Peach Leaf Willow / Narrow-Leaf Willow Woodland
gplb   = Little Bluestem - Grama (Side-Oats, Blue) - Threadleaf Sedge Herbaceous Vegetation
kbg    = Kentucky Bluegrass Disturbed Community
m-kplb = Mosaic - Kentucky Bluegrass / Little Bluestem
m-wwlb = Mosaic - Western Wheatgrasss / Little Bluestem
pdt    = Prairie Dog Town
ppbo   = Ponderosa Pine / Bur Oak Woodland
ppbw   = Ponderosa Pine / Bluebunch Wheatgrasss Woodland
ppcj   = Ponderosa Pine / Common Juniper Woodland
pplb   = Ponderosa Pine / Little Bluestem Woodland
ppsf   = Ponderosa Pine / Oregon Grape Forest
ppss   = Ponderosa Pine / Sun Sedge Woodland
wwbg   = Western-Wheatgrass - Blue Grama - Threadleaf Herbaceous Vegetation
</eaover>
<eadetcit>
Grossman, D. Et al. 1994. National Park Service/ National Biological
Service Vegetation Mapping Project, Standardized National Vegetation
Classification System 209 pp.
</eadetcit>
</overview>
</eainfo>
<distinfo>
<distrib>
<cntinfo>
<cntorgp>
<cntorg>USGS Biological Resources Division, Center for Biological Informatics</cntorg>
<cntper>USGS-NPS Vegetation Mapping Program Coordinator</cntper>
</cntorgp>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>Physical Address</addrtype>
<address>USGS</address>
<address>Biological Resources Division, CBI</address>
<address>Building 810, Room 8000</address>
<city>Denver</city>
<state>Colorado</state>
<postal>80225-0046</postal>
<country>USA</country>
</cntaddr>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>Mailing Address</addrtype>
<address>USGS</address>
<address>Biological Resources Division, CBI</address>
<address>PO BOX 25046, DFC, MS302</address>
<city>Denver</city>
<state>Colorado</state>
<postal>80225-0046</postal>
<country>USA</country>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>(303) 202-4220</cntvoice>
<cntfax>303-202-4229</cntfax>
<cntfax>303-202-4219 (org)</cntfax>
<cntemail>gs-b-npsveg@usgs.gov</cntemail>
</cntinfo>
</distrib>
<resdesc>DETO Veg map</resdesc>
<distliab>
Although these data have been processed successfully on a computer system at
the Biological Resources Division, no warranty expressed or implied is made
regarding the accuracy or utility of the data on any other system or for
general or scientific purposes, nor shall the act of distribution constitute
any such warranty. This disclaimer applies both to individual use of the
data and aggregate use with other data. It is strongly recommended that
these data are directly acquired from a Biological Resources Division
server, and not indirectly through other sources which may have changed the
data in some way. It is also strongly recommended that careful attention be
paid to the contents of the metadata file associated with these data. The
Biological Resources Division shall not be held liable for improper or
incorrect use of the data described and/or contained herein.
</distliab>
<stdorder>
<digform>
<digtinfo>
<formname>EXE (vegetation file of map composition)</formname>
</digtinfo>
<digtopt>
<onlinopt>
<computer>
<networka>
<networkr>http://biology.usgs.gov/npsveg/ftp/vegmapping/deto/deto.exe</networkr>
</networka>
</computer>
</onlinopt>
</digtopt>
</digform>
<fees>none</fees>
</stdorder>
<stdorder>
<digform>
<digtinfo>
<formname>SDTS</formname>
</digtinfo>
<digtopt>
<onlinopt>
<computer>
<networka>
<networkr>http://biology.usgs.gov/npsveg/ftp/vegmapping/deto/detosdts.exe</networkr>
</networka>
</computer>
</onlinopt>
</digtopt>
</digform>
<fees>none</fees>
</stdorder>
<stdorder>
<digform>
<digtinfo>
<formname>EXE (park boundary file of map composition)</formname>
</digtinfo>
<digtopt>
<onlinopt>
<computer>
<networka>
<networkr>http://biology.usgs.gov/npsveg/ftp/vegmapping/deto/detobdy.exe</networkr>
</networka>
</computer>
</onlinopt>
</digtopt>
</digform>
<fees>none</fees>
</stdorder>
<stdorder>
<digform>
<digtinfo>
<formname>SDTS</formname>
</digtinfo>
<digtopt>
<onlinopt>
<computer>
<networka>
<networkr>http://biology.usgs.gov/npsveg/ftp/vegmapping/deto/detobdysdts.exe</networkr>
</networka>
</computer>
</onlinopt>
</digtopt>
</digform>
<fees>none</fees>
</stdorder>
<stdorder>
<digform>
<digtinfo>
<formname>GIF</formname>
</digtinfo>
<digtopt>
<onlinopt>
<computer>
<networka>
<networkr>http://biology.usgs.gov/npsveg/deto/images/detoveg.gif</networkr>
</networka>
</computer>
</onlinopt>
</digtopt>
</digform>
<fees>none</fees>
</stdorder>
</distinfo>
<metainfo>
<metd>20011022</metd>
<metrd>20050518</metrd>
<metc>
<cntinfo>
<cntorgp>
<cntorg>USGS-NPS Vegetation Mapping Program Coordinator</cntorg>
</cntorgp>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
<address>
U.S. Geological Survey, Center for Biological Informatics, MS 302,
Room 8000, Building 810, Denver Federal Center
</address>
<city>Denver</city>
<state>Colorado</state>
<postal>80225</postal>
<country>USA</country>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>(303) 202-4220</cntvoice>
<cntfax>(303) 202-4219</cntfax>
<cntemail>gs-b-npsveg@usgs.gov</cntemail>
</cntinfo>
</metc>
<metstdn>FGDC-STD-001.1-1999 Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata, 1998 Part 1: Biological Data Profile, 1999</metstdn>
<metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
<metextns>
<onlink>http://biology.usgs.gov/fgdc.bio/bionwext.txt</onlink>
<metprof>Biological Data Profile FGDC-STD-001.1-1999</metprof>
</metextns>
</metainfo>
<mercury><begdate>19950912</begdate><enddate>19950912</enddate><htmlurl>http://mercury.ornl.gov/metadata/nbii/html/nbii/www.nbii.gov_metadata_mdata_CBI_usgs_brd_cbi_d_detoveg.html</htmlurl><LTER-Site>nbii</LTER-Site></mercury></metadata>
