<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<metadata><Source>http://www.nbii.gov/metadata/mdata/brd-bib/usgs_brd_fresc_b_Idfalcon.sgml</Source>
<idinfo>
<citation>
<citeinfo>
<origin>Lehman, R.N., K. Steenhof, L.B. Carpenter, and M.N. Kochert</origin>
<pubdate>2000</pubdate>
<title>Turnover and dispersal of prairie falcons in southwestern Idaho</title>
<geoform>Journal article</geoform>
<serinfo>
<sername>J. Raptor Res.</sername>
<issue>34(4):262-269</issue>
</serinfo>
<othercit>
Science Information System Project #: 73-3
Publication Control #: 829
</othercit>
</citeinfo>
</citation>
<descript>
<abstract>The Snake River Birds of Prey National Conservation Area (NCA) is unique because it supports an unusual concentration of nesting raptors, possibly the densest nesting assemblage of non-colonial raptors in the world. It also contains an exceptionally high raptor biodiversity. Congress recognized this extraordinary resource and established this 240,064 ha area (196,225 ha are public land) along a 130-km stretch of the Snake River as a National Conservation Area in 1993. This project, comprised of numerous component studies, is being conducted because of widespread concern about use of a portion of the NCA by the Idaho Army National Guard and extensive loss of raptor habitat due to wildfires. The project will test the hypothesis that military training activities have no effect on raptors, their prey, and their habitats in a shrubsteppe and salt desert shrub environment. It will also assess the effects of wildfire on raptors and the ability of the post-burn vegetation community to support prey populations. The study will also collect baseline data that will allow evaluation of techniques for restoring and protecting native plant communities as well as assessment of the relationship between livestock grazing and prey abundance. The project focuses on the spatial and temporal variation in habitat use by foraging raptors and on habitat characteristics associated with the principal prey species to investigate the relationships among three trophic levels (soils/vegetation, prey, and raptors).</abstract>
<purpose>Reporting research results</purpose>
<supplinf>
Extent of item: 262-269pp
Illustrative Matter:  tables
</supplinf>
</descript>
<timeperd>
<timeinfo>
<sngdate>
<caldate>2000</caldate>
</sngdate>
</timeinfo>
<current>publication date</current>
</timeperd>
<status>
<progress>Complete</progress>
<update>None planned</update>
</status>
<spdom>
<descgeog>Snake River Birds of Prey National Conservation Area</descgeog>
<bounding>
<westbc>-116.25</westbc>
<eastbc>-116.1</eastbc>
<northbc>43.1</northbc>
<southbc>43</southbc>
</bounding>
</spdom>
<keywords>
<theme>
<themekt>none</themekt>
<themekey>dispersal</themekey>
<themekey>turnover</themekey>
</theme>
<theme>
<themekt>Science Information System Controlled Vocabulary</themekt>
<themekey>Birds</themekey>
<themekey>National Wildlife Refuges</themekey>
<themekey>Populations</themekey>
<themekey>Monitoring</themekey>
<themekey>Wildlife</themekey>
</theme>
<place>
<placekt>none</placekt>
<placekey>southwestern Idaho</placekey>
<placekey>Snake River Birds of Prey National Conservation Area</placekey>
<placekey>ID</placekey>
</place>
</keywords>
<taxonomy>
<keywtax>
<taxonkt>none</taxonkt>
<taxonkey>Prairie falcons (Falco mexicanus)</taxonkey>
<taxonkey>birds</taxonkey>
</keywtax>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Kingdom</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Animalia</taxonrv>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Phylum</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Chordata</taxonrv>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Sub Phylum</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Vertebrata</taxonrv>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Class</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Aves</taxonrv>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Order</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Ciconiiformes</taxonrv>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Family</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Falconidae</taxonrv>
<common>prairie falcon</common>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Genus</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Falco</taxonrv>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Species</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Falco mexicanus</taxonrv>
</taxoncl>
</taxoncl>
</taxoncl>
</taxoncl>
</taxoncl>
</taxoncl>
</taxoncl>
</taxoncl>
</taxonomy>
<accconst>None</accconst>
<useconst>None</useconst>
<ptcontac>
<cntinfo>
<cntperp>
<cntper>Lehman, Robert</cntper>
<cntorg>USGS Forest and Rangeland Ecosystem Science Center; Snake River Field Station</cntorg>
</cntperp>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
<address>Snake River Field Station, 970 Lusk St.</address>
<city>Boise</city>
<state>ID</state>
<postal>83706</postal>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>208/426/5205</cntvoice>
<cntemail>blehman@eagle.boisestate.edu</cntemail>
</cntinfo>
</ptcontac>
</idinfo>
<distinfo>
<distrib>
<cntinfo>
<cntorgp>
<cntorg>Olendorff Library</cntorg>
</cntorgp>
<cntpos>Librarian</cntpos>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
<address>
USGS FRESC Snake River Field Station
970 Lusk Street
</address>
<city>Boise</city>
<state>ID</state>
<postal>83706</postal>
<country>USA</country>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>208 426-5218</cntvoice>
<cntfax>208 426-5210</cntfax>
</cntinfo>
</distrib>
<resdesc>Publication Control #: 829</resdesc>
<distliab>
The USGS Forest and Rangeland Ecosystem Science Center and its research partners make every effort to provide and maintain accurate, complete, usable, and timely information. However, some USGS data and information may, of necessity, be preliminary in nature. These data and information are provided with the understanding that they are not guaranteed to be correct or complete. Users are cautioned to consider carefully the provisional nature of these data and information before using them for decisions that concern personal or public safety or the conduct of business that involves substantial monetary or operational consequences. It is also strongly recommended that careful attention be paid to the contents of the metadata file associated with these data and information. Conclusions drawn from, or actions undertaken on the basis of, such data and information are the sole responsibility of the user.
USGS-authored or produced data and information are in the public domain. Whereas the content of many USGS publications and other information resources are in the public domain, some USGS products contain material that is copyrighted by others and used by the USGS with permission. Users of this information may need to obtain permission from the copyright owner for other uses. Furthermore, some non-USGS data, products, and information referred to may be protected under U.S. and foreign copyright laws. Users may need to obtain permission from the copyright owner to acquire, use, reproduce, or distribute these materials. It is the sole responsibility of the user of the information to secure all necessary permission.
</distliab>
<stdorder>
<nondig>Publications are available as reprints, reports, pamphlets, or brochures.</nondig>
<fees>None</fees>
<ordering>Request specific publications by reference number.</ordering>
</stdorder>
</distinfo>
<metainfo>
<metd>20010530</metd>
<metc>
<cntinfo>
<cntorgp>
<cntorg>USGS Forest and Rangeland Ecosystem Science Center (FRESC)</cntorg>
</cntorgp>
<cntpos>Library</cntpos>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
<address>
777 NW 9th St.
Suite 100
</address>
<city>Corvallis</city>
<state>OR</state>
<postal>97330</postal>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>541-750-1030</cntvoice>
<cntfax>541-750-1069</cntfax>
<cntemail>fresc_outreach@usgs.gov</cntemail>
</cntinfo>
</metc>
<metstdn>FGDC Biological Data Profile of the Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
<metstdv>FGDC-STD-001.1-1999</metstdv>
</metainfo>
<mercury><begdate>20000101</begdate><enddate>20001231</enddate><htmlurl>http://mercury.ornl.gov/metadata/nbii/html/brd/www.nbii.gov_metadata_mdata_brd-bib_usgs_brd_fresc_b_Idfalcon.html</htmlurl><LTER-Site>brd</LTER-Site></mercury></metadata>
