<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<metadata><Source>http://www.nbii.gov/metadata/mdata/CBI/usgs_brd_cbi_d_wicaveg.sgml</Source>
<idinfo>
<citation>
<citeinfo>
<origin>
Remote Sensing and GIS Group, Technical Service Center, US Bureau of
Reclamation, Mail Code D-8260, POB 25007, Denver CO 80225
</origin>
<pubdate>1999</pubdate>
<title>
Wind Cave National Park Spatial Vegetation Data; Cover Type /
Association level of the National Vegetation Classification System
</title>
<geoform>maps data</geoform>
<serinfo>
<sername>USGS-NPS Vegetation Mapping Program</sername>
<issue>None</issue>
</serinfo>
<pubinfo>
<pubplace>Denver, CO</pubplace>
<publish>USGS-BRD</publish>
</pubinfo>
<othercit>Created under contract to the USGS-BRD-CBI</othercit>
<onlink>http://www.rsgis.do.usbr.gov</onlink>
<onlink>http://biology.usgs.gov/npsveg/wica/images/wicaveg.gif</onlink>
<onlink>http://biology.usgs.gov/npsveg/ftp/vegmapping/wica/wica.exe</onlink>
<onlink>http://biology.usgs.gov/npsveg/ftp/vegmapping/wica/wicasdts.exe</onlink>
<onlink>http://biology.usgs.gov/npsveg/ftp/vegmapping/wica/wicabdy.exe</onlink>
<onlink>http://biology.usgs.gov/npsveg/ftp/vegmapping/wica/wicabdysdts.exe</onlink>
</citeinfo>
</citation>
<descript>
<abstract>
This geospatial database covers vegetation land cover and land use for
Wind Cave National Park and surrounding areas and is authorized as part of
the USGS/NPS Vegetation Mapping Program (http://biology.usgs.gov/npsveg).
The program is administered by the Biological Resources Division
(BRD) of the United States Geological Survey (USGS). This mapping effort
was performed by the US Bureau of Reclamation's (USBR) Remote Sensing and
GIS Group, Technical Service Center, Denver, CO. The vegetation mapping
program is part of a larger Inventory and Monitoring (I&amp;M) program started
by the National Park Service (NPS) (http://www.aqd.nps.gov/nrid/im/). I&amp;M
goals are, among others, to map the vegetation of all national parks and
monuments and provide a baseline inventory of vegetation. The USGS/BRD is
responsible for overall management and oversight of all ongoing mapping
efforts. The mapped vegetation reflects conditions that existed during the
specific year and season that the aerial photographs were taken. There is
a margin of error inherent in the use of aerial photographs. Therefore, a
detailed ground and historical analysis of a single site may result in a
revision of the vegetation alliance boundaries established through
photographic interpretation.
</abstract>
<purpose>
The purposes of the mapping effort are varied and include the following:
Provides support for NPS Resources Management; Promotes vegetation-related
research for both NPS and USGS/BRD; Provides support for NPS Planning and
Compliance; Adds to the information base for NPS Interpretation; and
Assists in NPS Operations.
</purpose>
<supplinf>
The following vegetation and land use classes were mapped for this
project: LAND USE: 51 Transportation Communications, and Utilities; 52
Mixed Urban or Built-up Land; 53 Croplands and Pasture; 55 Other
Agricultural Land; 57 Open Water; 59 Strip Mines, Quarries, and Gravel
Pits. VEGETATION: 1 Purple three-awn - Fetid marigold Herbaceous
Vegetation; 2 Ponderosa pine Limestone Rock Outcrop; 3 Red Beds Spares
Vegetation; 4 Black Hills Rock Outcrop Sparse Vegetation; 6 Bison Wallows;
11 Little Bluestem -Sideouts grama Herbaceous Alliance (with burned
ponderosa pine; 12 Chokechery Shrubland with burned ponderosa pine; 13
Western Wheatgrass - Kentucky Complex with burned ponderosa pine; 14
Emergent Wetland Herbaceous Vegetation 15 Little Bluestem - Grama Grass
Herbaceous Vegetation; 16 Western Wheatgrass - Kentucky Bluegrass Complex;
17 Introduced Weedy Graminoid Herbaceous Vegetation ; 18 Needle-and-thread
- Blue Grama-Threadlead Sedge Herbaceous Vegetation; 30 Mt Mahogany /
Sideoats Grama Shrubland I; 31 Mt Mahogany / Sideoats Grama Shrubland II ;
32 Lead Plant Shrubland; 33 Chokecherry Shrubland; 34 Bebb Willow
Shrubland; 35 Western Snowberry Shrubland; 40 Plains Cottonwood / Western
snowberry Woodland; 41 Boxelder / Chokecherry Forest; 42 Bur Oak Stand; 43
Green Ash - American Elm / Chokecherry Forest; 44 Birch - Aspen Stand; 45
Ponderosa Pine Woodland Complex I; 46 Ponderosa Pine / Little Bluestem
Woodland; 47 Ponderosa Pine / Chokecherry Forest; 48 Ponderosa Pine
Woodland Complex II; 49 Young Ponderosa Pine Dense Cover Complex.
(previous geoform was 'Map')</supplinf>
</descript>
<timeperd>
<timeinfo>
<sngdate>
<caldate>199706</caldate>
</sngdate>
</timeinfo>
<current>Source Photography Date</current>
</timeperd>
<status>
<progress>Complete</progress>
<update>None Planned</update>
</status>
<spdom>
<bounding>
<westbc>-103.6194</westbc>
<eastbc>-103.3222</eastbc>
<northbc>43.65139</northbc>
<southbc>43.50639</southbc>
</bounding>
<descgeog>
Wind Cave National Park, SD including approx 5 mile buffer around park
which includes private lands and portions of Custer State Park and Black
Hills National Forest.
</descgeog>
</spdom>
<keywords>
<theme>
<themekt>None</themekt>
<themekey>association</themekey>
<themekey>alliance</themekey>
<themekey>land cover</themekey>
<themekey>land use</themekey>
<themekey>vegetation</themekey>
<themekey>National Park Service</themekey>
</theme>
<place>
<placekt>None</placekt>
<placekey>Wind Cave</placekey>
<placekey>Pringle</placekey>
<placekey>South Dakota</placekey>
<placekey>National Park</placekey>
<placekey>Wind Cave National Park</placekey>
</place>
</keywords>
<taxonomy>
<keywtax>
<taxonkt>None</taxonkt>
<taxonkey>Plants</taxonkey>
<taxonkey>vegetation</taxonkey>
<taxonkey>National Vegetation Classification System</taxonkey>
</keywtax>
<taxonsys>
<classsys>
<classcit>
<citeinfo>
<origin>U.S. Government; Federal Geographic Data Committee</origin>
<pubdate>19971022</pubdate>
<title>National Vegetation Classification Standard (NVCS)</title>
<geoform>document</geoform>
<pubinfo>
<pubplace>Washington D.C.</pubplace>
<publish>Federal Geographic Data Committee</publish>
</pubinfo>
<onlink>http://www.fgdc.gov/standards/status/sub2_1.html</onlink>
</citeinfo>
</classcit>
</classsys>
<taxonpro>
Sequence of field test data and observation plots, and CIR photo signature
field observations.
</taxonpro>
</taxonsys>
<taxongen>
Refer to complete listing of mapped plant alliances/associations
under Supplemental Information above.
</taxongen>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Kingdom</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Plantae</taxonrv>
</taxoncl>
</taxonomy>
<accconst>None</accconst>
<useconst>
Any person using the information presented here should fully understand the
data collection and compilation procedures, as described in the metadata,
before beginning analysis. The burden for determining fitness for use lies
entirely with the user. For purposes of publication or dissemination, citations
or credit should be given to the U.S. Geological Survey, and the National Park
Service, and the U.S. Bureau of Reclamation.
</useconst>
<ptcontac>
<cntinfo>
<cntperp>
<cntper>USGS-NPS Vegetation Mapping Program Coordinator</cntper>
<cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, Center for Biological Informatics</cntorg>
</cntperp>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
<address>
U.S. Geological Survey, Center for Biological
Informatics, MS 302, Room 8000, Building 810,
Denver Federal Center
</address>
<city>Denver</city>
<state>Colorado</state>
<postal>80225</postal>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>(303) 202-4220</cntvoice>
<cntfax>303-202-4229</cntfax>
<cntfax>303-202-4219 (org)</cntfax>
<cntemail>gs-b-npsveg@usgs.gov</cntemail>
</cntinfo>
</ptcontac>
<browse>
<browsen>http://biology.usgs.gov/npsveg/wica/images/wicaveg.gif</browsen>
<browsed>
Graphic file showing vegetation distribution of
Wind Cave NP and environs, by ecological
subgroups.  Low resolution for web browser - 194 KB file size.
</browsed>
<browset>GIF</browset>
</browse>
<datacred>Jay Carlson, Dan Cogan, Doug Crawford, Trudy Myer, and Jim Von Loh of USBR</datacred>
<native>UNIX-ARC/INFO</native>
</idinfo>
<dataqual>
<attracc>
<attraccr>
These data have an overall accuracy of 73 % (69.8% Kappa index) within a
90% confidence interval of 77.6% upper limit and 68.4% lower limit.
</attraccr>
</attracc>
<logic>
All polygon features are checked for topology and existence of label points
using the ARC/INFO software. Each polygon begins and ends at the same point
with the node feature. All nodes are checked for error so that there are no
unintentional dangling features . There are no duplicate lines or polygons.
All nodes will snap together and close polygons based on a specified
tolerance. If the node is not within the tolerance it is adjusted manually.
The tests for logical consistency are performed in ARC/INFO using certain
commands.
</logic>
<complete>
All data that can be photo-interpreted is digitized in accordance with the
minimum mapping unit of .5 hectares. This includes features that fall into
the NVCS vegetation (landcover) classification and the Anderson Level II
land use classification. Minimum mapping unit is .5 hectares but
some classes below the MMU are included such as wetlands; prominent stands
of vegetation; and polygons cut off by other features and boarders. Roads
(out to visible disturbed ground right-of-way or fence line) wider than
approx 10 meters were digitized as polygons and attributed accordingly.
Roads visible on the DOQQ's but thinner than 10 meters were digitized as
lines. Wet drainages were digitized as lines and attributed with code #14.
Dry drainages thinner than 10 meters were not digitized.
</complete>
<posacc>
<horizpa>
<horizpar>
USGS DOQQ's were used as basemap to acquire geospatial horizontal
locations.
</horizpar>
</horizpa>
</posacc>
<lineage>
<method>
<methtype>Field and Remote Sensing</methtype>
<methodid>
<methkt>None</methkt>
<methkey>photo-interpretation</methkey>
<methkey>Field Methods for Vegetation Mapping</methkey>
<methkey>ground truth</methkey>
<methkey>reconnaissance</methkey>
<methkey>gradsect</methkey>
<methkey>observation</methkey>
<methkey>plot</methkey>
<methkey>photo signatures</methkey>
<methkey>ground verification</methkey>
<methkey>stereoscope</methkey>
</methodid>
<methdesc>
All vegetation and land use classes were interpreted and mapped from
1:12,000 scale, color infrared photography flown in June 1997. Color
prints were developed from the CIR negatives and have an approximate 20%
overlap east-to-west and 60% north-to-south. Data from the photos was
interpreted on Mylar overlays. Vegetation was delineated and classified
on the mylars using a combination of field and remote sensing
techniques. Field techniques followed the standards described in Field
Methods for Vegetation Mapping (The Nature Conservancy, 1994). These
included preliminary reconnaissance, environmental stratification of the
study area using a gradsect approach (Austin and Heyligers, 1989), and
observation point and detailed plot data collection. Multiple plot and
observation data were collected for each unique vegetation association
found within the study area. Biological, environmental, locational, and
biological interactions/historical/disturbance data were collected at
each sample point using the standard plot survey or observation point
form developed by The Nature Conservancy (1994). Remote sensing
techniques included ground verification of unique photo signatures,
stereoscopic magnification, and photo interpretation of the vegetation
and land-use practices using standard photo interpretation
characteristics such as tone, texture, color, pattern, topographic
position, and shadow. Soil maps were also used to aid in proper
interpretation. Photographs were examined using a stereoscope as needed
and light tables. A detailed photo-interpretation key is provided in the
USBR Technical Memorandum cited elsewhere in this document.
</methdesc>
<methcite>
<citeinfo>
<origin>Austin, M.P. and P.C. Heyligers</origin>
<pubdate>1989</pubdate>
<title>
Vegetation survey design for conservation: Gradsect sampling of
forests in northeastern New South Wales
</title>
<geoform>document</geoform>
<edition>Biological Conservation, Vol 50</edition>
<othercit>pp 13-32</othercit>
</citeinfo>
</methcite>
</method>
<method>
<methtype>Field</methtype>
<methdesc>See above</methdesc>
<methcite>
<citeinfo>
<origin>The Nature Conservancy</origin>
<pubdate>1994</pubdate>
<title>Field Methods for Vegetation Mapping</title>
<geoform>document</geoform>
<edition>NPS Vegetation Mapping Program, Final Draft</edition>
<onlink>http://biology.usgs.gov/npsveg/fieldmethods/index.html</onlink>
</citeinfo>
</methcite>
</method>
<srcinfo>
<srccite>
<citeinfo>
<origin>Horizons, Inc., POB 3134, Rapid City, SD 57709</origin>
<origin>Voice: 605-343-0280; Fax: 605-343-0305</origin>
<origin>EMail: eng@horizonsinc.com</origin>
<pubdate>199706</pubdate>
<title>Aerial CIR Photos</title>
<geoform>image</geoform>
<onlink>http://www.horizonsinc.com</onlink>
<onlink>http://biology.usgs.gov/npsveg/wica/photos.html</onlink>
</citeinfo>
</srccite>
<srcscale>12000</srcscale>
<typesrc>Color Prints</typesrc>
<srctime>
<timeinfo>
<sngdate>
<caldate>199706</caldate>
</sngdate>
</timeinfo>
<srccurr>Ground Condition</srccurr>
</srctime>
<srccitea>None</srccitea>
<srccontr>
These aerial photographs were the basis for the photointerpretation
process.
</srccontr>
</srcinfo>
<srcinfo>
<srccite>
<citeinfo>
<origin>USGS</origin>
<pubdate>1997</pubdate>
<title>Digital Orthophoto Quarter Quadrangles (DOQQ)</title>
<geoform>Remote-Sensing Image</geoform>
<serinfo>
<sername>Boland Ridge, Butcher Hill, Cicero Peak, Mt Cooldige, Pringle, &amp; Wind Cave</sername>
<issue>USGS 7.5m quads in South Dakota</issue>
</serinfo>
<othercit>Refer to USGS web site for metadata information</othercit>
<onlink>http://edcwww.cr.usgs.gov/webglis</onlink>
</citeinfo>
</srccite>
<srcscale>12000</srcscale>
<typesrc>Digital</typesrc>
<srctime>
<timeinfo>
<sngdate>
<caldate>1995</caldate>
</sngdate>
</timeinfo>
<srccurr>Ground Condition</srccurr>
</srctime>
<srccitea>None</srccitea>
<srccontr>The DOQQ's were used as basemap for transfer work.</srccontr>
</srcinfo>
<srcinfo>
<srccite>
<citeinfo>
<origin>USGS/BRD, Center for Biological Informatics</origin>
<pubdate>19990430</pubdate>
<title>Vegetation Procedure Report</title>
<geoform>report</geoform>
<serinfo>
<sername>Boland Ridge, Butcher Hill, Cicero Peak, Mt Cooldige, Pringle, &amp; Wind Cave</sername>
<issue>USGS 7.5m quads in South Dakota</issue>
</serinfo>
<othercit>Refer to USGS web site for metadata information</othercit>
<onlink>http://edcwww.cr.usgs.gov/webglis</onlink>
<onlink>http://biology.usgs.gov/npsveg/wica/report.html</onlink>
</citeinfo>
</srccite>
<srcscale>12000</srcscale>
<typesrc>Digital</typesrc>
<srctime>
<timeinfo>
<sngdate>
<caldate>1995</caldate>
</sngdate>
</timeinfo>
<srccurr>Ground Condition</srccurr>
</srctime>
<srccitea>None</srccitea>
<srccontr>The DOQQ's were used as basemap for transfer work.</srccontr>
</srcinfo>
<procstep>
<procdesc>
Vegetation information on the mylars (discussed above under methods)
were transferred into the GIS database using two methods, either heads-up
digitizing or scanning. METHOD I: Heads-up digitizing will be used in
areas where there are strong visible transitions between vegetation
types (i.e., have boundaries that are easy to see on the digital ortho
image). Briefly, heads-up digitizing is a procedure whereby the operator
digitizes by hand and eye on a computer terminal screen showing a
digital image of an ortho-rectified photo. By looking at similar
features on both the aerial photograph (from which the classification
was made on mylar) and on the orthophoto, the line drawn on the aerial
photo overlay is transferred to the digital image, which is registered
to coordinates on the earth. This technique should produce good results
except where there is little feature contrast on the ortho, in which
case the operator will usually scan the photo to transfer those
features. METHOD II: Photos that are too difficult to accurately
transfer via heads-up will be scanned, ie, the mylars will be scanned,
not the actual CIR photo. Before the mylar is scanned, it will be marked
with control points that correspond to visible points on the DOQQ. Six
control points should be located for best results though a minimum of 4
are required for a projective transform. The GIS software was used to
convert the scanned mylar into a geo-referenced coverage which was then
attributed and combined with the larger vegetation coverage associated
with the quarter quad area. The entire transfer and editing sequence was
automated via an in-house ARC/INFO AML. The final vegetation coverages
consist of (1) Quarter-quad boarder, (2) Park and GIS project area
boundary arcs, if applicable, and (3) vegetation polygons and linear
features. Another step involved heads-up digitizing of roads visible on
the CIR/DOQQ in accordance with the criteria discussed under the
Completeness Report above.
</procdesc>
<procdate>1998</procdate>
<proccont>
<cntinfo>
<cntorgp>
<cntorg>
Remote Sensing and GIS Group, Technical Service
Center, US Bureau of Reclamation
</cntorg>
</cntorgp>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>Mailing Address</addrtype>
<address>POB 25007</address>
<city>Denver</city>
<state>CO</state>
<postal>80225</postal>
<country>USA</country>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>303-446-2283</cntvoice>
<cntfax>303-445-6337</cntfax>
<cntemail>jvonloh@do.usbr.gov</cntemail>
<hours>7:30 a.m. to 4:00 p.m. Monday Thru Friday, MST</hours>
</cntinfo>
</proccont>
</procstep>
<procstep>
<procdesc>
Data plot and observation coverages: Coverages for the plot and
observation data points were created from the plot and observation data
sheets. The coordinates on the data sheets were in datum NAD27. Once the
coverages were finalized they were reprojected into datum NAD83.
</procdesc>
<procdate>1998</procdate>
</procstep>
</lineage>
</dataqual>
<spdoinfo>
<direct>Vector</direct>
</spdoinfo>
<spref>
<horizsys>
<planar>
<gridsys>
<gridsysn>Universal Transverse Mercator</gridsysn>
<utm>
<utmzone>13</utmzone>
<transmer>
<longcm>-105</longcm>
<latprjo>0</latprjo>
<feast>500000</feast>
<fnorth>0</fnorth>
<sfctrmer>.9996</sfctrmer>
</transmer>
</utm>
</gridsys>
<planci>
<plance>coordinate pair</plance>
<coordrep>
<absres>1</absres>
<ordres>1</ordres>
</coordrep>
<plandu>meters</plandu>
</planci>
</planar>
<geodetic>
<horizdn>North American Datum of 1983</horizdn>
<ellips>Geodedic Reference System 80</ellips>
<semiaxis>6378137</semiaxis>
<denflat>298.257</denflat>
</geodetic>
</horizsys>
</spref>
<eainfo>
<overview>
<eaover>
VEGETATION COVERAGES: Due to the large size of the database, vegetation
coverages were named according to associated USGS 7.5m quads and the
quarterquad quadrant as follows: &lt;quadname&gt;_veg# with # referring to the
quarter quadrant as follows: 1 - Northwest quadrant; 2 - Northeast
quadrant; 3 - Southeast quadrant; 4 - Southwest quadrant. Coding
Information: Polygon coverage with labels in each polygon with the
following custom items: (veg_code - 3 3 I) coded with vegetation
classification number. See Supplemental Info under Id Info above for
complete listing of attribute codes and their descriptions; (photo - 6 6
I) coded with associated CIR photo number; (location - 6 6 C) coded
according to whether the polygon is in the park or buffer area. Also, each
arc was coded as follows: (digtype - 2 2 I) coded to identify how the arc
was transferred into the database or type of arc as follows: 1 = heads-up,
on screen digitizing; 2 = scanned mylar; 3 = arc associated with gis study
area border; 4 = arc associated with quarterquad border; 5 = arc
associated with park border. (veg_code - 3 3 I) linear wetland features
coded with vegetation classification number. BOUNDARY COVERAGES: bndrypark
- Park boundary coverage. This coverage was digitized from USGS 7.5m
quads. bndryproj - GIS mapping project area. This coverage was derived
from markings on a 1:100k map provided to us by the USGS/BRD. bndryquad -
Boundaries of all the 7.5m quads. This coverage was created via an
in-house AML that creates tics based on lower left and upper right
coordinates for the desired area. The program created tics every 7.5
minutes and then arcs were snapped to the tics to create the quad borders.
Coding Information: bndrypark - line coverage - no custom attributing.
bndryproj - line coverage - no custom attributing. bndryquad - polygon
coverage with labels in each quad polygon with the following items:
(quadname - 8 8 c) - abbreviated name for each quad; (fullname - 20 20 c)
- full quadname. DATA COVERAGES: dataobsv - Point coverage of observation
data points. dataplot - Point coverage of plot data points. Coding
Information: Label points with items as follows: (plot_code - 3 3 n) coded
with plot number from plot data sheets; (veg_code - 14 14 c) coded with
veg class text; (type - 10 10 c) coded with broad vegetation class (eg:
woodland). Note1: x-coord and y-coord added with ARC/INFO "addxy" command.
Note2: Field data points were collected with GPS units set to datum NAD27.
All coverages were re-projected into Datum NAD83 so the x- y- coordinates
will not match those shown on the data sheets. OTHER COVERAGES: sec_roads
- Line coverage of secondary roads digitized from USGS DOQQ. The parks
projects will be using DOQQ's as the basemap for transfer of information
from the CIR photos to the GIS database. The DOQQ's are standard USGS
product and are in datum of NAD83.
</eaover>
<eadetcit>
Wind Cave National Park, USGS/NPS Vegetation Mapping Program, Technical
Memorandum No. 8260-99-03, USBR
</eadetcit>
</overview>
</eainfo>
<distinfo>
<distrib>
<cntinfo>
<cntperp>
<cntper>USGS-NPS Vegetation Mapping Program Coordinator</cntper>
<cntorg>
U.S. Geological Survey, Center for Biological
Informatics
</cntorg>
</cntperp>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
<address>
U.S. Geological Survey, Center for Biological
Informatics, MS 302, Room 8000, Building 810,
Denver Federal Center
</address>
<city>Denver</city>
<state>Colorado</state>
<postal>80225</postal>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>(303) 202-4220</cntvoice>
<cntfax>303-202-4229</cntfax>
<cntfax>303-202-4219 (org)</cntfax>
<cntemail>gs-b-npsveg@usgs.gov</cntemail>
</cntinfo>
</distrib>
<resdesc>Wind Cave National Park Vegetation Map</resdesc>
<distliab>
Although these data have been processed successfully on a computer system at
the Biological Resources Division, no warranty expressed or implied is made
regarding the accuracy or utility of the data on any other system or for
general or scientific purposes, nor shall the act of distribution constitute
any such warranty. This disclaimer applies both to individual use of the
data and aggregate use with other data. It is strongly recommended that
these data are directly acquired from a Biological Resources Division
server, and not indirectly through other sources which may have changed the
data in some way. It is also strongly recommended that careful attention be
paid to the contents of the metadata file associated with these data. The
Biological Resources Division shall not be held liable for improper or
incorrect use of the data described and/or contained herein.
</distliab>
<stdorder>
<digform>
<digtinfo>
<formname>EXE</formname>
</digtinfo>
<digtopt>
<onlinopt>
<computer>
<networka>
<networkr>http://biology.usgs.gov/npsveg/ftp/vegmapping/wica/wica.exe</networkr>
</networka>
</computer>
</onlinopt>
</digtopt>
</digform>
<fees>None</fees>
</stdorder>
<stdorder>
<digform>
<digtinfo>
<formname>SDTS</formname>
</digtinfo>
<digtopt>
<onlinopt>
<computer>
<networka>
<networkr>http://biology.usgs.gov/npsveg/ftp/vegmapping/wica/wicasdts.exe</networkr>
</networka>
</computer>
</onlinopt>
</digtopt>
</digform>
<fees>None</fees>
</stdorder>
<stdorder>
<digform>
<digtinfo>
<formname>EXE</formname>
</digtinfo>
<digtopt>
<onlinopt>
<computer>
<networka>
<networkr>http://biology.usgs.gov/npsveg/ftp/vegmapping/wica/wicabdy.exe</networkr>
</networka>
</computer>
</onlinopt>
</digtopt>
</digform>
<fees>None</fees>
</stdorder>
<stdorder>
<digform>
<digtinfo>
<formname>SDTS</formname>
</digtinfo>
<digtopt>
<onlinopt>
<computer>
<networka>
<networkr>http://biology.usgs.gov/npsveg/ftp/vegmapping/wica/wicabdysdts.exe</networkr>
</networka>
</computer>
</onlinopt>
</digtopt>
</digform>
<fees>None</fees>
</stdorder>
<stdorder>
<digform>
<digtinfo>
<formname>GIF</formname>
</digtinfo>
<digtopt>
<onlinopt>
<computer>
<networka>
<networkr>http://biology.usgs.gov/npsveg/wica/images/wicaveg.gif</networkr>
</networka>
</computer>
</onlinopt>
</digtopt>
</digform>
<fees>None</fees>
</stdorder>
</distinfo>
<metainfo>
<metd>20012022</metd>
<metrd>20050523</metrd>
<metc>
<cntinfo>
<cntorgp>
<cntorg>USGS-NPS Vegetation Mapping Program Coordinator</cntorg>
</cntorgp>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
<address>
U.S. Geological Survey, Center for Biological Informatics, MS 302,
Room 8000, Building 810, Denver Federal Center
</address>
<city>Denver</city>
<state>Colorado</state>
<postal>80225</postal>
<country>USA</country>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>(303) 202-4220</cntvoice>
<cntfax>(303) 202-4219</cntfax>
<cntemail>gs-b-npsveg@usgs.gov</cntemail>
</cntinfo>
</metc>
<metstdn>FGDC-STD-001.1-1999 Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata, 1998 Part 1: Biological Data Profile, 1999</metstdn>
<metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
<metextns>
<onlink>http://biology.usgs.gov/fgdc.bio/bionwext.txt</onlink>
<metprof>Biological Data Profile FGDC-STD-001.1-1999</metprof>
</metextns>
</metainfo>
<mercury><begdate>19970601</begdate><enddate>19970631</enddate><htmlurl>http://mercury.ornl.gov/metadata/nbii/html/nbii/www.nbii.gov_metadata_mdata_CBI_usgs_brd_cbi_d_wicaveg.html</htmlurl><LTER-Site>nbii</LTER-Site></mercury></metadata>
