<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<metadata><Source>http://www.nbii.gov/metadata/mdata/CBI/usgs_brd_cbi_d_rocrfield.sgml</Source>
<idinfo>
<citation>
<citeinfo>
<origin>USGS, Biological Resources Division, Center for Biological Informatics</origin>
<pubdate>19961029</pubdate>
<title>Rock Creek Park Field Plots Data Base for Vegetation Mapping</title>
<geoform>maps data</geoform>
<serinfo>
<sername>USGS-NPS Vegetation Mapping Program</sername>
<issue>Rock Creek Park</issue>
</serinfo>
<pubinfo>
<pubplace>Denver, CO</pubplace>
<publish>USGS, Biological Resources Division, Center for Biological Informatics</publish>
</pubinfo>
<othercit>Created under contract to the USGS-BRD-CBI by The Nature Conservancy.</othercit>
<onlink>http://biology.usgs.gov/npsveg/rocr/fielddata.html</onlink>
</citeinfo>
</citation>
<descript>
<abstract>
The National Park Service (NPS), in conjunction
with the Biological Resources Division (BRD) of
the U.S. Geological Survey (USGS), has implemented
a program to "develop a uniform hierarchical
vegetation methodology" at a national level.  The
program will also create a geographic information
system (GIS) database for the parks under its
management.  The purpose of the data is to
document the state of vegetation within the NPS
service area during the 1990's, thereby providing
a baseline study for further analysis at the
Regional or Service-wide level.  Aerial
Information Systems (AIS) was subcontracted by
Environmental Systems Research Institute (ESRI),
the prime contractor, to perform the
photointerpretation for the program.  ESRI
subcontracted The Nature Conservancy (TNC) to
conduct the field sampling effort and to support
the development of the National Standard
Classification.
</abstract>
<purpose>
Several parks, representing different regions,
environmental conditions, and vegetation types,
were chosen by BRD to be part of the prototype
phase of the program.  The initial goal of the
prototype phase is to "develop, test, refine, and
finalize the standards and protocols" to be used
during the production phase of the project.  This
includes the development of a standardized
vegetation classification system for each park and
the establishment of photointerpretation, field,
and accuracy assessment procedures.  Rock Creek
Park, established in 1890, was designated as one
of the prototype parks.  The park is located on
the fall line between the Atlantic coastal plain
and the piedmont.  The main portion of the park is
bounded on the north by the Maryland State line
and on the south by the Virginia State line.  Its
western edge follows along Oregon Avenue, and it
is bounded on the east by 16th Street NW.  The
western outlying portions of the Park extend to
and slightly beyond Nebraska Avenue NW.  The
eastern outlying portions extend from 16th Street
NW to the junction of US Highway 1 and the
Maryland border.  The park is noted for having
exceptional resources, including six natural
resources that maintain its significance within
the National Park System.  Included in these six
natural resources, are three that are directly
related to the vegetation of the park.  They are:
1) Deciduous forests, 2) Wetlands, and 3) Plant
species protected in both Virginia and Maryland.
Based on these and other resources, Rock Creek
Park is divided up into nine management zones
pertaining to vegetation, automobile access,
recreation, administration, and cultural
resources.
</purpose>
<supplinf>
Rock Creek is one of the largest forested urban
parks in the United States, with more the &amp;frac34; of the
park's approximately 2,760 acres covered by mature
deciduous forest. A significant portion of this
forest is second growth, with a moderately high
diversity in canopy and understory species.  Rock
Creek Park is made up of steep canyons and side
slopes that bisect several significant east-west
trending ridgelines.  The park descends along the
fall line through numerous small rapids along the
creek.  Rock Creek itself, descends over 150' from
the state line to its confluence with the Potomac
River.  Flood plain development is fairly
restrictive, limited primarily to Rock Creek
itself.  Broad Branch, the main tributary to Rock
Creek within the park, flows southeasterly and
joins Rock Creek towards the southern portion of
the park. At the confluence, the park boundary
significantly narrows in its east-west extent.
All sections are accessible either by automobile
or by hiking.  Most portions of the park are
accessible through short hikes, usually under one
mile.  Gradients above the floodplain are
surprisingly steep, and make for some moderate
hiking.  For purposes of vegetation mapping, the
park was divided into four sections pertaining
primarily to its location on the fall line between
the coastal plain and piedmont.  The park was
further divided into the main portion of the park
(containing Rock Creek), and the various outliner
portions of the park to the east and west.
(previous geoform was 'database')</supplinf>
</descript>
<timeperd>
<timeinfo>
<sngdate>
<caldate>19961029</caldate>
</sngdate>
</timeinfo>
<current>Source_Photography_Date</current>
</timeperd>
<status>
<progress>Complete</progress>
<update>None Planned</update>
</status>
<spdom>
<descgeog>
The park is located on the fall line between the
Atlantic coastal plain and the piedmont.  The main
portion of the park is bounded on the north by the
Maryland State line and on the south by the
Virginia State line.  Its western edge follows
along Oregon Avenue, and it is bounded on the east
by 16th Street NW.  The western outlying portions
of the Park extend to and slightly beyond Nebraska
Avenue NW.  The eastern outlying portions extend
from 16th Street NW to the junction of US Highway
1 and the Maryland border.
</descgeog>
<bounding>
<westbc>77.1</westbc>
<eastbc>77</eastbc>
<northbc>38.98333</northbc>
<southbc>38.9</southbc>
</bounding>
</spdom>
<keywords>
<theme>
<themekt>None</themekt>
<themekey>National Park Service</themekey>
<themekey>U.S. Geological Service</themekey>
<themekey>The Nature Conservancy</themekey>
<themekey>Aerial Information Systems</themekey>
<themekey>Center for Biological Informatics</themekey>
<themekey>land cover</themekey>
<themekey>vegetation</themekey>
<themekey>community</themekey>
<themekey>association</themekey>
</theme>
<place>
<placekt>None</placekt>
<placekey>Rock Creek Park</placekey>
<placekey>Washington D.C.</placekey>
<placekey>USA</placekey>
</place>
<stratum>
<stratkt>None</stratkt>
<stratkey>Glover Archbold Park and Environs</stratkey>
<stratkey>Fort Totten Park, Barnard Hill Park and Environs</stratkey>
<stratkey>Land Use Areas of the Park</stratkey>
<stratkey>Coastal Plain</stratkey>
<stratkey>Piedmont</stratkey>
<stratkey>Forest Zone</stratkey>
</stratum>
<temporal>
<tempkt>None</tempkt>
<tempkey>Data Represents October 1996</tempkey>
</temporal>
</keywords>
<taxonomy>
<keywtax>
<taxonkt>None</taxonkt>
<taxonkey>National Vegetation Classification System</taxonkey>
</keywtax>
<taxonsys>
<classsys>
<classcit>
<citeinfo>
<origin>
United States Department of the Interior National
Biological Survey and National Park Service
</origin>
<pubdate>19941101</pubdate>
<title>
Standardized National Vegetation Classification
System
</title>
<edition>Version 1</edition>
<geoform>Classification System</geoform>
<serinfo>
<sername>NBS/NPS Vegetation Mapping Program</sername>
<issue>Final Draft</issue>
</serinfo>
<pubinfo>
<pubplace>Redlands, California</pubplace>
<publish>ESRI</publish>
</pubinfo>
<othercit>Prepared by the Nature Conservancy</othercit>
</citeinfo>
</classcit>
</classsys>
<idref>
<citeinfo>
<origin>
United States Department of the Interior National
Biological Survey and National Park Service
</origin>
<pubdate>19941101</pubdate>
<title>
Standardized National Vegetation Classification
System
</title>
<edition>Version 1</edition>
<geoform>Classification System</geoform>
<serinfo>
<sername>NBS/NPS Vegetation Mapping Program</sername>
<issue>Final Draft</issue>
</serinfo>
<pubinfo>
<pubplace>Redlands, California</pubplace>
<publish>ESRI</publish>
</pubinfo>
<othercit>Prepared by the Nature Conservancy</othercit>
</citeinfo>
</idref>
<taxonpro>
See "Photo Interpretation Report, BRD/NPS Vegetation and Inventory and Mapping Program,
Rock Creek Park," October 1, 1998 &lt;http://biology.usgs.gov/npsveg/rocr/pi_rpt.pdf&gt;
</taxonpro>
<taxoncom>Complete</taxoncom>
</taxonsys>
<taxongen>
Vegetation Alliances of the National Vegetation
Classification System (October 1995)
</taxongen>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Kingdom</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Plantae</taxonrv>
</taxoncl>
</taxonomy>
<accconst>None</accconst>
<useconst>
Any person using the information presented here
should fully understand the data collection and
compilation procedures, as described in these
metadata, before beginning analysis.  The burden
for determining fitness for use lies entirely with
the user.  For purposes of publication or
dissemination, citations should be given to the
U.S. Geological Survey and the National Park
Service
</useconst>
<ptcontac>
<cntinfo>
<cntorgp>
<cntper>USGS-NPS Vegetation Mapping Program Coordinator</cntper>
<cntorg>
USGS Biological Resources Division, Center for Biological
Informatics
</cntorg>
</cntorgp>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>Physical Address</addrtype>
<address>USGS</address>
<address>Biological Resources Division, CBI</address>
<address>Building 810, Room 8000</address>
<city>Denver</city>
<state>Colorado</state>
<postal>80225-0046</postal>
<country>USA</country>
</cntaddr>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>Mailing Address</addrtype>
<address>USGS</address>
<address>Biological Resources Division, CBI</address>
<address>PO BOX 25046, DFC, MS302</address>
<city>Denver</city>
<state>Colorado</state>
<postal>80225-0046</postal>
<country>USA</country>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>(303) 202-4220</cntvoice>
<cntfax>303-202-4229</cntfax>
<cntfax>303-202-4219 (org)</cntfax>
<cntemail>gs-b-npsveg@usgs.gov</cntemail>
</cntinfo>
</ptcontac>
<browse>
<browsen>http://biology.usgs.gov/npsveg/rocr/images/rocrplot.jpg</browsen>
<browsed>182 Kbyte</browsed>
<browset>JPEG</browset>
</browse>
<secinfo>
<secsys>None</secsys>
<secclass>None</secclass>
<sechandl>None</sechandl>
</secinfo>
<native>Microsoft Access mdb</native>
</idinfo>
<dataqual>
<attracc>
<attraccr>
Physical description - For 77 sites, contains
site code, site name, GPS coordinates, physical factors
(elevation, slope, aspect, topographic setting, landform,
surface geology, cowardin system type, hydrography,
surface materials, soil texture and drainage,
leaf characteristics, and physiography.
Species listing - Contains species listings for each site,
listed by site code one species per line, with species type,
plant code, and strata code.
</attraccr>
</attracc>
<logic>
Physical description - Entries for each of the listed
attributes are in the form of consistent groupings of
either textual or numerical descriptors.
Species - Entries for each of the listed attributes are
in the form of consistent groupings of either textual or
numerical descriptors.
</logic>
<complete>
Descriptive entries for each of the 77 plots are complete
for each of the applicable attributes listed in the database.
</complete>
<posacc>
<horizpa>
<horizpar>
Unknown.  The coordinates associated with each plot are assumed
to be generated from GPS receivers, but no specific information
is currently available.
</horizpar>
</horizpa>
</posacc>
<lineage>
<method>
<methtype>Field</methtype>
<methdesc>
FIELD METHODS: Plots were subjectively placed so as to be
most representative of the mapped vegetation unit. All mapped
vegetation types were sampled over a range of environmental
variation. Additional plots were taken where the vegetation type
documented in the field was unclassified or less well known. For
example, the ash floodplain map unit polygons were targeted
specifically for field verification. This vegetation types was later
classified as part of the Platanus occidentalis - Fraxinus
pennsylvanica Forest Association.
Plot sizes ranged from 20 x 20 m for forests and woodlands,
10 x 10 m for shrublands, and 5 x 5 m for herbaceous vegetation.
In some cases, where the polygons were too narrow to
reasonably accommodate standard plot sizes, the plots were
adjusted accordingly, e.g., 10 x 20 m plots were often used in
sampling narrow bands of floodplain forest in the park. The
vegetation was visually divided into strata, and all the species of
each stratum were listed and percent cover estimated. Additional
species within the vegetation unit or polygon that occurred outside
of sampled plots were listed separately. Species that were not
identifiable in the field were collected for later identification. In
addition to floristic information, the following environmental
information was recorded on field forms: soil profile description,
flooding regime, soil moisture regime, slope, aspect and evidence
of disturbance. Latitude and longitude of each plot was recorded
using a GPS unit. The vegetation profile in cross-section was
sketched by hand to represent the location and setting of the plot.
Seventy-seven vegetation plots in total were sampled for this project.
DATA ANALYSIS: Park plot data (77 plots) were entered by
Rock Creek Park staff into The Nature Conservancy's PLOTS
Database System (1997) on a Microsoft Access platform. Species
were assigned standardized codes and names based on the PLANTS
database developed by National Resources Conservation Service
(NRCS) in cooperation with the Biota of North America Program
(BONAP). For the vegetation analysis, portions of the Rock Creek
Park data set were copied onto spreadsheets in a format compatible
with PC-ORD Multivariate Analysis package (McCune and Mefford
1997). Plots that represented cultivated types or exotics-dominated
sites were excluded from the analysis. Several outliers (plots that are
very dissimilar from all the others) were identified using Sorenson and
Euclidian formulas in PC-ORD and were excluded from the primary
analyses. The remaining data set of 67 plots was analyzed with Detrended
Correspondence Analysis/DCA (Hill and Gauch 1980) and Two-Way
Indicator Species Analysis/TWINSPAN (Hill 1979). DCA ordinates both
species and samples simultaneously along perceived gradients (e.g. that
may indicate moisture gradient, elevation, etc.). TWINSPAN successively
divides the plots into groups that are similar in species composition. The
initial results indicated that some plots were artificially clustering based on
high percent cover of several exotic species. The data set was further
modified to exclude these exotics and the revised data were re-analyzed
with DCA and TWINSPAN.
These groups were compared with the National Vegetation Classification
(Grossman et al. 1998) and matched to existing Alliances and/or Associations
where appropriate.
Environmental data on soil characteristics, slope, aspect and topography for
each plot were used to interpret the results. The soil survey, geologic map
and topographic maps were also used in the interpretation. Plot information
on flooding regime was incomplete but could be extrapolated from the polygon
and plot locations delineated on air photos and topographic maps.
Environmental data were analyzed using the ordination program CANOCO in
PC-ORD. However, due to the small size of the study area, the relatively
uniform topography of the park and some incomplete and inconsistent data on
soil types and hydrology, the CANOCO results provided little additional
information for the classification.
</methdesc>
<methcite>
<citeinfo>
<origin>
Lesley Sneddon, Julie Lundgren, Mark Anderson,
Dennis Grossman, Kathy Goodin, Anthony Curtis,
Mark Bryer, Robert Ford, Eden Crane, Susan Salmons,
Tara Faud, Stephanie Glenn, Tim Assal, Jason Grant,
Jeannie Whitler, Rebecca Wright, Jim Drake
The Nature Conservancy,
Eastern Regional Office,
201 Devonshire Street, 5th Floor,
Boston, MA 02110
and
The Nature Conservancy,
International Headquarters,
1815 North Lynn Street,
Arlington, VA 22209
</origin>
<pubdate>1998</pubdate>
<title>
USGS-NPS Vegetation Mapping Program,
Classification of the Vegetation of Rock Creek Park
</title>
<geoform>Report</geoform>
<pubinfo>
<pubplace>Denver, CO</pubplace>
<publish>USGS, BRD, Center for Biological Informatics</publish>
</pubinfo>
<othercit>Created under contract to the USGS-BRD-CBI.</othercit>
<onlink>&lt;http://biology.usgs.gov/npsveg/rocr/methods.pdf&gt;</onlink>
</citeinfo>
</methcite>
</method>
<srcinfo>
<srccite>
<citeinfo>
<origin>Air Survey Corporation Sterling, Virginia</origin>
<pubdate>19961029</pubdate>
<pubtime>Unknown</pubtime>
<title>Rock Creek Park</title>
<edition>Version 1.0</edition>
<geoform>image</geoform>
<serinfo>
<sername>1.0</sername>
<issue>Unknown</issue>
</serinfo>
<pubinfo>
<pubplace>Sterling Virginia</pubplace>
<publish>Air Survey Corporation</publish>
</pubinfo>
<othercit>The aerial photography is CIR 1:6,000 scale.</othercit>
<onlink>http://biology.usgs.gov/npsveg/rocr/photos.html</onlink>
</citeinfo>
</srccite>
<srcscale>12000</srcscale>
<typesrc>CIR Aerial Photography</typesrc>
<srctime>
<timeinfo>
<sngdate>
<caldate>19961029</caldate>
<time>Unknown</time>
</sngdate>
</timeinfo>
<srccurr>publication date</srccurr>
</srctime>
<srccitea>ASC</srccitea>
<srccontr>None</srccontr>
</srcinfo>
<procstep>
<procdesc>See Methodology Description above</procdesc>
<srcused>ASC</srcused>
<procdate>199803</procdate>
</procstep>
</lineage>
</dataqual>
<spdoinfo>
<indspref>
The ecology field sites were digitized to indicate
the area for which a TNC ecologist conducted an
ecological field sampling.
</indspref>
<direct>Point</direct>
<ptvctinf>
<sdtsterm>
<sdtstype>Point</sdtstype>
</sdtsterm>
</ptvctinf>
</spdoinfo>
<spref>
<horizsys>
<planar>
<gridsys>
<gridsysn>Universal Transverse Mercator</gridsysn>
<utm>
<utmzone>18</utmzone>
<transmer>
<longcm>-180</longcm>
<latprjo>-90</latprjo>
<feast>50000</feast>
<fnorth>0</fnorth>
<sfctrmer>0.9996</sfctrmer>
</transmer>
</utm>
</gridsys>
<planci>
<plance>coordinate pair</plance>
<coordrep>
<absres>1</absres>
<ordres>1</ordres>
</coordrep>
<plandu>Meters</plandu>
</planci>
</planar>
<geodetic>
<horizdn>North American Datum of 1983</horizdn>
<ellips>Geodedic Reference System 80</ellips>
<semiaxis>6378137</semiaxis>
<denflat>298.257</denflat>
</geodetic>
</horizsys>
<vertdef>
<altsys>
<altdatum>North American Vertical Datum of 1988</altdatum>
<altres>1</altres>
<altunits>Feet</altunits>
<altenc>Explicit elevation coordinate included with horizontal coordinates</altenc>
</altsys>
</vertdef>
</spref>
<eainfo>
<overview>
<eaover>
Physical Descriptive Data:
Plot Code: This field is the unique identifier for a Plot record.  It is
generated by the system, at the time a new record  is entered into
the database.  The Plot Code is assembled from two parts: the
Location Code and the Plot Code Counter, which is a sequential
counter field that is increased automatically each time a Plot is
entered for that Location. The sequential counter can be reset to
any number you would like.
SubPlot: ‘yes&amp;#146; if the plot is a subplot of another larger plot. Blank if
the plot is not a subplot of another plot.
Polygon Code: Code indicating the vegetation polygon where the plot was
taken.  This is entered only if working from previously delineated
photos.
Provisional Community Name: The name of the vegetation type which most
closely resembles this type using the classification system.
Entered at the finest level of the classification possible.  This
is meant to be a field call of the vegetation classification and
may change when the data are analyzed.  Colloquial names can be
used in this field if necessary.
Classified Community Name: The community name from the National
Vegetation Classification System, once the data are analyzed and
the community has been classified.
TNC Elcode: The Elcode (Element Code) for the community element
corresponding to the Classified Community Name.
Quad Name: Appropriate name/scale from survey map used; 7.5 minute
quadrangle used if possible.
Quad Code: Code of USGS 7.5 minute quadrangle map.
GPS Techniques: (empty) The projection and GPS datum, plus any
noteworthy comments regarding equipment and/or techniques used to
process the GPS data.
Corrected UTM X: X coordinate of Universal Transverse Mercator
projection after post-processing correction.  Filled in at the
office, not in the field.
Corrected UTM Y: Y coordinate of Universal Transverse Mercator
projection after post-processing correction.  Filled in at the
office, not in the field.
Survey Date: Date the survey was taken; month, day, year*.  *Year is
entered as 4 characters, so as to avoid the "Year 2000" computer
problem.
Surveyors: (empty) Names (and addresses, if appropriate) of surveyors,
principle surveyor listed first.
X Dimension: The length in meters* of one side of each of the plots in
which samples were taken.  If the plot is circular, enter the
length of its radius.  If transects were used, enter their length
here. The value of X Dimension should correspond to the plot
specified in the Plot Shape field.  *NOTE:  Dimensions MUST be
converted to meters.
Y Dimension: The length in meters* of the side of the plot adjacent to
the side entered in the X Dimension field.  The value entered in
the Y Dimension field should correspond to the plot referred to in
the Plot Shape  and X Dimension  fields.  Leave this field blank if
the plot is circular.  Enter a one if a transect was used.  *NOTE:
Dimensions MUST be converted to meters.
Plot Shape: Shape which best describes that used for this sample.
Possible values are "rectangular", "square", "circular",
"transect/strip", "Other"
Photos: "yes" if photos of the plot were taken at the time of sampling.
Permanent: "yes" to indicate if the plot has been permanently marked.
Slope: Degrees of slope measured using a clinometer.  Possible values
include "FLAT"=0°=0%, "GENTLE"=0-5°=1-9%, "MODERATE"=6-14°=10-25%,
"SOMEWHAT STEEP"=15-26°=26-49%, "STEEP"=27-45°=50-100%, "VERY
STEEP"=45-69°=101-275%, "ABRUPT"=70-100°=276-300%,
"OVERHANG/SHELTERED"=&gt;100°=&gt;300%
Aspect: aspect of the slope; measured using a compass (should have been
corrected for the magnetic declination).  		 Possible Values are
"flat", "variable". Topo Position: Possible values include
"INTERFLUVE"=(crest, summit, ridge) linear top of ridge, hill, or
mountain; the elevated area between two fluves (drainageways)
that sheds water to the drainageways.
"HIGH SLOPE"=(shoulder slope, upper slope, convex creep slope)
geomorphic component that forms the uppermost inclined surface
at the top of a slope. Comprises the transition zone from
backslope to summit.  Surface is dominantly convex in profile
and erosional in origin.
"HIGH LEVEL"=(mesa) level top of plateau.
"MIDSLOPE"=(transportational midslope, middle slope) intermediate
slope position
"BACKSLOPE"=(dipslope) subset of midslopes which are steep, linear,
and may include cliff segments (fall faces).
"STEP IN SLOPE"=(ledge, terracette) nearly level shelf interrupting
a steep slope, rock wall, or cliff face.
"LOWSLOPE"=(lower slope, foot slope, colluvial footslope) inner
gently inclined surface at the base of a slope.  Surface
profile is generally concave and a transition between midslope
or backslope, and toe slope.
"TOESLOPE"=(alluvial toeslope) outermost gently inclined surface at
base of a slope.  In profile, commonly gentle and linear and
characterized by alluvial deposition.
"LOW LEVEL"=(terrace) valley floor or shoreline representing the
former position of an alluvial plane, lake, or shore.
"CHANNEL WALL"=(bank) sloping side of a channel.
"CHANNEL BED"=(narrow valley bottom, gully arroyo) bed of single
or braided watercourse commonly barren of vegetation and
formed of modern alluvium.
"BASIN FLOOR"=(depression) nearly level to gently sloping, bottom
surface of a basin.
Landform: A descriptive term for the landform characteristics of the
area.
Surficial Geology: a term that describes the geologic substrate
influencing the plant community (bedrock or surficial materials).
Cowardin System: "Upland" if the system is not a wetland, if wetland,
the name of the USFWS system which best describes its hydrology and
landform.  Values include
"ESTUARINE" = Deepwater tidal habitats and adjacent tidal wetlands
that are usually semi enclosed by land but have open, partly
obstructed, or sporadic access to the open ocean, and in which
ocean water is at least occasionally diluted by freshwater
runoff from the land.  The salinity is above 0.5 parts per
thousand, and may be periodically increased above that of the
open ocean by evaporation.  Along some low energy coastlines
there is appreciable dilution of sea water.  Off shore areas
with typical estuarine plants and animals, such as red
mangroves and eastern oysters are also included in the
Estuarine System.  The presence of halophytic plants may be
used to differentiate Estuarine from other freshwater systems
if there is insufficient data on salinity.
"PALUSTRINE" = Nontidal wetlands dominated by trees, shrubs,
persistent emergents, emergent mosses or lichens, and all such
wetlands that occur in tidal areas where salinity due to ocean
derived salts is below 0.5 parts per thousand.  It also
includes wetlands lacking such vegetation, but with all of the
following four characteristics: (1) area less than 8 ha (20
acres); (2) active waveformed or bedrock shoreline features
lacking; (3) water depth in the deepest part of basin less
than 2m at low water; and salinity due to ocean derived salts
less than 0.5 parts per thousand.
"RIVERINE" = Includes all wetlands and deepwater habitats contained
within a channel, with two exceptions: (1) wetland dominated
by trees, shrubs, persistent emergents, emergent mosses, or
lichens, and (2) habitats with water containing ocean derived
salts in excess of 0.5 parts per thousand.  A channel is "an
open conduit either naturally or artificially created which
periodically on continuously contains moving water, or which
forms a connecting link between two bodies of standing water".
"LACUSTRINE" = Includes wetlands and deepwater habitats with all of
the following characteristics: (1) situated in a topographic
depression or a dammed river channel; (2) lacking trees,
shrubs, persistent emergents, emergent mosses or lichens with
greater than 30% areal coverage: and (3) total area exceeds 8
ha (20 acres).  Similar wetland and deepwater habitats
totaling less than 8 ha are also included in the Lacustrine
System if an active waveformed or bedrock shoreline feature
makes up all or part of the boundary, or if the water depth in
the deepest part of the basin exceeds 2 m (6.6 feet) at low
water.  Lacustrine waters may be tidal or nontidal, but ocean
derived salinity is always less than 0.5 parts per thousand.
Hydro Regime: The appropriate term from the following possible values
"SEMIPERMANENTLY FLOODED" = Surface water persists throughout
growing season in most years except during periods of drought.
Land surface is normally saturated when water level drops
below soil surface.  Includes Cowardin's Intermittently
Exposed and Semipermanently Flooded modifiers.
"SEASONALLY FLOODED" = Surface water is present for extended
periods during the growing season, but is absent by the end of
the growing season in most years.  The water table after
flooding ceases is very variable, extending from saturated to
a water table well below the ground surface.  Includes
Cowardin's Seasonal, Seasonal-Saturated, and Seasonal-Well
Drained modifiers.
"SATURATED" = Surface water is seldom present, but substrate is
saturated to surface for extended periods during the growing
season.  Equivalent to Cowardin's Saturated modifier.
"TEMPORARILY FLOODED" = Surface water present for brief periods
during growing season, but water table usually lies well below
soil surface.  Often characterizes flood-plain wetlands.
Equivalent to Cowardin's Temporary modifier.
"INTERMITTENTLY FLOODED" = Substrate is usually exposed, but
surface water can be present for variable periods without
detectable seasonal periodicity.  Inundation is not
predictable to a give season and is dependent upon highly
localized rain storms.  this modifier was developed for use in
the arid West for water regimes of Playa lakes, intermittent
streams, and dry washes but can be used in other parts of the
U.S. where appropriate.  This modifier can be applied to both
wetland and non-wetland situations.  Equivalent to Cowardin's
Intermittently Flooded modifier.
"PERMANENTLY FLOODED" = Water covers the land surface at all times
of the year in all years.  Equivalent to Cowardin's
"permanently flooded".
"PERMANENTLY FLOODED TIDAL" = Salt water covers the land surface at
all times of the year in all years.  This modifier applies
only to permanently flooded areas irregularly flooded by fresh
tidal water.  Equivalent to Cowardin's "permanently
flooded/tidal".
"TIDALLY FLOODED" = flooded by the alternate rise and fall of the
surface of oceans, seas, and the bays, rivers, etc. connected
to them, caused by the attraction of the moon and sun or by
the back-up of water caused by unfavorable winds.
"UNKNOWN" = The water regime of the area is not known.  The unit
is simply described as "(wetland)'.
Salinity/Halinity: Possible values include
Coastal Tidal: Saltwater - tidal = &gt; 30 ppt
Coastal Tidal: Brackish = 0.5 - 30 ppt
Coastal Tidal: Freshwater = &lt; 0.5 ppt
Inland: Saltwater = &gt; 30 ppt
Inland: Brackish = 0.5 - 30 ppt
Soil Texture: Simplified Key to Soil Texture (Brewer and McCann, 1982)
A1   Soil does not remain in a ball when squeezed . . . . . . .sand
A2   Soil remains in a ball when squeezed . . . . . . . . . . . . B
B1   Squeeze the ball between your thumb and forefinger, attempting
to make a ribbon that you push up over your finger.
Soil makes no ribbon . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .  loamy sand
B2   Soil makes a ribbon; may be very short . . . . . . . . . . . C
C1   Ribbon extends less than 1 inch before breaking . . . . . . . D
C2   Ribbon extends 1 inch or more before breaking . . . . . . . .E
D1   Add excess water to small amount of soil;
soil feels at least slightly gritty . . . . loam or sandy loam
D2   Soil feels smooth . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .  silt loam
E1   Soil makes a ribbon that breaks when 12 inches long; cracks if
bent into a ring . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . F
E2   Soil makes a ribbon 2+ inches long; doesn't crack when bent
into a ring . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .G
F1   Add excess water to small amount of soil; soil feels at least
slightly gritty . . . . . . . . . sandy clay loam or clay loam
F2   Soil feels smooth . . . . . . . . . . .silty clay loam or silt
G1   Add excess water to a small amount of soil; soil feels at
least slightly gritty . . . . . . . . . . . sandy clay or clay
G2   Soil feels smooth . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . silty clay
Soil Drainage: Soil drainage classes are defined in terms of (1) actual
moisture content (in excess of field moisture capacity), and (2)
the extent of the period during which excess water is present in
the plant root zone.  It is recognized that permeability, level of
groundwater, and seepage are factors affecting moisture status.
However, because these are not easily observed or measured in the
field, they cannot be used generally as criteria of moisture
status.  It is further recognized that soil profile morphology, for
example mottling, normally, but not always, reflects soil moisture
status.  Although soil morphology may be a valuable field
indication of moisture status, it should not be the overriding
criterion.  Soil drainage classes cannot be based solely on the
presence or absence of mottling.  Topographic position and
vegetation as well as soil morphology are useful field criteria for
assessing soil moisture status.
RAPIDLY DRAINED - The soil moisture content seldom exceeds field
capacity in any horizon except immediately after water
addition.  Soils are free from any evidence of gleying
throughout the profile.  Rapidly drained soils are commonly
coarse textured or soils on steep slopes.
WELL DRAINED - The soil moisture content does not normally exceed
field capacity in any horizon (except possibly the C) for a
significant part of the year.  Soils are usually free from
mottling in the upper 3 feet, but may be mottled below this
depth.  B horizons, if present, are reddish, brownish, or
yellowish.
MODERATELY WELL DRAINED - The soil moisture in excess of field
capacity remains for a small but significant period of the
year.  Soils are commonly mottled (chroma &lt; 2) in the lower B
and C horizons or below a depth of 2 feet.  The Ae horizon, if
present, may be faintly mottled in fine textured soils and in
medium textured soils that have a slowly permeable layer below
the solum.  In grassland soils the B and C horizons may be
only faintly mottled and the A horizon may be relatively thick
and dark.
SOMEWHAT POORLY DRAINED - The soil moisture in excess of field
capacity remains in subsurface horizons for moderately long
periods during the year.  Soils are commonly mottled in the B
and C horizons; the Ae horizon, if present, may be mottled.
The matrix generally has a lower chroma than in the well
drained soil on similar parent material.
POORLY DRAINED - The soil moisture in excess of field capacity
remains in all horizons for a large part of the year.  The
soils are usually very strongly gleyed.  Except in high chroma
parent materials the B, if present, and upper C horizons
usually have matrix colors of low chroma.  Faint mottling may
occur throughout.
VERY POORLY DRAINED - Free water remains at or within 12 inches of
the surface most of the year.  The soils are usually very
strongly gleyed.  Subsurface horizons usually are of low
chroma and yellowish to bluish hues.  Mottling may be present
but at depth in the profile.  Very poorly drained soils
usually have a mucky or peaty surface horizon.
Leaf Phenology: The value which best describes the leaf phenology of the
dominant stratum.
EVERGREEN - Greater than 75% of the total woody cover is never
without green foliage.
DECIDUOUS - Greater than 75% of the total woody cover sheds its
foliage simultaneously in connection with the unfavorable
season.
COLD DECIDUOUS - Unfavorable season mainly characterized by winter
frost.
DROUGHT DECIDUOUS - Unfavorable season mainly characterized by
drought, in most cases winter-drought.  Foliage is shed
regularly every year.  Most trees with relatively thick,
fissured bark.
MIXED EVERGREEN - DECIDUOUS - Evergreen and deciduous species
generally contribute 5-75% of the total woody cover.
MIXED EVERGREEN / COLD DECIDUOUS - Evergreen and cold-deciduous
species admixed.
MIXED EVERGREEN / DROUGHT DECIDUOUS - Evergreen and drought-
deciduous species admixed.
HERB - PERENNIAL - Herbaceous vegetation composed of more than 50%
perennial species.
HERB - ANNUAL - Herbaceous vegetation composed of more than 50%
annual species.
Leaf Type: The value which best describes the leaf form of the
dominant stratum.
BROADLEAF - Woody vegetation primarily broadleaved (generally
contribute to greater than 50% of the total woody cover).
NEEDLELEAF - Woody vegetation primarily needleleaved (generally
contribute to greater than 50% cover).
MYCROPHYLLOUS - Woody cover primarily microphyllous.
GRAMINOID - Herbaceous vegetation composed of more than 50%
graminoid / stipe leaf species.
BROADLEAF HERBACEOUS (FORB) - Herbaceous vegetation composed of
more than 50% broadleaf forb species.
PTERIDOPHYTE - Herbaceous vegetation composed of more than 50%
species with frond or frondlike leaves.
Physio Class: Physiognomic classes are determined by assessing the
relative percent cover and height of the lifeform comprising the
uppermost strata with cover greater than 0%.  (Note: Percent canopy
cover and height ranges are provided as guidelines, not strict
cutoff points).
FOREST - Trees (&gt;5m) with crowns interlocking (generally forming 60-
100% cover).
WOODLAND - Trees (&gt;5m) with crowns not touching (25-60% cover).
SPARSE WOODLAND - Trees (&gt;5m) with crowns widely spaced (10-25%
cover).
SHRUBLAND - Shrubs/Trees (0.5 - 5m) with 25-100% cover.
SPARSE SHRUBLAND - Shrubs/Trees (0.5 - 5m) with 10 - 25 % cover.
DWARF SHRUBLAND - Dwarf Shrubs/Shrubs/Trees (&lt;0.5m) with 25-100%
cover
SPARSE DWARF SHRUBLAND - Dwarf Shrubs/Shrubs/Trees (&lt;0.5m) with
10-25% cover.
HERBACEOUS - Herbaceous plants with 10-100% cover.
SPARSE VASCULAR / NON-VASCULAR - 1-10% Vascular Vegetation.
T1 Hgt: Average height of emergent trees. 01=&lt;0.5m, 02=0.5-1m, 03=1-2m,
04=2-5m, 05=5-10m, 06=10-15m, 07=15-20m, 08=20-35m, 09=35-50m,
10=&gt;50m
T1 Cover: class value that represents the average percent cover of the
whole emergent tree stratum.
T2 Hgt: Average height of tree canopy.  01=&lt;0.5m, 02=0.5-1m, 03=1-2m,
04=2-5m, 05=5-10m, 06=10-15m, 07=15-20m, 08=20-35m, 09=35-50m,
10=&gt;50m
T2 Cover:  class value that represents the average percent cover of the
whole tree canopy stratum.
T3 Hgt: Average height of tree subcanopy.  01=&lt;0.5m, 02=0.5-1m, 03=1-2m,
04=2-5m, 05=5-10m, 06=10-15m, 07=15-20m, 08=20-35m, 09=35-50m,
10=&gt;50m
T3 Cover:  class value that represents the average percent cover of the
whole tree subcanopy stratum.
S1 Hgt: Average height of tall shrubs (&lt;5 m).  01=&lt;0.5m, 02=0.5-1m,
03=1-2m, 04=2-5m, 05=5-10m, 06=10-15m, 07=15-20m, 08=20-35m,
09=35-50m, 10=&gt;50m
S1 Cover:  class value that represents the average percent cover of the
whole tall shrubs stratum.
S2 Hgt: Average height of short shrubs (&lt; 2m).  01=&lt;0.5m, 02=0.5-1m,
03=1-2m, 04=2-5m, 05=5-10m, 06=10-15m, 07=15-20m, 08=20-35m,
09=35-50m, 10=&gt;50m
S2 Cover:  class value that represents the average percent cover of the
whole short shrubs stratum.
H Hgt: Average height of Herbaceous stratum.  01=&lt;0.5m, 02=0.5-1m,
03=1-2m, 04=2-5m, 05=5-10m, 06=10-15m, 07=15-20m, 08=20-35m,
09=35-50m, 10=&gt;50m
H Cover:  class value that represents the average percent cover of the
whole Herbaceous stratum.
N Hgt: Average height of Nonvascular stratum.  01=&lt;0.5m, 02=0.5-1m,
03=1-2m, 04=2-5m, 05=5-10m, 06=10-15m, 07=15-20m, 08=20-35m,
09=35-50m, 10=&gt;50m
N Cover:  class value that represents the average percent cover of the
whole Nonvascular stratum.
V Hgt: Average height of Vine / Liana stratum.  01=&lt;0.5m, 02=0.5-1m,
03=1-2m, 04=2-5m, 05=5-10m, 06=10-15m, 07=15-20m, 08=20-35m,
09=35-50m, 10=&gt;50m
V Cover:  class value that represents the average percent cover of the
whole Vine / Liana stratum.
E Hgt: Average height of Epiphyte stratum.  01=&lt;0.5m, 02=0.5-1m,
03=1-2m, 04=2-5m, 05=5-10m, 06=10-15m, 07=15-20m, 08=20-35m,
09=35-50m, 10=&gt;50m
E Cover:  class value that represents the average percent cover of the
whole Epiphyte stratum.
Other Measure1 Defined: Non-standard cover classes; 0=No data; 1=&lt;1%;
2=1-10%; 3=10-25%; 4=25-50%; 5=50-75%; 6=75-95%; 7=&gt;95
Other Measure2 Defined:
Animal Use Evidence: Comment on any evidence of use of the plot /
polygon by non-domestic animals (i.e., tracks, scat, gopher or
prairie dog mounds, etc.).  Notes on domestic animals should be
made in the field Disturbance Comments.
Disturbance Comments: Comment on any evidence of natural or
anthropogenic disturbance and specify the source.
Other Comments: Use this field for general comments, or any comments
that don't seem to fit elsewhere.
Update:
User:
Species Counter:
Optional Fields Defined: Hydrologic zones
Opt1: Hydrologic zone number
Species Listing Data for Plots:
Plot Code: This field is the unique identifier for a Plot record.  It is
generated by the system, at the time a new record  is entered into
the database.  The Plot Code is assembled from two parts: the
Location Code and the Plot Code Counter, which is a sequential
counter field that is increased automatically each time a Plot is
entered for that Location. The sequential counter can be reset to
any number you would like.
Plant Symbol: The symbol field provides a quick and easy way to search
for a species name in the PLANTS database.  It generally consists
of the first two characters of the Genus name, plus the first two
characters of the Species name.  Identical symbol codes that are
for different species names are appended with tie-breaker
characters.
Scientific Name: The scientific name for an individual species record
within the NRCS PLANTS Database.  As supplied by the NRCS, this
field also contains authority information.  This field is used as
validation data when a species' name is entered into the Species
Scientific Name field in either the Plots or the AA Observations
table.
Common Name: The common name for an individual species record within the
NRCS PLANTS Database.
Family: The family name for an individual species within the NRCS PLANTS
Database.
Used PLANTS: This field will be automatically checked if the name
appearing in the Species Scientific Name field is found in the
PLANTS database.  Note that the automatic check-off will only
take place if there is an exact match between the Species Scientific Name
and the name as listed in PLANTS.
Source: This field indicates the source of the name record in the PLANTS
Database.  Values are:
SS=Standard Source (e.g. the NRCS PLANTS list),
NS=Non-standard Source (any source other than NRCS),
SY=Accepted synonym by NRCS list.
Within Plot:
The Stratum Sort: The stratum in which this species occurs.  T1=Emergent Tree,
T2= Tree Canopy, T3=Tree Subcanopy, S1=Tall Shrub (&gt;5m),
S2=Short Shrub (&lt;2m), S3=Dwarf-Shrub, H=Herbaceous, N=Nonvascular,
E=Epiphyte, V=Vine/Liana.
Diagnostic: This is to be checked if the species is known to be
diagnostic of the vegetation type.
Other Measure1:
Other Measure2:
Update:
User:
</eaover>
<eadetcit>
Grossman, D. Et al. 1994.  National Park Service
Vegetation Mapping Project,
Standardized National Vegetation Classification System 209 pp.
</eadetcit>
</overview>
</eainfo>
<distinfo>
<distrib>
<cntinfo>
<cntperp>
<cntper>USGS-NPS Vegetation Mapping Program Coordinator</cntper>
<cntorg>
U.S. Geological Survey, Biological Resources
Division, Center for Informatics
</cntorg>
</cntperp>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>Mailing Address</addrtype>
<address>USGS</address>
<address>Biological Resources Division</address>
<address>Center for Informatics</address>
<address>PO Box 25046, DFC, MS302</address>
<city>Denver</city>
<state>Colorado</state>
<postal>80225-0046</postal>
<country>USA</country>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>(303) 202-4220</cntvoice>
<cntfax>303-202-4229</cntfax>
<cntfax>303-202-4219 (org)</cntfax>
<cntemail>gs-b-npsveg@usgs.gov</cntemail>
</cntinfo>
</distrib>
<resdesc>ROCR Veg Map</resdesc>
<distliab>
Although these data have been processed
successfully on a computer system at the U.S.
Geological Survey, no warranty expressed or
implied is made regarding the accuracy or utility
of the data on any other system or for general or
scientific purposes, nor shall the act of
distribution constitute any such warranty. This
disclaimer applies both to individual use of the
data and aggregate use with other data.  It is
strongly recommended that these data are directly
acquired from a U.S. Geological Survey server, and
not indirectly through other sources which may
have changed the data in some way.  It is also
strongly recommended that careful attention be
paid to the contents of the metadata file
associated with these data.  The U.S. Geological
Survey shall not be held liable for improper or
incorrect use of the data described and/or
contained herein.
</distliab>
<stdorder>
<digform>
<digtinfo>
<formname>HTML</formname>
</digtinfo>
<digtopt>
<onlinopt>
<computer>
<networka>
<networkr>http://biology.usgs.gov/npsveg/rocr/fielddata.html</networkr>
</networka>
</computer>
</onlinopt>
</digtopt>
</digform>
<fees>None</fees>
</stdorder>
</distinfo>
<metainfo>
<metd>200102</metd>
<metrd>20050517</metrd>
<metc>
<cntinfo>
<cntorgp>
<cntorg>USGS-NPS Vegetation Mapping Program Coordinator</cntorg>
</cntorgp>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
<address>
U.S. Geological Survey, Center for Biological Informatics, MS 302,
Room 8000, Building 810, Denver Federal Center
</address>
<city>Denver</city>
<state>Colorado</state>
<postal>80225</postal>
<country>USA</country>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>(303) 202-4220</cntvoice>
<cntfax>(303) 202-4219</cntfax>
<cntemail>gs-b-npsveg@usgs.gov</cntemail>
</cntinfo>
</metc>
<metstdn>FGDC-STD-001.1-1999 Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata, 1998 Part 1: Biological Data Profile, 1999</metstdn>
<metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
<metextns>
<onlink>http://biology.usgs.gov/fgdc.bio/bionwext.txt</onlink>
<metprof>Biological Data Profile FGDC-STD-001.1-1999</metprof>
</metextns>
</metainfo>
<mercury><begdate>19961029</begdate><enddate>19961029</enddate><htmlurl>http://mercury.ornl.gov/metadata/nbii/html/nbii/www.nbii.gov_metadata_mdata_CBI_usgs_brd_cbi_d_rocrfield.html</htmlurl><LTER-Site>nbii</LTER-Site></mercury></metadata>
