<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<metadata><Source>http://www.nbii.gov/metadata/mdata/ECTI/ecti_d_dutchplants.sgml</Source>
<idinfo>
<citation>
<citeinfo>
<origin>F.G. Wortelboer</origin>
<pubdate>Unknown</pubdate>
<title>Plant Name Checklist</title>
<edition>Version 1.1</edition>
<geoform>maps data</geoform>
<pubinfo>
<pubplace>Amsterdam, Netherlands</pubplace>
<publish>Expert Center for Taxonomic Identification</publish>
</pubinfo>
<othercit>ISBN: Win: 90-75000-16-2</othercit>
</citeinfo>
</citation>
<descript>
<abstract>This Dutch CD ROM contains a unique and useable database of more than 130,000 plant names. Plant names change continuously because of continuing  investigation and classification. Often separate names (scientific, general, old and new) are used for the same plant. Therefore confusion can occur when using supply lists and garden literature. Searching and maintaining the correct contemporary names is time consuming and elaborate. The Checklist Plantnames CD ROM offers a simple solution because the old and new names of a great number of garden and wild plants are  arranged in an orderly way.  This CD ROM has compiled names from over a 150 different sources: Flora's standardized lists, international registries, encyclopedias, and garden books. Special attention has been given to names useing the English literature.  The author has been provided with all the latin names. For all other information, the source is mentioned. The user friendly program on this CD ROM offers extensive possibilities for searching and selecting names or parts of names. This CD ROM contains: over 80,000 latin names of types, cultivates etc, over 30,000 synomyms and spelling changes, over 15,000 English names, over 5,000 Dutch names, over 2,500 species, over 300 families. Additional information can be found on the Plantago Software web page.</abstract>
<purpose>The purpose of this CD ROM is to provide information about more than 130,000 plant names.</purpose>
<supplinf>This information was obtained from the ETI web site - http://www.eti.uva.nl/Products/CD-catalogue.html.  (previous geoform was 'CD ROM database')</supplinf>
</descript>
<timeperd>
<timeinfo>
<sngdate>
<caldate>Unknown</caldate>
</sngdate>
</timeinfo>
<current>publication date</current>
</timeperd>
<status>
<progress>Complete</progress>
<update>Unknown</update>
</status>
<spdom>
<descgeog>world</descgeog>
<bounding>
<westbc>-180</westbc>
<eastbc>180</eastbc>
<northbc>90</northbc>
<southbc>-90</southbc>
</bounding>
</spdom>
<keywords>
<theme>
<themekt>none</themekt>
<themekey>taxonomy</themekey>
<themekey>database</themekey>
<themekey>plant names</themekey>
<themekey>ecology</themekey>
<themekey>distribution</themekey>
<themekey>Plantago software</themekey>
</theme>
<place>
<placekt>none</placekt>
<placekey>world</placekey>
</place>
</keywords>
<taxonomy>
<keywtax>
<taxonkt>none</taxonkt>
<taxonkey>Plant</taxonkey>
</keywtax>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Kingdom</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Plant</taxonrv>
</taxoncl>
</taxonomy>
<accconst>none</accconst>
<useconst>none</useconst>
<ptcontac>
<cntinfo>
<cntorgp>
<cntorg>Expert Center for Taxonomic Identification</cntorg>
<cntper>Webmaster</cntper>
</cntorgp>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
<address>P.O. Box 94766, Mauritskade 61</address>
<city>Amsterdam</city>
<postal>NL-1090 GT</postal>
<country>Netherlands</country>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>+31-20-5257239</cntvoice>
<cntfax>+31-20-5257238</cntfax>
<cntemail>webmaster@eti.uva.nl</cntemail>
<cntinst>info@eti.uva.nl - general information about ETI. Phone and fax numbers are for general information.  Email adress webmaster@eti.uva.nl may know the most about the online World Biodiversity database.</cntinst>
</cntinfo>
</ptcontac>
</idinfo>
<dataqual>
<logic>not applicable</logic>
<complete>This CD ROM has compiled names from over a 150 different sources: Flora's standardized lists, international registries, encyclopedias, and garden books. This CD ROM contains over 80,000 latin names,  over 30,000 synomyms and spelling changes, over 15,000 English names, over 5,000 Dutch names, over 2,500 species, over 300 families. Additional information can be found on the Plantago Software web page.</complete>
<lineage>
<procstep>
<procdesc>not applicable</procdesc>
<procdate>not applicable</procdate>
</procstep>
</lineage>
</dataqual>
<eainfo>
<overview>
<eaover>Entity - Plant Names; Attributes - latin names, English names</eaover>
<eadetcit>unknown</eadetcit>
</overview>
</eainfo>
<distinfo>
<distrib>
<cntinfo>
<cntorgp>
<cntorg>Expert Center for Taxonomic Identification</cntorg>
<cntper>Webmaster</cntper>
</cntorgp>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
<address>P.O. Box 94766, Mauritskade 61</address>
<city>Amsterdam</city>
<postal>NL-1090 GT</postal>
<country>Netherlands</country>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>+31-20-5257239</cntvoice>
<cntfax>+31-20-5257238</cntfax>
<cntemail>webmaster@eti.uva.nl</cntemail>
<cntinst>info@eti.uva.nl - general information about ETI. Phone and fax numbers are for general information.  Email adress webmaster@eti.uva.nl may know the most about the online World Biodiversity database.</cntinst>
</cntinfo>
</distrib>
<distliab>ETI is committed to updating its CD-ROM publications in the above mentioned series, including adapting them to hardware configurations and computer operating systems to come (meaning that they will be replaced by new versions when big changes occur). All users of ETI CD-ROM products and the Linnaeus II software can ask for support at our	by a helpdesk [support@eti.uva.nl]. We will do our very best to help you with any questions that may arise.</distliab>
<stdorder>
<fees>$30.32</fees>
<ordering>The Checklist Plantennamen CD-ROM can be ordered at your local bookshop, and the following distributor(s): ETI, Mauritskade 61, 1092AD Amsterdam, Nederland ETI-partners may order directly at ETI as they receive a discount on the retail prices of all CD's. The Linnaeus II software for Biodiversity Documentation can be purchased only at ETI.</ordering>
</stdorder>
<techpreq>Windows:  Windows 95/98/NT, Pentium CPU, 32MB RAM, Thousands of colors, 8x speed CD-ROM or higher.  Macintosh: Not available.</techpreq>
</distinfo>
<metainfo>
<metd>20010831</metd>
<metfrd>20020831</metfrd>
<metc>
<cntinfo>
<cntperp>
<cntper>Cheryl Solomon</cntper>
<cntorg>Science Systems and Applications, Inc.</cntorg>
</cntperp>
<cntpos>Metadata specialist</cntpos>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
<address>10210 Greenbelt Road, Suite 500</address>
<city>Lanham</city>
<state>Maryland</state>
<postal>20706</postal>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>301 867-2080</cntvoice>
<cntfax>301-867-2149.</cntfax>
<cntemail>solomon@gcmd.nasa.gov</cntemail>
</cntinfo>
</metc>
<metstdn>FGDC Biological Data Profile of the Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
<metstdv>FGDC-STD-001.1-1999</metstdv>
<metac>none</metac>
<metuc>none</metuc>
</metainfo>
<mercury><begdate>Unknown</begdate><enddate>Unknown</enddate><htmlurl>http://mercury.ornl.gov/metadata/nbii/html/nbii/www.nbii.gov_metadata_mdata_ECTI_ecti_d_dutchplants.html</htmlurl><LTER-Site>nbii</LTER-Site></mercury></metadata>
