<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<metadata><Source>http://www.nbii.gov/metadata/mdata/brd-bib/usgs_brd_fresc_b_salmonberry.sgml</Source>
<idinfo>
<citation>
<citeinfo>
<origin>John C. Tappeiner II, John C. Zasada, David W. Huffman, and Lisa M. Ganio</origin>
<pubdate>2001</pubdate>
<title>Salmonberry and salal annual aerial stem production: the maintenance of shrub cover in forest stands</title>
<geoform>Journal article</geoform>
<serinfo>
<sername>Canadian Journal of Forest Research</sername>
<issue>31:1629-1638</issue>
</serinfo>
<othercit>Publication Control #: 1045</othercit>
</citeinfo>
</citation>
<descript>
<abstract>Dense shrub populations can influence the potential for trees and other plants to establish and grow by affecting the availability of light, soil water, and other resources. The ability of forest shrubs to maintain a dense stable cover, once they are established, has important implications for the development, structure, and species composition of forest stands. However, little work has been done to document how this cover is maintained. A recently retired FRESC scientist co-authored a publication in which the vegetative stem production of salmonberry and salal (two common clonal shrubs in Oregon) were monitored for eight years and five years, respectively. The results show that both salmonberry and salal maintained stem density by annual production of new aerial stems on rhizomes and at the base of older aerial stems. Not many of the stems that were produced survived.  However, enough survived to replace old, large stems that died, and thus maintain the shrub cover. Annual stem production occurred in thinned and unthinned stands, in hardwoods, and in stands in both riparian and upland sites. Similar to other studies, no tree regeneration was observed in plots under either salmonberry or salal.  Sprouting ability may be reduced if overstory tree density is high or if trees can become established immediately following a treatment and quickly overtop the shrubs.</abstract>
<purpose>Reporting research results</purpose>
<supplinf>
Extent of item: 9pp
Illustrative Matter:  tables, graphs
</supplinf>
</descript>
<timeperd>
<timeinfo>
<sngdate>
<caldate>2001</caldate>
</sngdate>
</timeinfo>
<current>publication date</current>
</timeperd>
<status>
<progress>Complete</progress>
<update>None planned</update>
</status>
<spdom>
<descgeog>Oregon Coast Range</descgeog>
<bounding>
<westbc>-124</westbc>
<eastbc>-123.5</eastbc>
<northbc>45.1</northbc>
<southbc>44.5</southbc>
</bounding>
</spdom>
<keywords>
<theme>
<themekt>None</themekt>
<themekey>cover</themekey>
<themekey>stem production</themekey>
<themekey>establishment</themekey>
</theme>
<theme>
<themekt>Science Information System Controlled Vocabulary</themekt>
<themekey>Plants</themekey>
<themekey>Forests</themekey>
<themekey>Ecosystem Science</themekey>
<themekey>Terrestrial</themekey>
</theme>
<place>
<placekt>none</placekt>
<placekey>Oregon</placekey>
<placekey>Coast Range</placekey>
<placekey>OR</placekey>
</place>
</keywords>
<taxonomy>
<keywtax>
<taxonkt>none</taxonkt>
<taxonkey>salal</taxonkey>
<taxonkey>salmonberry</taxonkey>
<taxonkey>plants</taxonkey>
</keywtax>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Kingdom</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Plantae</taxonrv>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Division</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Magnoliophyta</taxonrv>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Class</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Magnoliopsida</taxonrv>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Sub Class</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Rosidae</taxonrv>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Order</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Rosales</taxonrv>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Family</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Rosaceae</taxonrv>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Genus</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Rubus</taxonrv>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Species</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Rubus spectabilis</taxonrv>
<common>salmonberry</common>
</taxoncl>
</taxoncl>
</taxoncl>
</taxoncl>
</taxoncl>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Sub Class</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Dilleniidae</taxonrv>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Order</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Ericales</taxonrv>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Family</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Ericaceae</taxonrv>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Genus</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Gaultheria</taxonrv>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Species</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Gaultheria shallon</taxonrv>
<common>salal</common>
</taxoncl>
</taxoncl>
</taxoncl>
</taxoncl>
</taxoncl>
</taxoncl>
</taxoncl>
</taxoncl>
</taxonomy>
<accconst>None</accconst>
<useconst>None</useconst>
<ptcontac>
<cntinfo>
<cntperp>
<cntper>Tappeiner II, John C.</cntper>
<cntorg>USGS Forest and Rangeland Ecosystem Science Center</cntorg>
</cntperp>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
<address>
777 NW 9th St.
Suite 100
</address>
<city>Corvallis</city>
<state>OR</state>
<postal>97330</postal>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>541-750-1030</cntvoice>
<cntemail>john.tappeiner@orst.edu</cntemail>
</cntinfo>
</ptcontac>
</idinfo>
<distinfo>
<distrib>
<cntinfo>
<cntorgp>
<cntorg>Olendorff Library</cntorg>
</cntorgp>
<cntpos>Librarian</cntpos>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
<address>
USGS FRESC Snake River Field Station
970 Lusk Street
</address>
<city>Boise</city>
<state>ID</state>
<postal>83706</postal>
<country>USA</country>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>208 426-5218</cntvoice>
<cntfax>208 426-5210</cntfax>
</cntinfo>
</distrib>
<resdesc>Publication Control #: 1045</resdesc>
<distliab>
The USGS Forest and Rangeland Ecosystem Science Center and its research partners make every effort to provide and maintain accurate, complete, usable, and timely information. However, some USGS data and information may, of necessity, be preliminary in nature. These data and information are provided with the understanding that they are not guaranteed to be correct or complete. Users are cautioned to consider carefully the provisional nature of these data and information before using them for decisions that concern personal or public safety or the conduct of business that involves substantial monetary or operational consequences. It is also strongly recommended that careful attention be paid to the contents of the metadata file associated with these data and information. Conclusions drawn from, or actions undertaken on the basis of, such data and information are the sole responsibility of the user.
USGS-authored or produced data and information are in the public domain. Whereas the content of many USGS publications and other information resources are in the public domain, some USGS products contain material that is copyrighted by others and used by the USGS with permission. Users of this information may need to obtain permission from the copyright owner for other uses. Furthermore, some non-USGS data, products, and information referred to may be protected under U.S. and foreign copyright laws. Users may need to obtain permission from the copyright owner to acquire, use, reproduce, or distribute these materials. It is the sole responsibility of the user of the information to secure all necessary permission.
</distliab>
<stdorder>
<nondig>Publications are available as reprints, reports, pamphlets, or brochures.</nondig>
<fees>None</fees>
<ordering>Request specific publications by reference number.</ordering>
</stdorder>
</distinfo>
<metainfo>
<metd>20011119</metd>
<metrd>20011126</metrd>
<metc>
<cntinfo>
<cntorgp>
<cntorg>USGS Forest and Rangeland Ecosystem Science Center (FRESC)</cntorg>
</cntorgp>
<cntpos>Library</cntpos>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
<address>
777 NW 9th St.
Suite 100
</address>
<city>Corvallis</city>
<state>OR</state>
<postal>97330</postal>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>541-750-1030</cntvoice>
<cntfax>541-750-1069</cntfax>
<cntemail>fresc_outreach@usgs.gov</cntemail>
</cntinfo>
</metc>
<metstdn>FGDC Biological Data Profile of the Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
<metstdv>FGDC-STD-001.1-1999</metstdv>
</metainfo>
<mercury><begdate>20010101</begdate><enddate>20011231</enddate><htmlurl>http://mercury.ornl.gov/metadata/nbii/html/brd/www.nbii.gov_metadata_mdata_brd-bib_usgs_brd_fresc_b_salmonberry.html</htmlurl><LTER-Site>brd</LTER-Site></mercury></metadata>
