<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<metadata><Source>http://www.nbii.gov/metadata/mdata/brd-bib/usgs_brd_fresc_b_desertinvasive.sgml</Source>
<idinfo>
<citation>
<citeinfo>
<origin>Mathew L. Brooks and David A. Pyke</origin>
<pubdate>2001</pubdate>
<title>Invasive plants and fire in the deserts of North America</title>
<geoform>Journal article</geoform>
<serinfo>
<sername>Tall Timbers Research Station Miscellaneous Publications</sername>
<issue>No. 11</issue>
</serinfo>
<othercit>
Science Information System Project #: 70131
Publication Control #: 1078
</othercit>
<lworkcit>
<citeinfo>
<origin>Galley, Krista, and Tyrone Wilson</origin>
<pubdate>2001</pubdate>
<title>Proceedings of the invasive species workshop: the role of fire in the control and spread of invasive species</title>
<geoform>Proceedings volume</geoform>
<pubinfo>
<pubplace>Tallahassee, FL</pubplace>
<publish>Tall Timbers Research Station</publish>
</pubinfo>
</citeinfo>
</lworkcit>
</citeinfo>
</citation>
<descript>
<abstract>The invasion of non-native plants, in combination with changes in the natural fire regime, is creating considerable challenges for land managers in the deserts of North America. Scientists discuss the relationship between invasive plants and fire in the changing deserts of North America. In portions of the Great Basin, Mojave, and Sonoran Deserts, native shrublands have been converted to grasslands full of non-native invasive species due to increased fire frequency. The invasive species create more fuel and help to perpetuate more frequent fires. Contrarily, lack of fire, climate changes, and historical overgrazing of livestock have allowed native woody shrubs to invade areas that have historically been perennial grasslands in the Chihuahuan Desert, and also allowed native trees to invade sagebrush steppe ecosystems in the Great Basin. Fire can be used to either control invasive species or to restore historical fire regimes, however, the potential for fire to promote the spread of invasive plants must be considered before fire is implemented as a management tool.</abstract>
<purpose>Reporting research results</purpose>
<supplinf>
Extent of item: 14pp
Illustrative Matter:  maps charts
</supplinf>
</descript>
<timeperd>
<timeinfo>
<sngdate>
<caldate>2001</caldate>
</sngdate>
</timeinfo>
<current>publication date</current>
</timeperd>
<status>
<progress>Complete</progress>
<update>None planned</update>
</status>
<spdom>
<descgeog>Great Basin, Mojave, and Sonoran deserts of North America</descgeog>
<bounding>
<westbc>-121</westbc>
<eastbc>-109</eastbc>
<northbc>44</northbc>
<southbc>25</southbc>
</bounding>
</spdom>
<keywords>
<theme>
<themekt>Science Information System Controlled Vocabulary</themekt>
<themekey>Monitoring</themekey>
</theme>
<theme>
<themekt>None</themekt>
<themekey>fire</themekey>
<themekey>invasive species</themekey>
</theme>
<place>
<placekt>None</placekt>
<placekey>Mojave Desert</placekey>
<placekey>Sonoran Desert</placekey>
<placekey>Great Basin</placekey>
<placekey>United States of America</placekey>
<placekey>USA</placekey>
<placekey>Mexico</placekey>
</place>
</keywords>
<accconst>None</accconst>
<useconst>None</useconst>
<ptcontac>
<cntinfo>
<cntperp>
<cntper>Pyke, David</cntper>
<cntorg>USGS Forest and Rangeland Ecosystem Science Center</cntorg>
</cntperp>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
<address>3200 SW Jefferson Way</address>
<city>Corvallis</city>
<state>OR</state>
<postal>97331</postal>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>541/750/7334</cntvoice>
<cntemail>david_a_pyke@usgs.gov</cntemail>
</cntinfo>
</ptcontac>
</idinfo>
<distinfo>
<distrib>
<cntinfo>
<cntorgp>
<cntorg>Olendorff Library</cntorg>
</cntorgp>
<cntpos>Librarian</cntpos>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
<address>
USGS FRESC Snake River Field Station
970 Lusk Street
</address>
<city>Boise</city>
<state>ID</state>
<postal>83706</postal>
<country>USA</country>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>208 426-5218</cntvoice>
<cntfax>208 426-5210</cntfax>
</cntinfo>
</distrib>
<resdesc>Publication Control #: 1078</resdesc>
<distliab>
The USGS Forest and Rangeland Ecosystem Science Center and its research partners make every effort to provide and maintain accurate, complete, usable, and timely information. However, some USGS data and information may, of necessity, be preliminary in nature. These data and information are provided with the understanding that they are not guaranteed to be correct or complete. Users are cautioned to consider carefully the provisional nature of these data and information before using them for decisions that concern personal or public safety or the conduct of business that involves substantial monetary or operational consequences. It is also strongly recommended that careful attention be paid to the contents of the metadata file associated with these data and information. Conclusions drawn from, or actions undertaken on the basis of, such data and information are the sole responsibility of the user.
USGS-authored or produced data and information are in the public domain. Whereas the content of many USGS publications and other information resources are in the public domain, some USGS products contain material that is copyrighted by others and used by the USGS with permission. Users of this information may need to obtain permission from the copyright owner for other uses. Furthermore, some non-USGS data, products, and information referred to may be protected under U.S. and foreign copyright laws. Users may need to obtain permission from the copyright owner to acquire, use, reproduce, or distribute these materials. It is the sole responsibility of the user of the information to secure all necessary permission.
</distliab>
<stdorder>
<nondig>Publications are available as reprints, reports, pamphlets, or brochures.</nondig>
<fees>None</fees>
<ordering>Request specific publications by reference number.</ordering>
</stdorder>
</distinfo>
<metainfo>
<metd>20020520</metd>
<metc>
<cntinfo>
<cntorgp>
<cntorg>Olendorff Library</cntorg>
</cntorgp>
<cntpos>Librarian</cntpos>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
<address>
USGS FRESC Snake River Field Station
970 Lusk Street
</address>
<city>Boise</city>
<state>ID</state>
<postal>83706</postal>
<country>USA</country>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>208 426-5218</cntvoice>
<cntfax>208 426-5210</cntfax>
</cntinfo>
</metc>
<metstdn>FGDC Biological Data Profile of the Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
<metstdv>FGDC-STD-001.1-1999</metstdv>
</metainfo>
<mercury><begdate>20010101</begdate><enddate>20011231</enddate><htmlurl>http://mercury.ornl.gov/metadata/nbii/html/brd/www.nbii.gov_metadata_mdata_brd-bib_usgs_brd_fresc_b_desertinvasive.html</htmlurl><LTER-Site>brd</LTER-Site></mercury></metadata>
