<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<metadata><Source>http://www.nbii.gov/metadata/mdata/brd-bib/usgs_brd_fresc_b_pub1096.sgml</Source>
<idinfo>
<citation>
<citeinfo>
<origin>Miller, Rick, Chris Baisan, Jeff Rose, and Dave Pacioretty</origin>
<pubdate>2001</pubdate>
<title>Pre- and post-settlement fire regimes in mountain big sagebrush steppe and aspen: the northwestern Great Basin</title>
<geoform>technical report</geoform>
<pubinfo>
<pubplace>Burns, OR</pubplace>
<publish>Eastern Oregon Agricultural Research Center, Oregon State University</publish>
</pubinfo>
<othercit>
Science Information System Project #: 7088
Publication Control #: 1096
</othercit>
</citeinfo>
</citation>
<descript>
<abstract>Fire is an important disturbance in sagebrush steppe ecosystems, influencing plant dynamics, composition, and structure. The balance between woody and herbaceous species in sagebrush steppe communities strongly depends on the amount of time between fires. This time interval has increased considerably since Eurasian settlement in the late 1800s. As a result, pinyon-juniper woodlands and the density and cover of shrubs in the more mesic sagebrush steppe communities of the northwestern Great Basin have significantly increased. Many private landowners and public land managers are interested in restoring fire as a way to improve range health, livestock grazing conditions, and wildlife habitat. Unfortunately, most fire-management and restoration programs are based on little or no historical information about pre-settlement fire regimes. This report describes the pre- and post-settlement fire regimes for the mountain big sagebrush steppe and aspen-dominated ecosystems in the northwestern portion of the Great Basin. The results indicate that fires burned approximately every 10-20 years pre-settlement. This compares to present conditions, where many sites have not burned in the last 100 years and only a few burned 50 years ago. The authors suggest that information on pre-settlement fire regimes and the impacts of altered fire regimes on ecosystem structure and composition is important in developing and supporting effective prescribe fire programs.</abstract>
<purpose>Reporting research results</purpose>
<supplinf>
Extent of item: 28pp
Illustrative Matter::  tables, maps, charts
</supplinf>
</descript>
<timeperd>
<timeinfo>
<sngdate>
<caldate>2001</caldate>
</sngdate>
</timeinfo>
<current>publication date</current>
</timeperd>
<status>
<progress>Complete</progress>
<update>None planned</update>
</status>
<spdom>
<descgeog>Northwestern Great Basin in southeastern Oregon and southern Idaho</descgeog>
<bounding>
<westbc>-120</westbc>
<eastbc>-117</eastbc>
<northbc>44</northbc>
<southbc>41.5</southbc>
</bounding>
</spdom>
<keywords>
<theme>
<themekt>NBII Biocomplexity Thesaurus</themekt>
<themekey>Arid environments</themekey>
<themekey>Grasslands</themekey>
<themekey>Rangelands</themekey>
<themekey>Plants</themekey>
<themekey>Fires</themekey>
<themekey>Human impact</themekey>
</theme>
<place>
<placekt>none</placekt>
<placekey>Great Basin</placekey>
<placekey>Oregon</placekey>
<placekey>OR</placekey>
<placekey>Idaho</placekey>
<placekey>ID</placekey>
<placekey>United States</placekey>
<placekey>USA</placekey>
</place>
</keywords>
<accconst>None</accconst>
<useconst>None</useconst>
<ptcontac>
<cntinfo>
<cntorgp>
<cntorg>Olendorff Library</cntorg>
</cntorgp>
<cntpos>Librarian</cntpos>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
<address>
USGS FRESC Snake River Field Station
970 Lusk Street
</address>
<city>Boise</city>
<state>ID</state>
<postal>83706</postal>
<country>USA</country>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>208 426-5218</cntvoice>
<cntfax>208 426-5210</cntfax>
<cntemail>fresc_outreach@usgs.gov</cntemail>
</cntinfo>
</ptcontac>
</idinfo>
<distinfo>
<distrib>
<cntinfo>
<cntorgp>
<cntorg>Olendorff Library</cntorg>
</cntorgp>
<cntpos>Librarian</cntpos>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
<address>
USGS FRESC Snake River Field Station
970 Lusk Street
</address>
<city>Boise</city>
<state>ID</state>
<postal>83706</postal>
<country>USA</country>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>208 426-5218</cntvoice>
<cntfax>208 426-5210</cntfax>
<cntemail>fresc_outreach@usgs.gov</cntemail>
</cntinfo>
</distrib>
<resdesc>Publication Control #: 1096</resdesc>
<distliab>
The USGS Forest and Rangeland Ecosystem Science Center and its research partners make every effort to provide and maintain accurate, complete, usable, and timely information. However, some USGS data and information may, of necessity, be preliminary in nature. These data and information are provided with the understanding that they are not guaranteed to be correct or complete. Users are cautioned to consider carefully the provisional nature of these data and information before using them for decisions that concern personal or public safety or the conduct of business that involves substantial monetary or operational consequences. It is also strongly recommended that careful attention be paid to the contents of the metadata file associated with these data and information. Conclusions drawn from, or actions undertaken on the basis of, such data and information are the sole responsibility of the user.
USGS-authored or produced data and information are in the public domain. Whereas the content of many USGS publications and other information resources are in the public domain, some USGS products contain material that is copyrighted by others and used by the USGS with permission. Users of this information may need to obtain permission from the copyright owner for other uses. Furthermore, some non-USGS data, products, and information referred to may be protected under U.S. and foreign copyright laws. Users may need to obtain permission from the copyright owner to acquire, use, reproduce, or distribute these materials. It is the sole responsibility of the user of the information to secure all necessary permission.
</distliab>
<stdorder>
<nondig>Publications are available as reprints, reports, pamphlets, or brochures.</nondig>
<fees>None</fees>
<ordering>Request specific publications by reference number.</ordering>
</stdorder>
</distinfo>
<metainfo>
<metd>20050325</metd>
<metc>
<cntinfo>
<cntorgp>
<cntorg>Olendorff Library</cntorg>
</cntorgp>
<cntpos>Librarian</cntpos>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
<address>
USGS FRESC Snake River Field Station
970 Lusk Street
</address>
<city>Boise</city>
<state>ID</state>
<postal>83706</postal>
<country>USA</country>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>208 426-5218</cntvoice>
<cntfax>208 426-5210</cntfax>
<cntemail>fresc_outreach@usgs.gov</cntemail>
</cntinfo>
</metc>
<metstdn>FGDC Biological Data Profile of the Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
<metstdv>FGDC-STD-001.1-1999</metstdv>
</metainfo>
<mercury><begdate>20010101</begdate><enddate>20011231</enddate><htmlurl>http://mercury.ornl.gov/metadata/nbii/html/brd/www.nbii.gov_metadata_mdata_brd-bib_usgs_brd_fresc_b_pub1096.html</htmlurl><LTER-Site>brd</LTER-Site></mercury></metadata>
