<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<metadata><Source>http://www.nbii.gov/metadata/mdata/CBI/usgs_brd_cbi_d_moruattribacc.sgml</Source>
<idinfo>
<citation>
<citeinfo>
<origin>U.S. Geological Survey</origin>
<origin>Department of the Interior</origin>
<pubdate>199810</pubdate>
<title>Mount Rushmore National Memorial Accuracy Assessment</title>
<geoform>maps data</geoform>
<serinfo>
<sername>USGS-NPS Vegetation Mapping Program</sername>
<issue>Mount Rushmore National Memorial</issue>
</serinfo>
<pubinfo>
<pubplace>Denver, CO</pubplace>
<publish>
USGS Biological Resources Division, Center for
Biological Informatics
</publish>
</pubinfo>
<onlink>http://biology.usgs.gov/npsveg/moru/pi_rpt.pdf#assessment</onlink>
<onlink>http://biology.usgs.gov/npsveg/moru/images/moruaa.gif</onlink>
<onlink>http://biology.usgs.gov/npsveg/ftp/vegmapping/moru/moruaa.exe</onlink>
<onlink>http://biology.usgs.gov/npsveg/ftp/vegmapping/moru/moruaasdts.exe</onlink>
<onlink>http://biology.usgs.gov/npsveg/moru/aa_matrix.pdf</onlink>
<onlink>http://biology.usgs.gov/npsveg/ftp/vegmapping/moru/aa_matrix.xls</onlink>
<lworkcit>
<citeinfo>
<origin>US Dept of Interior</origin>
<origin>
National Biological Survey (aka National Biological
Service)
</origin>
<origin>[Now the Biological Resources Division of USGS]</origin>
<origin>and National Park Service</origin>
<pubdate>199411</pubdate>
<title>Field Assessment Procedures</title>
<geoform>document</geoform>
<edition>Final Draft</edition>
<pubinfo>
<pubplace>Denver, CO</pubplace>
<publish>USGS/BRD/Center for Biological Informatics</publish>
</pubinfo>
<othercit>
Report prepared by the USGS Center for Biological
Informatics in cooperation with Environmental
Systems Research Institute, 380 New York Street,
Redlands, CA.
</othercit>
<onlink>http://biology.usgs.gov/npsveg/moru/pi_rpt.pdf#assessment</onlink>
</citeinfo>
</lworkcit>
</citeinfo>
</citation>
<descript>
<abstract>
The accuracy assessment field work was performed in July and August,
1996 to verify the accuracy of the vegetation communities spatial data
developed by the USGS-NPS Vegetation Mapping Program for Mount Rushmore
National Memorial.  The data points were randomly distributed
stratified according to vegetation association over the project area
according to protocols developed by the Program. Points were located by
GPS navigation and the community information was collected at the point,
without knowledge of the attributes of the vegetation spatial data. The
data points were compared to the attributes of the polygon in which
they were contained.  Attributes of the polygons or accuracy assessment
points that did not match were changed during later analysis due to
errors in the AA methodology or map attribution errors.  A contingency
table was completed from the final dataset.
</abstract>
<purpose>
These data were necessary assess the mapping effort in addition to meeting
the requirements of the mapping program.
</purpose>
<supplinf>
All codes used in the digital file are referenced by the look-up table that
accompanies this file. The look-up table is called veg.lut. It contains both
the common name and latin names of the vegetation types.
(previous geoform was 'database and report')</supplinf>
</descript>
<timeperd>
<timeinfo>
<rngdates>
<begdate>199607</begdate>
<enddate>199608</enddate>
</rngdates>
</timeinfo>
<current>Ground Condition</current>
</timeperd>
<status>
<progress>Complete</progress>
<update>None planned</update>
</status>
<spdom>
<bounding>
<westbc>-103.5</westbc>
<eastbc>-103.38</eastbc>
<northbc>43.9</northbc>
<southbc>43.8</southbc>
</bounding>
<descgeog>Mount Rushmore National Memorial - Black Hills, South Dakota, USA</descgeog>
</spdom>
<keywords>
<theme>
<themekt>none</themekt>
<themekey>National Park Service</themekey>
<themekey>U.S. Geological Service</themekey>
<themekey>Center for Biological Informatics</themekey>
<themekey>land cover</themekey>
<themekey>vegetation</themekey>
<themekey>alliance</themekey>
<themekey>association</themekey>
</theme>
<place>
<placekt>None</placekt>
<placekey>Mount Rushmore National Memorial</placekey>
<placekey>Black Hills</placekey>
<placekey>South Dakota</placekey>
<placekey>USA</placekey>
</place>
</keywords>
<taxonomy>
<keywtax>
<taxonkt>None</taxonkt>
<taxonkey>vegetation classification</taxonkey>
<taxonkey>Standardized National Vegetation Classification System</taxonkey>
<taxonkey>alliance</taxonkey>
<taxonkey>community association</taxonkey>
<taxonkey>Plant Communities</taxonkey>
</keywtax>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Kingdom</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Plantae</taxonrv>
<common>plants</common>
</taxoncl>
</taxonomy>
<accconst>None</accconst>
<useconst>
Any person using the information presented here should fully understand
the data collection and compilation procedures, as described in these
metadata, before beginning analysis.  The burden for determining fitness
for use lies entirely with the user.  For purposes of publication or
dissemination, citations should be given to the U.S. Geological Survey
and the National Park Service.
</useconst>
<ptcontac>
<cntinfo>
<cntorgp>
<cntper>USGS-NPS Vegetation Mapping Program Coordinator</cntper>
<cntorg>
USGS Biological Resources Division, Center for Biological
Informatics
</cntorg>
</cntorgp>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>Physical Address</addrtype>
<address>USGS</address>
<address>Biological Resources Division, CBI</address>
<address>Building 810, Room 8000</address>
<city>Denver</city>
<state>Colorado</state>
<postal>80225-0046</postal>
<country>USA</country>
</cntaddr>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>Mailing Address</addrtype>
<address>USGS</address>
<address>Biological Resources Division, CBI</address>
<address>PO BOX 25046, DFC, MS302</address>
<city>Denver</city>
<state>Colorado</state>
<postal>80225-0046</postal>
<country>USA</country>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>(303) 202-4220</cntvoice>
<cntfax>303-202-4229</cntfax>
<cntfax>303-202-4219 (org)</cntfax>
<cntemail>gs-b-npsveg@usgs.gov</cntemail>
</cntinfo>
</ptcontac>
<browse>
<browsen>http://biology.usgs.gov/npsveg/moru/images/moruaa.gif</browsen>
<browsed>
255 kbyte file showing vegetation associations and location of
accuracy assessment points
</browsed>
<browset>GIF</browset>
</browse>
<native>UNIX-ARC\INFO</native>
</idinfo>
<dataqual>
<attracc>
<attraccr>
The attributes for the accuracy assessment were recorded in the field
in July and August, 1996. Vegetation associations were identified based
on the field key and plant identification.  If additional communities were
found within a 50 meter radius of the plot center, they were recorded
as well. During the analysis, it was concluded that some attributes
were in error and changed to match the mapped attributes. This was done
by examination of the aerial photographs under stereoscopic view. The
attributes were in error due to 1) spatial error in the GPS derived
coordinates (4-8 meters), 2) change of vegetation community due
to temporal changes, or mis-identification of the community on the ground.
</attraccr>
</attracc>
<logic>
All attributes are codes that correspond to
vegetation communities and have been checked for
typographical and logical errors.
</logic>
<complete>All points were collected and analyzed.</complete>
<posacc>
<horizpa>
<horizpar>
The points were located using a military-style GPS receiver (PLGR),
which has a published accuracy of 4-8 meters.
</horizpar>
</horizpa>
<vertacc>
<vertaccr>Not applicable</vertaccr>
</vertacc>
</posacc>
<lineage>
<method>
<methtype>Field</methtype>
<methodid>
<methkt>None</methkt>
<methkey>Accuracy Assessment</methkey>
</methodid>
<methdesc>
To assess the thematic accuracy of the vegetation map we
conducted an accuracy assessment that allows the user of the
digital information an additional perspective upon the data.
The final product attempts to achieve the 80% per class
accuracy required for this product. Not all mapping units
were tested for accuracy. Since the final map contains two
separate classification systems, only the mapped areas that
fall under the NVCS were included in the accuracy assessment.
Areas such as agricultural and undescribed vegetation units
and other areas classified using Anderson Level II
classification were eliminated from the sample process.
Besides excluding the Anderson classified polygons we also
Excluded vegetation polygons visited and sampled during either
the vegetation description or verification phase that were
small enough to confidently say were entirely correct. These
were typically riparian polygons in Hell Canyon. These small
polygons were eliminated from a site visit in the random
selection process but were included in the final accuracy
assessment matrix. The remaining areas for sampling were then
stratified and sampled according to the number of polygons in
each class and the area occupied by each class. Field
Procedure: The field crew consisted of two botanists that were
Not involved in any part of the previous work on the park.
This crew either worked together or separately depending
upon local conditions. Both botanists were supplied with a list
of points to visit, a field key for map class identification,
field data forms, and a GPS to navigate to each site forms.
Both crew members worked "blind', meaning that neither one
was aware of the existing mapped class designations. Upon
arriving at each site, the crews scanned a wide area around
the immediate location and observed any local variation in
the plant associations. Using the key, the crew then assigned
a plant association to the accuracy point. In cases where the
variation was significant the crew made a "best fit" judgment
to the class name. In addition, other associations in the
area and those that might be confused with other plant
associations were also noted on each field form. Site
Selection: The stratified random selection of accuracy
assessment sites was done on the original map classes. The x
and y coordinates of each accuracy point were derived from
the original vegetation coverage. The coverage was gridded
into 50 x 50 meter cells using ArcGrid. A 50-meter grid was
chosen because it approximates the minimum mapping unit (MMU)
for the project. Using a random number generator, we then
re-selected the appropriate number of grids/samples from each
class and put them into a separate grid. Additional points
were selected for each class over the required number to
allow the field crew some latitude in case some sites were
inaccessible. The reselected cells where then converted into
a point coverage. The x and y coordinate for each point was
then transferred to an ASCII file. This coordinate file was
then used by the field team along with a GPS PLGR unit to
locate the position in the field. The point coverage with the
accuracy locations and the assigned map unit code are
included as a digital coverage. Data Analysis: Due to the
inherent heterogeneity of many natural systems, many of the
map class determinations to be incorrect. However, when
considered in the larger context were correct. To address
this issue we attempted to include a 'fuzzy' protocol in
analyzing the field accuracy data. For example, when the
field crew visited a site they noted not only the appropriate
vegetation association designation for the immediate area but
also other associations present. When field codes where then
compared with the mapped class the point was designated
correct if it agreed with any of the associations noted on
the field form.
</methdesc>
</method>
<srcinfo>
<srccite>
<citeinfo>
<origin>USGS-Biological Resources Division</origin>
<origin>U.S. National Park Service</origin>
<origin>Department of the Interior</origin>
<pubdate>199411</pubdate>
<title>Accuracy Assessment Procedures, NBS/NPS Vegetation Mapping Program</title>
<geoform>document</geoform>
<pubinfo>
<pubplace>Denver, CO</pubplace>
<publish>
USGS, Biological Resources Division, Center for
Biological Informatics
</publish>
</pubinfo>
<othercit>
Prepared by: Environmental Systems Research Institute; Redlands, CA
and National Center for Geographic Information and Analysis,
University of California, Santa Barbara, CA and The Nature Conservancy,
Arlington, VA under contract from U.S. Department of the Interior
Biological Resources Division and National Park Service.
</othercit>
</citeinfo>
</srccite>
<typesrc>electronic document</typesrc>
<srctime>
<timeinfo>
<rngdates>
<begdate>199411</begdate>
<enddate>Present</enddate>
</rngdates>
</timeinfo>
<srccurr>publication date</srccurr>
</srctime>
<srccitea>Accuracy Assessment Procedures Document</srccitea>
<srccontr>This document established the procedures and protocols for the accuracy assessment at Mount Rushmore National Memorial.</srccontr>
</srcinfo>
<srcinfo>
<srccite>
<citeinfo>
<origin>U.S. Geological Survey</origin>
<origin>Department of the Interior</origin>
<pubdate>199809</pubdate>
<title>
Mount Rushmore National Memorial Spatial
Vegetation Data: Cover type / Association
level of the National Vegetation Classification System
</title>
<geoform>document</geoform>
<serinfo>
<sername>USGS-NPS Vegetation Mapping Program</sername>
<issue>Mount Rushmore National Memorial</issue>
</serinfo>
<pubinfo>
<pubplace>Denver, CO</pubplace>
<publish>
USGS, Biological Resources Division, Center for
Biological Informatics
</publish>
</pubinfo>
<othercit>
Created in large part by Environmental Systems Research
Institute, Inc. Redlands, CA under contract from USGS/BRD/
CBI.
</othercit>
</citeinfo>
</srccite>
<typesrc>Disc</typesrc>
<srctime>
<timeinfo>
<sngdate>
<caldate>19950725</caldate>
</sngdate>
</timeinfo>
<srccurr>ground condition</srccurr>
</srctime>
<srccitea>
Spatial data of vegetation
communities for Mount Rushmore National Memorial.
</srccitea>
<srccontr>
The vegetation spatial data were tested for accuracy with the
AA data.
</srccontr>
</srcinfo>
<procstep>
<procdesc>
The accuracy assessment field work was performed
in July, 1995 to verify the accuracy of the
vegetation communities spatial data developed by
the USGS-NPS Vegetation Mapping Program for Mount
Rushmore National Memorial.  The data points were
randomly distributed stratified according to
vegetation association over the project area
according to protocols developed by the Program.
Points were located by GPS navigation and the
community information was collected at the point,
without knowledge of the attributes of the
vegetation spatial data.
</procdesc>
<srcused>Spatial data of vegetation communities for Mount Rushmore National Memorial.</srcused>
<srcused>Accuracy Assessment Procedure Document</srcused>
<procdate>199507</procdate>
</procstep>
</lineage>
</dataqual>
<spdoinfo>
<indspref>
Mount Rushmore National Memorial is in Pennington County and is part of the south
eastern Black Hills. The memorial shares its southwest boundary with the Norbeck
Wilderness Preserve. All other boundaries are shared with the Black Hills National
Forest.
</indspref>
<direct>Point</direct>
<ptvctinf>
<sdtsterm>
<sdtstype>Point</sdtstype>
</sdtsterm>
</ptvctinf>
</spdoinfo>
<spref>
<horizsys>
<planar>
<gridsys>
<gridsysn>Universal Transverse Mercator</gridsysn>
<utm>
<utmzone>13</utmzone>
<transmer>
<longcm>-105</longcm>
<latprjo>0</latprjo>
<feast>500000</feast>
<fnorth>0</fnorth>
<sfctrmer>.9996</sfctrmer>
</transmer>
</utm>
</gridsys>
<planci>
<plance>Coordinate Pair</plance>
<coordrep>
<absres>1</absres>
<ordres>1</ordres>
</coordrep>
<plandu>Meters</plandu>
</planci>
</planar>
<geodetic>
<horizdn>North American Datum of 1983</horizdn>
<ellips>Geodetic Reference System 80</ellips>
<semiaxis>6378137</semiaxis>
<denflat>297.257</denflat>
</geodetic>
</horizsys>
</spref>
<eainfo>
<overview>
<eaover>
The system is organized hierarchically to support conservation and
resource stewardship applications across multiple scales. The upper
levels of the hierarchy are based on the physical form or structure
of the vegetation (physiognomy) and have been refined from the
international standards developed by the United Nations Educational,
Scientific, and Cultural Organization (UNESCO).  The two most detailed
levels of the hierarchy are based on the species composition of the
existing vegetation (floristics) and reflect the phyto-sociological
standards that were originally developed by European ecologists. The
vegetation classification is continually advanced through the
collection and analysis of new field data and will be greatly
strengthened during the course of the NBS/NPS mapping efforts.
National Park Service/Biological Resources Division Vegetation
Inventory and Mapping Program for Mount Rushmore National Memorial,
South Dakota, Final Community Association Classification, May 1, 1998.
Alliance/Community  HB=Bur Oak / Ironwood Forest  PB=Ponderosa Pine
Bur Oak Woodland  PH=Paper Birch / Beaked Hazel Forest  PJ=Ponderosa
Pine / Common Juniper Woodland  PL=Ponderosa Pine / Little Bluestem
Woodland  PR=Ponderosa Pine / Rough Leafed Rice Grass Woodland  PW=
Ponderosa Pine / Bearberry Woodland  SS=Stream Side Shrubland
WM=Wooly Sedge / Blue Joint Herbaceous Vegetation (Wet Meadow).
</eaover>
<eadetcit>
Grossman, D. Et al. 1994. National Park Service / National Biological Service
Vegetation Mapping Project, National Vegetation Classification System 209 pp.
</eadetcit>
</overview>
</eainfo>
<distinfo>
<distrib>
<cntinfo>
<cntperp>
<cntper>USGS-NPS Vegetation Mapping Program Coordinator</cntper>
<cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, Center for Biological Informatics</cntorg>
</cntperp>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
<address>
U.S. Geological Survey, Center for Biological
Informatics, MS 302, Room 8000, Building 810,
Denver Federal Center
</address>
<city>Denver</city>
<state>Colorado</state>
<postal>80225</postal>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>(303) 202-4220</cntvoice>
<cntfax>303-202-4229</cntfax>
<cntfax>303-202-4219 (org)</cntfax>
<cntemail>gs-b-npsveg@usgs.gov</cntemail>
</cntinfo>
</distrib>
<distliab>
Although these data have been processed
successfully on a computer system at the
Biological Resources Division, no warranty
expressed or implied is made regarding the
accuracy or utility of the data on any other
system or for general or scientific purposes, nor
shall the act of distribution constitute any such
warranty. This disclaimer applies both to
individual use of the data and aggregate use with
other data.  It is strongly recommended that these
data are directly acquired from a Biological
Resources Division server, and not indirectly
through other sources which may have changed the
data in some way.  It is also strongly recommended
that careful attention be paid to the contents of
the metadata file associated with these data.  The
Biological Resources Division shall not be held
liable for improper or incorrect use of the data
described and/or contained herein.
</distliab>
<stdorder>
<digform>
<digtinfo>
<formname>PDF</formname>
</digtinfo>
<digtopt>
<onlinopt>
<computer>
<networka>
<networkr>http://biology.usgs.gov/npsveg/moru/pi_rpt.pdf#assessment</networkr>
</networka>
</computer>
</onlinopt>
</digtopt>
</digform>
<fees>None</fees>
</stdorder>
<stdorder>
<digform>
<digtinfo>
<formname>GIF</formname>
</digtinfo>
<digtopt>
<onlinopt>
<computer>
<networka>
<networkr>http://biology.usgs.gov/npsveg/moru/images/moruaa.gif</networkr>
</networka>
</computer>
</onlinopt>
</digtopt>
</digform>
<fees>None</fees>
</stdorder>
<stdorder>
<digform>
<digtinfo>
<formname>EXE</formname>
</digtinfo>
<digtopt>
<onlinopt>
<computer>
<networka>
<networkr>http://biology.usgs.gov/npsveg/ftp/vegmapping/moru/moruaa.exe</networkr>
</networka>
</computer>
</onlinopt>
</digtopt>
</digform>
<fees>None</fees>
</stdorder>
<stdorder>
<digform>
<digtinfo>
<formname>SDTS</formname>
</digtinfo>
<digtopt>
<onlinopt>
<computer>
<networka>
<networkr>http://biology.usgs.gov/npsveg/ftp/vegmapping/moru/moruaasdts.exe</networkr>
</networka>
</computer>
</onlinopt>
</digtopt>
</digform>
<fees>None</fees>
</stdorder>
<stdorder>
<digform>
<digtinfo>
<formname>PDF</formname>
</digtinfo>
<digtopt>
<onlinopt>
<computer>
<networka>
<networkr>http://biology.usgs.gov/npsveg/moru/aa_matrix.pdf</networkr>
</networka>
</computer>
</onlinopt>
</digtopt>
</digform>
<fees>None</fees>
</stdorder>
<stdorder>
<digform>
<digtinfo>
<formname>XLS</formname>
</digtinfo>
<digtopt>
<onlinopt>
<computer>
<networka>
<networkr>http://biology.usgs.gov/npsveg/ftp/vegmapping/moru/aa_matrix.xls</networkr>
</networka>
</computer>
</onlinopt>
</digtopt>
</digform>
<fees>None</fees>
</stdorder>
</distinfo>
<metainfo>
<metd>20011022</metd>
<metrd>20050513</metrd>
<metc>
<cntinfo>
<cntorgp>
<cntorg>USGS-NPS Vegetation Mapping Program Coordinator</cntorg>
</cntorgp>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
<address>
U.S. Geological Survey, Center for Biological Informatics, MS 302,
Room 8000, Building 810, Denver Federal Center
</address>
<city>Denver</city>
<state>Colorado</state>
<postal>80225</postal>
<country>USA</country>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>(303) 202-4220</cntvoice>
<cntfax>(303) 202-4219</cntfax>
<cntemail>gs-b-npsveg@usgs.gov</cntemail>
</cntinfo>
</metc>
<metstdn>FGDC-STD-001.1-1999 Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata, 1998 Part 1: Biological Data Profile, 1999</metstdn>
<metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
<metextns>
<onlink>http://biology.usgs.gov/fgdc.bio/bionwext.txt</onlink>
<metprof>Biological Data Profile FGDC-STD-001.1-1999</metprof>
</metextns>
</metainfo>
<mercury><begdate>19960701</begdate><enddate>19960831</enddate><htmlurl>http://mercury.ornl.gov/metadata/nbii/html/nbii/www.nbii.gov_metadata_mdata_CBI_usgs_brd_cbi_d_moruattribacc.html</htmlurl><LTER-Site>nbii</LTER-Site></mercury></metadata>
