<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<metadata><Source>http://www.nbii.gov/metadata/mdata/FAO/fao_d_hexacorallia.sgml</Source>
<idinfo>
<citation>
<citeinfo>
<origin>Daphne G. Fautin and Robert W. Buddemeier</origin>
<pubdate>2002</pubdate>
<title>Biogeoinformatics of Hexacorallia (corals, sea anemones, and their allies) interfacing geospatial, taxonomic, and environmental data for a group of marine invertebrates.</title>
<geoform>maps data</geoform>
<pubinfo>
<pubplace>Wichita, Kansas</pubplace>
<publish>Kansas Geological Survey</publish>
</pubinfo>
<othercit>Funded by the US National Science Foundation grant OCE 00-03970, with additional support from grants DEB95-21819, DEB 99-78106 (PEET - Partnerships to Enhance Expertise in Taxonomy -- program) and three supplements in the REU program (Research Experience for Undergraduates) to Daphne G. Fautin. Significant support for the environmental aspects has been provided by the Land Ocean Interactions in the Coastal Zone program, in part under contract with the United Nations Environment Programme (GEF).</othercit>
<onlink>http://www.kgs.ukans.edu/Hexacoral/Biodata/index.html</onlink>
</citeinfo>
</citation>
<descript>
<abstract>The Biogeoinformatics of Corals provides a public information resource of data, interpretation, and methods related to the taxonomy, biogeography, and habitat characteristics or environmental correlates of the Hexacorallia and allied taxa.  Data include a bibliographic reference to the work in which each taxon was originally described, synonymy of each taxon taxonomic status of each taxon, images of many species - from the published literature as well as previously unpublished ones, type specimens - by species and by museum, type locality of each species, published distribution of each species, list of relevant publications by each author, and classification schemes of Hexacorallia.  There is another Environmental database at this site which provides data about such variables that are important to hexacorallia as wind speed, air  temperature, precipitation, and water surplus.</abstract>
<purpose>The Biogeoinformatics of Corals provides a public information resource of data, interpretation, and methods related to the taxonomy, biogeography, and habitat characteristics or environmental correlates of the Hexacorallia and allied taxa;  connect and integrate the activities of the individual and institutional partners; keep a wide range of project information updated and available to all interested parties; provide a directory and communication links to participants and related projects.</purpose>
<supplinf>Information was obtained from http://www.kgs.ukans.edu/Hexacoral/.  (previous geoform was 'Database')</supplinf>
</descript>
<timeperd>
<timeinfo>
<sngdate>
<caldate>2002</caldate>
</sngdate>
</timeinfo>
<current>publication date</current>
</timeperd>
<status>
<progress>In Work</progress>
<update>As needed</update>
</status>
<spdom>
<descgeog>world</descgeog>
<bounding>
<westbc>-180</westbc>
<eastbc>180</eastbc>
<northbc>90</northbc>
<southbc>-90</southbc>
</bounding>
</spdom>
<keywords>
<theme>
<themekt>none</themekt>
<themekey>biogeoinformatics</themekey>
<themekey>geospatial data</themekey>
<themekey>taxonomic data</themekey>
<themekey>environmental data</themekey>
</theme>
<place>
<placekt>none</placekt>
<placekey>world</placekey>
</place>
</keywords>
<taxonomy>
<keywtax>
<taxonkt>none</taxonkt>
<taxonkey>hexacorallia</taxonkey>
<taxonkey>corals</taxonkey>
<taxonkey>sea anemones</taxonkey>
</keywtax>
<taxonsys>
<classsys>
<classcit>
<citeinfo>
<origin>Agencies listed below</origin>
<pubdate>2002</pubdate>
<title>Integrated Taxonomic Information System</title>
<geoform>Database</geoform>
<pubinfo>
<pubplace>Washington, D.C.</pubplace>
<publish>U.S. Department of Agriculture</publish>
</pubinfo>
<othercit>Department of Commerce, National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration (NOAA),  Department of Interior (DOI), Geological Survey (USGS), Environmental Protection Agency (EPA), Department of Agriculture (USDA), Agriculture Research Service (ARS) Natural Resources Conservation Service (NRCS) Smithsonian Institution National Museum of Natural History (NMNH).</othercit>
<onlink>http://www.itis.usda.gov/</onlink>
</citeinfo>
</classcit>
</classsys>
<taxonpro>unknown</taxonpro>
</taxonsys>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Kingdom</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Animalia</taxonrv>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Phylum</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Cnidaria</taxonrv>
<common>cinidarians, coelenterates</common>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Class</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Anthozoa</taxonrv>
<common>corals</common>
<common>flower animals</common>
<common>sea anemones</common>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Sub Class</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Hexacorallia</taxonrv>
</taxoncl>
</taxoncl>
</taxoncl>
</taxoncl>
</taxonomy>
<accconst>Access to some of the information is controlled by password.</accconst>
<useconst>none</useconst>
<ptcontac>
<cntinfo>
<cntperp>
<cntper>Daphne Fautin</cntper>
<cntorg>University of Kansas, Division of Biological Sciences</cntorg>
</cntperp>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
<city>Lawrence</city>
<state>Kansas</state>
<postal>66045</postal>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>785 864-3062</cntvoice>
<cntfax>785 864-5321</cntfax>
<cntemail>fautin@ukans.edu</cntemail>
</cntinfo>
</ptcontac>
</idinfo>
<dataqual>
<attracc>
<attraccr>Updates, including both additions and corrections, are being made continually in all categories. Corrections are made as errors are found.  Additions of data and functionalities are made at intervals of several months; the date of the current version is prominently displayed. Archival copies of previous versions can be obtained upon request.</attraccr>
</attracc>
<logic>not applicable</logic>
<complete>As of 15 July 2002, the inventory of genera and species was virtually complete for Actiniaria, Ceriantharia, Corallimorpharia, and Ptychodactiaria (now considered a component of Actiniaria), although not all associated data are available for every species. As bibliographic details for higher taxonomic levels are assembled, the hierarchical placement of each taxon will be specified.</complete>
<lineage>
<method>
<methtype>database</methtype>
<methdesc>The 'Biodata' query structure and database can be searched by geographic location of the entries, by various levels of taxonomic classification (including synonyms), by aspects of the literature reference(s) (Title, Author, Year), and by the Museum repository for type specimens (if any). Images are included if available.</methdesc>
</method>
<method>
<methtype>database</methtype>
<methdesc>
The 'Envirodata' query structure provides access to the contents of a global, half-degree (30') database that serves a variety of marine, terrestrial, atmospheric and geomorphic global datasets in a common scale and format. This database is designed to be queried first by geographic region or location, and a variety of options are available for extraction of data f or the grid cells
representing multiple points or regions. The environmental variables are selected from a user specified version of the database - a selected (preferred) data set, all available environmental data, or either selected or total data bases with Land-Ocean Interactions in the Coastal Zone (LOICZ) biogeochemical budget variables included.
</methdesc>
</method>
<procstep>
<procdesc>unknown</procdesc>
<procdate>Unknown</procdate>
</procstep>
</lineage>
</dataqual>
<spdoinfo>
<indspref>Based on local reference names.</indspref>
</spdoinfo>
<eainfo>
<overview>
<eaover>Entity - hexacorallia; attributes - taxonomy, distribution, habitat, environmental variables: wind speed, air temperature, water surplus, water deficit, evapotranspiration, snow melt</eaover>
<eadetcit>none</eadetcit>
</overview>
</eainfo>
<distinfo>
<distrib>
<cntinfo>
<cntperp>
<cntper>Daphne Fautin</cntper>
<cntorg>University of Kansas, Division of Biological Sciences</cntorg>
</cntperp>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
<city>Lawrence</city>
<state>Kansas</state>
<postal>66045</postal>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>785 864-3062</cntvoice>
<cntfax>785 864-5321</cntfax>
<cntemail>fautin@ukans.edu</cntemail>
</cntinfo>
</distrib>
<distliab>Although these data have been processed successfully on a computer system at the University of Kansas, no warranty expressed or implied is made regarding the accuracy or utility of the data on any other system or for general or scientific purposes, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty. This disclaimer applies both to individual use of the data and aggregate use with other data.  It is strongly recommended that these data are directly acquired from a University of Kansas server, and not indirectly through other sources which may have changed the data in some way.  It is also strongly recommended that careful attention be paid to the contents of the metadata file associated with these data.  The University of Kansas shall not be held liable for improper or incorrect use of the data described and/or contained herein.</distliab>
<stdorder>
<digform>
<digtinfo>
<formname>online database</formname>
</digtinfo>
<digtopt>
<onlinopt>
<computer>
<networka>
<networkr>http://www.kgs.ukans.edu/Hexacoral/Biodata/index.html</networkr>
</networka>
</computer>
</onlinopt>
</digtopt>
</digform>
<fees>None, if available online.</fees>
</stdorder>
</distinfo>
<metainfo>
<metd>20020401</metd>
<metfrd>20030401</metfrd>
<metc>
<cntinfo>
<cntperp>
<cntper>Cheryl Solomon</cntper>
<cntorg>Science Systems and Applications, Inc.</cntorg>
</cntperp>
<cntpos>Metadata specialist</cntpos>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
<address>10210 Greenbelt Road, Suite 500</address>
<city>Lanham</city>
<state>Maryland</state>
<postal>20706</postal>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>301 867-2080</cntvoice>
<cntfax>301-867-2149.</cntfax>
<cntemail>solomon@gcmd.nasa.gov</cntemail>
</cntinfo>
</metc>
<metstdn>FGDC Biological Data Profile of the Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
<metstdv>FGDC-STD-001.1-1999</metstdv>
</metainfo>
<mercury><begdate>20020101</begdate><enddate>20021231</enddate><htmlurl>http://mercury.ornl.gov/metadata/nbii/html/nbii/www.nbii.gov_metadata_mdata_FAO_fao_d_hexacorallia.html</htmlurl><LTER-Site>nbii</LTER-Site></mercury></metadata>
