<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<metadata><Source>http://www.nbii.gov/metadata/mdata/brd-bib/usgs_brd_fresc_b_utcheatgrass.sgml</Source>
<idinfo>
<citation>
<citeinfo>
<origin>Jayne Belnap and Susan L. Phillips</origin>
<pubdate>2001</pubdate>
<title>Soil biota in an ungrazed grassland: response to annual grass (Bromus tectorum) invasion</title>
<geoform>Journal article</geoform>
<serinfo>
<sername>Ecological Applications</sername>
<issue>11(5):1261-1275</issue>
</serinfo>
<othercit>
Science Information System Project #: 762
Publication Control #: 1041
</othercit>
</citeinfo>
</citation>
<descript>
<abstract>Due to the devastating invasion of exotic plants in natural ecosystems, it is important for ecologists and land managers to understand the relationship between invasive plants and native ecosystems. In the past few years there have been many efforts directed at the aboveground, more visible impacts of invasive species on ecosystems. Unfortunately, little attention has been given to the role that the more inconspicuous soil food webs play in the invasion process and how the response of soil biota to invasive plants may influence the way native ecosystems function. Recently two USGS scientists, Jayne Belnap and Susan Phillips, published a paper discussing how the invasion of cheatgrass altered the structure of communities in Canyonlands National Park. They found that the invasion increased the quantities of some members (e.g. bacteria), while decreasing the number and richness of other members (e.g. fungi). Their findings suggest that many changes imposed upon the native ecosystem by the invading grass may be difficult or impossible to reverse. As a result they suggest that management efforts spent in preventing invasion or eliminating new invasions are likely to be more effective than trying to restore native ecosystem conditions prior to invasion.</abstract>
<purpose>Reporting research results</purpose>
<supplinf>
Extent of item: 14pp
Illustrative Matter:  tables, graphs, figures
</supplinf>
</descript>
<timeperd>
<timeinfo>
<sngdate>
<caldate>2001</caldate>
</sngdate>
</timeinfo>
<current>publication date</current>
</timeperd>
<status>
<progress>Complete</progress>
<update>None planned</update>
</status>
<spdom>
<descgeog>Canyonlands National Park, Utah</descgeog>
<bounding>
<westbc>-110.1</westbc>
<eastbc>-109.68</eastbc>
<northbc>38.55</northbc>
<southbc>37.95</southbc>
</bounding>
</spdom>
<keywords>
<theme>
<themekt>Science Information System Controlled Vocabulary</themekt>
<themekey>Desert and Arid Lands</themekey>
<themekey>Grassland/Rangeland</themekey>
<themekey>Invasive Species</themekey>
<themekey>Terrestrial</themekey>
</theme>
<place>
<placekt>none</placekt>
<placekey>Canyonlands National Park</placekey>
<placekey>Utah</placekey>
<placekey>UT</placekey>
</place>
</keywords>
<taxonomy>
<keywtax>
<taxonkt>none</taxonkt>
<taxonkey>plants</taxonkey>
</keywtax>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Kingdom</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Plantae</taxonrv>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Division</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Magnoliophyta</taxonrv>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Class</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Liliopsida</taxonrv>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Order</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Cyperales</taxonrv>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Family</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Poaceae</taxonrv>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Genus</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Bromus</taxonrv>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Species</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Bromus tectorum</taxonrv>
<common>cheat grass</common>
</taxoncl>
</taxoncl>
</taxoncl>
</taxoncl>
</taxoncl>
</taxoncl>
</taxoncl>
</taxonomy>
<accconst>None</accconst>
<useconst>None</useconst>
<ptcontac>
<cntinfo>
<cntperp>
<cntper>Belnap, Jayne</cntper>
<cntorg>Forest and Rangeland Ecosystem Science Center (FRESC)</cntorg>
</cntperp>
<cntpos>Station Leader</cntpos>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
<address>2290 S. West Resource Blvd.</address>
<city>Moab</city>
<state>UT</state>
<postal>84532</postal>
<country>USA</country>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>(435) 719-2333</cntvoice>
<cntfax>(435) 719-2300</cntfax>
<cntemail>jayne_belnap@usgs.gov</cntemail>
</cntinfo>
</ptcontac>
</idinfo>
<distinfo>
<distrib>
<cntinfo>
<cntorgp>
<cntorg>Olendorff Library</cntorg>
</cntorgp>
<cntpos>Librarian</cntpos>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
<address>
USGS FRESC Snake River Field Station
970 Lusk Street
</address>
<city>Boise</city>
<state>ID</state>
<postal>83706</postal>
<country>USA</country>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>208 426-5218</cntvoice>
<cntfax>208 426-5210</cntfax>
</cntinfo>
</distrib>
<resdesc>Publication Control #: 1041</resdesc>
<distliab>
The USGS Forest and Rangeland Ecosystem Science Center and its research partners make every effort to provide and maintain accurate, complete, usable, and timely information. However, some USGS data and information may, of necessity, be preliminary in nature. These data and information are provided with the understanding that they are not guaranteed to be correct or complete. Users are cautioned to consider carefully the provisional nature of these data and information before using them for decisions that concern personal or public safety or the conduct of business that involves substantial monetary or operational consequences. It is also strongly recommended that careful attention be paid to the contents of the metadata file associated with these data and information. Conclusions drawn from, or actions undertaken on the basis of, such data and information are the sole responsibility of the user.
USGS-authored or produced data and information are in the public domain. Whereas the content of many USGS publications and other information resources are in the public domain, some USGS products contain material that is copyrighted by others and used by the USGS with permission. Users of this information may need to obtain permission from the copyright owner for other uses. Furthermore, some non-USGS data, products, and information referred to may be protected under U.S. and foreign copyright laws. Users may need to obtain permission from the copyright owner to acquire, use, reproduce, or distribute these materials. It is the sole responsibility of the user of the information to secure all necessary permission.
</distliab>
<stdorder>
<nondig>Publications are available as reprints, reports, pamphlets, or brochures.</nondig>
<fees>None</fees>
<ordering>Request specific publications by reference number.</ordering>
</stdorder>
</distinfo>
<metainfo>
<metd>20011105</metd>
<metrd>20011112</metrd>
<metc>
<cntinfo>
<cntorgp>
<cntorg>USGS Forest and Rangeland Ecosystem Science Center (FRESC)</cntorg>
</cntorgp>
<cntpos>Library</cntpos>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
<address>
777 NW 9th St.
Suite 100
</address>
<city>Corvallis</city>
<state>OR</state>
<postal>97330</postal>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>541-750-1030</cntvoice>
<cntfax>541-750-1069</cntfax>
<cntemail>fresc_outreach@usgs.gov</cntemail>
</cntinfo>
</metc>
<metstdn>FGDC Biological Data Profile of the Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
<metstdv>FGDC-STD-001.1-1999</metstdv>
</metainfo>
<mercury><begdate>20010101</begdate><enddate>20011231</enddate><htmlurl>http://mercury.ornl.gov/metadata/nbii/html/brd/www.nbii.gov_metadata_mdata_brd-bib_usgs_brd_fresc_b_utcheatgrass.html</htmlurl><LTER-Site>brd</LTER-Site></mercury></metadata>
