<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<metadata><Source>http://www.nbii.gov/metadata/mdata/CBI/usgs_brd_cbi_d_throattribacc.sgml</Source>
<idinfo>
<citation>
<citeinfo>
<origin>
Remote Sensing and GIS Group, Technical Service Center, US Bureau of Reclamation, Mail Code
D-8260, POB 25007, Denver CO 80225
</origin>
<pubdate>2000</pubdate>
<title>Theodore Roosevelt National Park Accuracy Assessment Data</title>
<geoform>maps data</geoform>
<serinfo>
<sername>USGS-NPS Vegetation Mapping Program</sername>
<issue>Theodore Roosevelt National Park</issue>
</serinfo>
<pubinfo>
<pubplace>Denver, CO</pubplace>
<publish>USGS-BRD</publish>
</pubinfo>
<othercit>Created under contract to the USGS-BRD-CBI</othercit>
<onlink>http://biology.usgs.gov/npsveg/thro/report.pdf#accuracy</onlink>
<onlink>http://biology.usgs.gov/npsveg/thro/report.pdf#assessment</onlink>
<onlink>http://biology.usgs.gov/npsveg/thro/images/throaa.jpg</onlink>
<onlink>http://biology.usgs.gov/npsveg/ftp/vegmapping/thro/throaa.exe</onlink>
<onlink>http://biology.usgs.gov/npsveg/ftp/vegmapping/thro/throaasdts.exe</onlink>
<onlink>http://biology.usgs.gov/npsveg/thro/aa_matrix.pdf</onlink>
<onlink>http://biology.usgs.gov/npsveg/ftp/vegmapping/thro/aa_matrix.xls</onlink>
</citeinfo>
</citation>
<descript>
<abstract>
This metadata is for the accuracy assessment data
associated with the vegetation land cover and land use
geospatial database for Theodore Roosevelt National Park and
surrounding areas.  The project is authorized as
part of the USGS/NPS Vegetation Mapping Program
(http://biology.usgs.gov/npsveg). The program is
being administered by the Biological Resources
Division (BRD) of the United States Geological
Survey (USGS).  The USGS/BRD is responsible for
overall management and oversight of all ongoing
mapping efforts.  This mapping effort was
performed by the US Bureau of Reclamation's (USBR)
Remote Sensing and GIS Group, Technical Service
Center, Denver, CO. The vegetation mapping program
is part of a larger Inventory and Monitoring (I&amp;M)
program started by the National Park Service (NPS)
Their website is : http://www1.nature.nps.gov/im/
</abstract>
<purpose>
The purposes of the mapping effort are varied and
include the following: Provides support for NPS
Resources Management; Promotes vegetation-related
research for both NPS and USGS/BRD; Provides
support for NPS Planning and Compliance; Adds to
the information base for NPS Interpretation; and
Assists in NPS Operations.  The NPS  I&amp;M goals
are, among others, to map the vegetation of all
national parks and monuments and provide a
baseline inventory of vegetation.
</purpose>
<supplinf>(previous geoform was 'Table')</supplinf>
</descript>
<timeperd>
<timeinfo>
<sngdate>
<caldate>1998</caldate>
</sngdate>
</timeinfo>
<current>
From the USGS-NPS Vegetation Mapping Program Theodore Roosevelt
National Park, North Dakota Procedure Report,
March 7, 2000.  See:
http://biology.usgs.gov/npsveg/thro/report.pdf#accuracy
</current>
</timeperd>
<status>
<progress>Complete</progress>
<update>None Planned</update>
</status>
<spdom>
<bounding>
<westbc>-103.75</westbc>
<eastbc>-103.125</eastbc>
<northbc>47.75</northbc>
<southbc>46.75</southbc>
</bounding>
<descgeog>Theodore Roosevelt NP and surrounding environs</descgeog>
</spdom>
<keywords>
<theme>
<themekt>None</themekt>
<themekey>Land cover</themekey>
<themekey>Land use</themekey>
<themekey>Vegetation</themekey>
<themekey>National Park Service</themekey>
<themekey>Accuracy Assessment</themekey>
</theme>
<place>
<placekt>None</placekt>
<placekey>North Dakota</placekey>
<placekey>Theodore Roosevelt National Park</placekey>
<placekey>Little Missouri River</placekey>
<placekey>Little Missouri National Grasslands</placekey>
<placekey>Elkhorn Ranch</placekey>
<placekey>Medora</placekey>
</place>
</keywords>
<taxonomy>
<keywtax>
<taxonkt>none</taxonkt>
<taxonkey>vegetation</taxonkey>
<taxonkey>plants</taxonkey>
<taxonkey>National Vegetation Classification System</taxonkey>
</keywtax>
<taxonsys>
<classsys>
<classcit>
<citeinfo>
<origin>Anderson, et al</origin>
<pubdate>1976</pubdate>
<title>A Land Use and Land Cover Classification System for Use with Remote Sensor Data</title>
<geoform>document</geoform>
<serinfo>
<sername>Geological Survey Professional Paper</sername>
<issue>No. 964</issue>
</serinfo>
<pubinfo>
<pubplace>Washington, DC</pubplace>
<publish>US GPO</publish>
</pubinfo>
<othercit>This project used the Level II Land Use Classes</othercit>
<onlink>http://biology.usgs.gov/npsveg/classification/index.html</onlink>
</citeinfo>
</classcit>
</classsys>
<taxonpro>Sequence of field test data plots, observation plots, and photo-signature observations.</taxonpro>
</taxonsys>
<taxongen>Refer to complete listing of mapped plant alliances/associations under Supplemental Information above.</taxongen>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Kingdom</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Plantae</taxonrv>
</taxoncl>
</taxonomy>
<accconst>None</accconst>
<useconst>
Acknowledgment of the USGS/BRD, National Park Service,
and the USBR/RSGIS Group would be appreciated in
products derived from these data.  Any person using
the information presented here should fully understand
the data collection and compilation procedures, as
described in the metadata, before beginning
analysis.  The burden for determining fitness for
use lies entirely with the user.
</useconst>
<ptcontac>
<cntinfo>
<cntorgp>
<cntper>USGS-NPS Vegetation Mapping Program Coordinator</cntper>
<cntorg>
USGS Biological Resources Division, Center for Biological
Informatics
</cntorg>
</cntorgp>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>Physical Address</addrtype>
<address>USGS</address>
<address>Biological Resources Division, CBI</address>
<address>Building 810, Room 8000</address>
<city>Denver</city>
<state>Colorado</state>
<postal>80225-0046</postal>
<country>USA</country>
</cntaddr>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>Mailing Address</addrtype>
<address>USGS</address>
<address>Biological Resources Division, CBI</address>
<address>PO BOX 25046, DFC, MS302</address>
<city>Denver</city>
<state>Colorado</state>
<postal>80225-0046</postal>
<country>USA</country>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>(303) 202-4220</cntvoice>
<cntfax>303-202-4229</cntfax>
<cntfax>303-202-4219 (org)</cntfax>
<cntemail>gs-b-npsveg@usgs.gov</cntemail>
</cntinfo>
</ptcontac>
<browse>
<browsen>http://biology.usgs.gov/npsveg/thro/images/throaa.jpg</browsen>
<browsed>248 Kbyte</browsed>
<browset>JPEG</browset>
</browse>
<datacred>Dan Cogan, Doug Crawford, Jean Pennell, Trudy Meyer, Jim Von Loh of Theodore Roosevelt NP, NPS</datacred>
<native>UNIX-ARC/INFO</native>
</idinfo>
<dataqual>
<attracc>
<attraccr>
Overall, initial accuracy of the vegetation map is 74.3% for all vegetation classes and the Kappa Index is 71.3%.  Results for each vegetation class are discussed here, and recommendations are made relative to creating a more accurate vegetation map, as desired.
The specific results are presented in Tables 4-2 and 4-3 below.  Confidence interval calculations are presented in Appendix O.  In general, the percentage of the Park that an individual map class covered is reflected in the number of AA points collected for that type.  For example, needle-and-thread herbaceous alliance was interpreted for approximately 33% of the Park and is represented by 28% of the AA points, and the  badlands sparse vegetation complex was interpreted for approximately 20% of the Park and is represented by 14% of the AA points.  Similarly, the prairie dog town complex was interpreted for approximately 2% of the Park and is represented by 1.7% of the AA points.
However, several map classes are sampled with a larger number of AA points relative to their actual percent abundance/ground cover.  For example:  the silver buffaloberry shrubland alliance covers 0.1 % of the park and is represented by 2.6% of the AA points;  the little bluestem - sideoats grama herbaceous alliance covers  0.3 % and is represented by 3.5% of the AA points; and  the prairie sandreed herbaceous alliance covers  0.2 % and is represented by 2.3% of the AA points.  Four map classes were not sampled as follows:  the ponderosa pine woodland alliance does not occur within Park boundaries and is well-represented by plot and observation data;  the quaking aspen woodland alliance has a plot and/or observation form for every stand known to occur in the Park and no additional stands were observed;  the emergent wetland class is too small to be interpreted on aerial photos and has an observation form for every wetland observed during field research in the Park; and the Canada thistle herbaceous alliance is too small to be interpreted on aerial photos and has several observation forms reporting occurrences in the Park.
</attraccr>
</attracc>
<logic>Unknown</logic>
<complete>
AA data, including limited habitat and vegetation data, was recorded on field forms to document the classification decision made by the investigator.  All AA data were collected during July 1998.  The weather at this time was unusually warm and vegetation readily identifiable except where it was heavily grazed.
AA data were collected as shown in Figure 3-5 with more points collected within extensive types, e.g., AA points were collected proportional to the size of the plant association/map class within the Park.  Accuracy assessment of the THRO project area was conducted in January 2000.  This involved entering all accuracy data points into a coverage and overlaying these electronically on final vegetation maps (quarter-quads).  AA point (identification) numbers plotted alongside each point allowed for comparison with accuracy assessment data forms.  A contingency table was set up to record the reference data (collected field data) versus the sample data (vegetation map) for each map unit.
</complete>
<posacc>
<horizpa>
<horizpar>The UTM coordinates and elevation of all plots were logged using a hand-held Precision Lightweight Global Positioning  System (GPS) Receiver (PLGR) unit.</horizpar>
</horizpa>
</posacc>
<lineage>
<procstep>
<procdesc>
AA data were collected as shown in Figure 3-5 with more points collected within extensive types, e.g., AA points were collected proportional to the size of the plant association/map class within the Park.  Accuracy assessment of the THRO project area was conducted in January 2000.  This involved entering all accuracy data points into a coverage and overlaying these electronically on final vegetation maps (quarter-quads).  AA point (identification) numbers plotted alongside each point allowed for comparison with accuracy assessment data forms.  A contingency table was set up to record the reference data (collected field data) versus the sample data (vegetation map) for each map unit.
Errors of commission (i.e. user&amp;#146;s errors) for each class were calculated by dividing the number of correctly classified samples by the total number of samples that were classified as belonging to that map class.  Errors of omission (i.e. producer&amp;#146;s errors) for each class were calculated by dividing the number of samples that were classified correctly by the total number of reference samples in that class.  Confidence intervals for each map class were calculated using one of the methods shown in Table 3-1. depending on the normality and size of the data.
Overall total accuracy for THRO is calculated across all sampled map classes by dividing the number of correctly classified accuracy points by the total number of accuracy points.  Confidence intervals for overall total accuracy were calculated using the equation for normally distributed data (see Table 3-1).  A Kappa Index (Foody 1992 in Accuracy Assessment Procedures, TNC, 1994) was used to help account for any correct classification due to chance.
A total of 346 accuracy assessment points were used to assess the THRO vegetation map by:
using AA points collected during the summer of 1998 (front-loading method);
entering AA point coordinates into an electronic format to overlay on the vegetation map;
comparing map vegetation classification (transferred from photo interpretation) with field assessment of vegetation type to determine errors of omission and commission;
resolving questions by referring to original data forms, so that Dr. Butler could make the final determination; and
recording all information on the AA matrix (Table 4-3).
Overall, initial accuracy of the vegetation map is 74.3% for all vegetation classes and the Kappa Index is 71.3%.
The specific results are presented in Tables 4-2 and 4-3 below.  Confidence interval calculations are presented in Appendix O.  In general, the percentage of the Park that an individual map class covered is reflected in the number of AA points collected for that type.  For example, needle-and-thread herbaceous alliance was interpreted for approximately 33% of the Park and is represented by 28% of the AA points, and the  badlands sparse vegetation complex was interpreted for approximately 20% of the Park and is represented by 14% of the AA points.  Similarly, the prairie dog town complex was interpreted for approximately 2% of the Park and is represented by 1.7% of the AA points.
However, several map classes are sampled with a larger number of AA points relative to their actual percent abundance/ground cover.  For example:  the silver buffaloberry shrubland alliance covers 0.1 % of the park and is represented by 2.6% of the AA points;  the little bluestem - sideoats grama herbaceous alliance covers  0.3 % and is represented by 3.5% of the AA points; and  the prairie sandreed herbaceous alliance covers  0.2 % and is represented by 2.3% of the AA points.  Four map classes were not sampled as follows:  the ponderosa pine woodland alliance does not occur within Park boundaries and is well-represented by plot and observation data;  the quaking aspen woodland alliance has a plot and/or observation form for every stand known to occur in the Park and no additional stands were observed;  the emergent wetland class is too small to be interpreted on aerial photos and has an observation form for every wetland observed during field research in the Park; and the Canada thistle herbaceous alliance is too small to be interpreted on aerial photos and has several observation forms reporting occurrences in the Park.
</procdesc>
<procdate>199909</procdate>
</procstep>
<method>
<methtype>Field</methtype>
<methodid>
<methkt>None</methkt>
<methkey>front-loading</methkey>
<methkey>Kappa Index</methkey>
</methodid>
<methdesc>
The accuracy assessment (AA) for THRO vegetation mapping analyses consisted of preliminary planning and discussion, logistical planning, fieldwork, analysis of fieldwork, and computation of final results.  Preliminary planning involved RSGIG and Dr. Jack Butler (Plant Ecologist hired by TNC and responsible for collecting the field AA data).  Following detailed discussion, a modified accuracy assessment procedure dubbed &amp;#147;front-loading&amp;#148; (Owens 1998) was selected using protocols outlined in the Accuracy Assessment Procedures (TNC 1994).
The following guidelines for this procedure were adopted at this time:
Observations of vegetation classes were to be ground-based.
Ground sampling techniques were to be similar to the Observation Points collected during initial classification.
The number of samples per plant association/map class would vary depending on abundance of the class upon the landscape.
Logistical planning for the AA revolved around access to work areas within the Park.  The actual assessment was begun prior to completion of preliminary vegetation maps for the Park, thus the front-loading aspect of the study.
A maximum number of points to be collected was not assigned, so that the Park could be sampled as completely as possible.
Assessment was performed within Park boundaries and data points were not limited to the previously described gradsects, but rather were located based on availability of access and to a lesser extent, time constraints.  Selecting random AA sampling sites beforehand was deemed unnecessary due to familiarity of the principal researcher with vegetation types and distribution at THRO.  The final points chosen for assessment were selected to be as representative as possible of the vegetation in the immediate area, well away from stand boundaries, and in a stand larger than the minimum mapping unit (exceptions were made for emergent wetland, scoria and bentonite exposures, and some exotic species classes which rarely exceeded 0.5 hectares in size).  Field ecologists were supplied with a vegetation key, to be used to determine plant associations/map classes to enter on the field form.  The field form used for the AA was a modified version of the observation point form (Appendix E).
AA data, including limited habitat and vegetation data, was recorded on field forms to document the classification decision made by the investigator.  All AA data were collected during July 1998.  The weather at this time was unusually warm and vegetation readily identifiable except where it was heavily grazed.
AA data were collected as shown in Figure 3-5 with more points collected within extensive types, e.g., AA points were collected proportional to the size of the plant association/map class within the Park.  Accuracy assessment of the THRO project area was conducted in January 2000.  This involved entering all accuracy data points into a coverage and overlaying these electronically on final vegetation maps (quarter-quads).  AA point (identification) numbers plotted alongside each point allowed for comparison with accuracy assessment data forms.  A contingency table was set up to record the reference data (collected field data) versus the sample data (vegetation map) for each map unit.
</methdesc>
<methcite>
<citeinfo>
<origin>Remote Sensing and GIS Group, Technical Service Center, US Bureau of Reclamation, MC-D8260, POB 25007, Denver CO 80225</origin>
<pubdate>1998</pubdate>
<title>
Accuracy Assessment Procedures,
NBS/NPS Vegetation Mapping Program
</title>
<geoform>Report</geoform>
<pubinfo>
<pubplace>Denver, Colorado</pubplace>
<publish>USGS-BRD, Center for Biological Informatics</publish>
</pubinfo>
<othercit>
Prepared for:
United States Department of Interior
National Biological Survey and National Park Service
Prepared by:
Environmental Systems Research Institute
380 New York Street
Redlands, California 92373
National Center for Geographic Information and Analysis
University of California
3510 Phelps Hall
Santa Barbara, California 93106
The Nature Conservancy
1815 N. Lynn Street
Arlington, Virginia  22209
</othercit>
<onlink>http://biology.usgs.gov/npsveg/aa/aa.html</onlink>
</citeinfo>
</methcite>
</method>
</lineage>
</dataqual>
<spdoinfo>
<direct>Point</direct>
</spdoinfo>
<spref>
<horizsys>
<planar>
<gridsys>
<gridsysn>Universal Transverse Mercator</gridsysn>
<utm>
<utmzone>13</utmzone>
<transmer>
<longcm>-105</longcm>
<latprjo>0</latprjo>
<feast>0</feast>
<fnorth>0</fnorth>
<sfctrmer>.9996</sfctrmer>
</transmer>
</utm>
</gridsys>
<planci>
<plance>coordinate pair</plance>
<coordrep>
<absres>1</absres>
<ordres>1</ordres>
</coordrep>
<plandu>meters</plandu>
</planci>
</planar>
<geodetic>
<horizdn>North American Datum of 1983</horizdn>
<ellips>Geodetic Reference System 80</ellips>
<semiaxis>6378137</semiaxis>
<denflat>298.257</denflat>
</geodetic>
</horizsys>
</spref>
<eainfo>
<overview>
<eaover>
Information collected for Accuracy Assessment included:
Plot Number
Park Code
Date
Observer(s)
Datum
Accuracy
UTM Coordinates:       Easting     Northing
UTM Zone     9. Offset from Point:       Easting (in meters)      Northing (in meters)
Topographic Description
Elevation
Aspect
Veg Assoc. at Site
Veg Assoc. 2 within 50m of Site
Veg Assoc. 3 within 50m of Site
Major Species Present (by strata)
Canopy Closure of Top Layer
Rationale for Classification
Comments
</eaover>
<eadetcit>
See:
Accuracy Assessment Field Form:
http://biology.usgs.gov/npsveg/thro/report.pdf#appendixe
Mapping totals for area and quantity of polygons.
http://biology.usgs.gov/npsveg/thro/report.pdf#table4-1
Summary of AA Results for Theodore Roosevelt National Park, by map class.
http://biology.usgs.gov/npsveg/thro/report.pdf#table4-2
Contingency table (error matrix) for THRO vegetation mapping accuracy assessment.
http://biology.usgs.gov/npsveg/thro/aa_matrix.pdf
The map codes as described in Appendix K:
http://biology.usgs.gov/npsveg/thro/codescript.pdf
</eadetcit>
</overview>
</eainfo>
<distinfo>
<distrib>
<cntinfo>
<cntperp>
<cntper>USGS-NPS Vegetation Mapping Program Coordinator</cntper>
<cntorg>Center for Biological Informatics, USGS-BRD</cntorg>
</cntperp>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>Mailing Address</addrtype>
<address>PO Box 25046, MS-302</address>
<city>Denver</city>
<state>Colorado</state>
<postal>80225</postal>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>(303) 202-4220</cntvoice>
<cntfax>303-202-4229</cntfax>
<cntfax>303-202-4219 (org)</cntfax>
<cntemail>gs-b-npsveg@usgs.gov</cntemail>
</cntinfo>
</distrib>
<resdesc>Badlands National Accuracy Assessment Data</resdesc>
<distliab>
Although these data have been processed
successfully on a computer system at the
Biological Resources Division, no warranty
expressed or implied is made regarding the
accuracy or utility of the data on any other
system or for general or scientific purposes, nor
shall the act of distribution constitute any such
warranty. This disclaimer applies both to
individual use of the data and aggregate use with
other data.  It is strongly recommended that these
data are directly acquired from a Biological
Resources Division server, and not indirectly
through other sources which may have changed the
data in some way.  It is also strongly recommended
that careful attention be paid to the contents of
the metadata file associated with these data.  The
Biological Resources Division shall not be held
liable for improper or incorrect use of the data
described and/or contained herein.
</distliab>
<stdorder>
<digform>
<digtinfo>
<formname>PDF</formname>
</digtinfo>
<digtopt>
<onlinopt>
<computer>
<networka>
<networkr>http://biology.usgs.gov/npsveg/thro/report.pdf#accuracy</networkr>
</networka>
</computer>
</onlinopt>
</digtopt>
</digform>
<fees>None</fees>
</stdorder>
<stdorder>
<digform>
<digtinfo>
<formname>PDF</formname>
</digtinfo>
<digtopt>
<onlinopt>
<computer>
<networka>
<networkr>http://biology.usgs.gov/npsveg/thro/report.pdf#assessment</networkr>
</networka>
</computer>
</onlinopt>
</digtopt>
</digform>
<fees>None</fees>
</stdorder>
<stdorder>
<digform>
<digtinfo>
<formname>JPG</formname>
</digtinfo>
<digtopt>
<onlinopt>
<computer>
<networka>
<networkr>http://biology.usgs.gov/npsveg/thro/images/throaa.jpg</networkr>
</networka>
</computer>
</onlinopt>
</digtopt>
</digform>
<fees>None</fees>
</stdorder>
<stdorder>
<digform>
<digtinfo>
<formname>EXE</formname>
</digtinfo>
<digtopt>
<onlinopt>
<computer>
<networka>
<networkr>http://biology.usgs.gov/npsveg/ftp/vegmapping/thro/throaa.exe</networkr>
</networka>
</computer>
</onlinopt>
</digtopt>
</digform>
<fees>None</fees>
</stdorder>
<stdorder>
<digform>
<digtinfo>
<formname>SDTS</formname>
</digtinfo>
<digtopt>
<onlinopt>
<computer>
<networka>
<networkr>http://biology.usgs.gov/npsveg/ftp/vegmapping/thro/throaasdts.exe</networkr>
</networka>
</computer>
</onlinopt>
</digtopt>
</digform>
<fees>None</fees>
</stdorder>
<stdorder>
<digform>
<digtinfo>
<formname>PDF</formname>
</digtinfo>
<digtopt>
<onlinopt>
<computer>
<networka>
<networkr>http://biology.usgs.gov/npsveg/thro/aa_matrix.pdf</networkr>
</networka>
</computer>
</onlinopt>
</digtopt>
</digform>
<fees>None</fees>
</stdorder>
<stdorder>
<digform>
<digtinfo>
<formname>EXCEL</formname>
</digtinfo>
<digtopt>
<onlinopt>
<computer>
<networka>
<networkr>http://biology.usgs.gov/npsveg/ftp/vegmapping/thro/aa_matrix.xls</networkr>
</networka>
</computer>
</onlinopt>
</digtopt>
</digform>
<fees>None</fees>
</stdorder>
</distinfo>
<metainfo>
<metd>200001</metd>
<metrd>20050517</metrd>
<metc>
<cntinfo>
<cntorgp>
<cntorg>USGS-NPS Vegetation Mapping Program Coordinator</cntorg>
</cntorgp>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
<address>
U.S. Geological Survey, Center for Biological Informatics, MS 302,
Room 8000, Building 810, Denver Federal Center
</address>
<city>Denver</city>
<state>Colorado</state>
<postal>80225</postal>
<country>USA</country>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>(303) 202-4220</cntvoice>
<cntfax>(303) 202-4219</cntfax>
<cntemail>gs-b-npsveg@usgs.gov</cntemail>
</cntinfo>
</metc>
<metstdn>FGDC-STD-001.1-1999 Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata, 1998 Part 1: Biological Data Profile, 1999</metstdn>
<metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
<metextns>
<onlink>http://biology.usgs.gov/fgdc.bio/bionwext.txt</onlink>
<metprof>Biological Data Profile FGDC-STD-001.1-1999</metprof>
</metextns>
</metainfo>
<mercury><begdate>19980101</begdate><enddate>19981231</enddate><htmlurl>http://mercury.ornl.gov/metadata/nbii/html/nbii/www.nbii.gov_metadata_mdata_CBI_usgs_brd_cbi_d_throattribacc.html</htmlurl><LTER-Site>nbii</LTER-Site></mercury></metadata>
