<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<metadata><Source>http://www.nbii.gov/metadata/mdata/CBI/usgs_brd_cbi_d_rocrveg.sgml</Source>
<idinfo>
<citation>
<citeinfo>
<origin>Air Survey Corporation Sterling, Virginia</origin>
<pubdate>19961029</pubdate>
<pubtime>Unknown</pubtime>
<title>Rock Creek Park</title>
<edition>Version 1.0</edition>
<geoform>maps data</geoform>
<serinfo>
<sername>1.0</sername>
<issue>Unknown</issue>
</serinfo>
<pubinfo>
<pubplace>Sterling Virginia</pubplace>
<publish>Air Survey Corporation</publish>
</pubinfo>
<othercit>The aerial photography is CIR 1:6,000 scale.</othercit>
<onlink>http://biology.usgs.gov/npsveg/rocr/images/rocrveg.jpg</onlink>
<onlink>http://biology.usgs.gov/npsveg/ftp/vegmapping/rocr/rocr.exe</onlink>
<onlink>http://biology.usgs.gov/npsveg/ftp/vegmapping/rocr/rocrsdts.exe</onlink>
<onlink>http://biology.usgs.gov/npsveg/ftp/vegmapping/rocr/rocrbdy.exe</onlink>
<onlink>http://biology.usgs.gov/npsveg/ftp/vegmapping/rocr/rocrbdysdts.exe</onlink>
</citeinfo>
</citation>
<descript>
<abstract>
The National Park Service (NPS), in conjunction
with the Biological Resources Division (BRD) of
the U.S. Geological Survey (USGS), has implemented
a program to "develop a uniform hierarchical
vegetation methodology" at a national level.  The
program will also create a geographic information
system (GIS) database for the parks under its
management.  The purpose of the data is to
document the state of vegetation within the NPS
service area during the 1990's, thereby providing
a baseline study for further analysis at the
Regional or Service-wide level.  Aerial
Information Systems (AIS) was subcontracted by
Environmental Systems Research Institute (ESRI),
the prime contractor, to perform the
photointerpretation for the program.  ESRI
subcontracted The Nature Conservancy (TNC) to
conduct the field sampling effort and to support
the development of the National Standard
Classification.
</abstract>
<purpose>
Several parks, representing different regions,
environmental conditions, and vegetation types,
were chosen by BRD to be part of the prototype
phase of the program.  The initial goal of the
prototype phase is to "develop, test, refine, and
finalize the standards and protocols" to be used
during the production phase of the project.  This
includes the development of a standardized
vegetation classification system for each park and
the establishment of photointerpretation, field,
and accuracy assessment procedures.  Rock Creek
Park, established in 1890, was designated as one
of the prototype parks.  The park is located on
the fall line between the Atlantic coastal plain
and the piedmont.  The main portion of the park is
bounded on the north by the Maryland State line
and on the south by the Virginia State line.  Its
western edge follows along Oregon Avenue, and it
is bounded on the east by 16th Street NW.  The
western outlying portions of the Park extend to
and slightly beyond Nebraska Avenue NW.  The
eastern outlying portions extend from 16th Street
NW to the junction of US Highway 1 and the
Maryland border.  The park is noted for having
exceptional resources, including six natural
resources that maintain its significance within
the National Park System.  Included in these six
natural resources, are three that are directly
related to the vegetation of the park.  They are:
1) Deciduous forests, 2) Wetlands, and 3) Plant
species protected in both Virginia and Maryland.
Based on these and other resources, Rock Creek
Park is divided up into nine management zones
pertaining to vegetation, automobile access,
recreation, administration, and cultural
resources.
</purpose>
<supplinf>
Rock Creek is one of the largest forested urban
parks in the United States, with more the &amp;frac34; of the
park's approximately 2,760 acres covered by mature
deciduous forest. A significant portion of this
forest is second growth, with a moderately high
diversity in canopy and understory species.  Rock
Creek Park is made up of steep canyons and side
slopes that bisect several significant east-west
trending ridgelines.  The park descends along the
fall line through numerous small rapids along the
creek.  Rock Creek itself, descends over 150' from
the state line to its confluence with the Potomac
River.  Flood plain development is fairly
restrictive, limited primarily to Rock Creek
itself.  Broad Branch, the main tributary to Rock
Creek within the park, flows southeasterly and
joins Rock Creek towards the southern portion of
the park. At the confluence, the park boundary
significantly narrows in its east-west extent.
All sections are accessible either by automobile
or by hiking.  Most portions of the park are
accessible through short hikes, usually under one
mile.  Gradients above the floodplain are
surprisingly steep, and make for some moderate
hiking.  For purposes of vegetation mapping, the
park was divided into four sections pertaining
primarily to its location on the fall line between
the coastal plain and piedmont.  The park was
further divided into the main portion of the park
(containing Rock Creek), and the various outliner
portions of the park to the east and west.
(previous geoform was 'image')</supplinf>
</descript>
<timeperd>
<timeinfo>
<sngdate>
<caldate>19961029</caldate>
</sngdate>
</timeinfo>
<current>Source_Photography_Date</current>
</timeperd>
<status>
<progress>Complete</progress>
<update>None Planned</update>
</status>
<spdom>
<descgeog>
The park is located on the fall line between the
Atlantic coastal plain and the piedmont.  The main
portion of the park is bounded on the north by the
Maryland State line and on the south by the
Virginia State line.  Its western edge follows
along Oregon Avenue, and it is bounded on the east
by 16th Street NW.  The western outlying portions
of the Park extend to and slightly beyond Nebraska
Avenue NW.  The eastern outlying portions extend
from 16th Street NW to the junction of US Highway
1 and the Maryland border.
</descgeog>
<bounding>
<westbc>77.1</westbc>
<eastbc>77</eastbc>
<northbc>38.98333</northbc>
<southbc>38.9</southbc>
</bounding>
</spdom>
<keywords>
<theme>
<themekt>None</themekt>
<themekey>National Park Service</themekey>
<themekey>U.S. Geological Service</themekey>
<themekey>The Nature Conservancy</themekey>
<themekey>Aerial Information Systems</themekey>
<themekey>Center for Biological Informatics</themekey>
<themekey>land cover</themekey>
<themekey>vegetation</themekey>
<themekey>community</themekey>
<themekey>association</themekey>
</theme>
<place>
<placekt>None</placekt>
<placekey>Rock Creek Park</placekey>
<placekey>Washington D.C.</placekey>
<placekey>USA</placekey>
</place>
<stratum>
<stratkt>None</stratkt>
<stratkey>Glover Archbold Park and Environs</stratkey>
<stratkey>Fort Totten Park, Barnard Hill Park and Environs</stratkey>
<stratkey>Land Use Areas of the Park</stratkey>
<stratkey>Coastal Plain</stratkey>
<stratkey>Piedmont</stratkey>
<stratkey>Forest Zone</stratkey>
</stratum>
<temporal>
<tempkt>None</tempkt>
<tempkey>Data Represents October 1996</tempkey>
</temporal>
</keywords>
<taxonomy>
<keywtax>
<taxonkt>None</taxonkt>
<taxonkey>National Vegetation Classification System</taxonkey>
</keywtax>
<taxonsys>
<classsys>
<classcit>
<citeinfo>
<origin>
United States Department of the Interior National
Biological Survey and National Park Service
</origin>
<pubdate>19941101</pubdate>
<title>
Standardized National Vegetation Classification
System
</title>
<edition>Version 1</edition>
<geoform>Classification System</geoform>
<serinfo>
<sername>NBS/NPS Vegetation Mapping Program</sername>
<issue>Final Draft</issue>
</serinfo>
<pubinfo>
<pubplace>Redlands, California</pubplace>
<publish>ESRI</publish>
</pubinfo>
<othercit>Prepared by the Nature Conservancy</othercit>
</citeinfo>
</classcit>
</classsys>
<idref>
<citeinfo>
<origin>
United States Department of the Interior National
Biological Survey and National Park Service
</origin>
<pubdate>19941101</pubdate>
<title>
Standardized National Vegetation Classification
System
</title>
<edition>Version 1</edition>
<geoform>Classification System</geoform>
<serinfo>
<sername>NBS/NPS Vegetation Mapping Program</sername>
<issue>Final Draft</issue>
</serinfo>
<pubinfo>
<pubplace>Redlands, California</pubplace>
<publish>ESRI</publish>
</pubinfo>
<othercit>Prepared by the Nature Conservancy</othercit>
</citeinfo>
</idref>
<taxonpro>
See "Photo Interpretation Report, BRD/NPS Vegetation and Inventory and Mapping Program,
Rock Creek Park," October 1, 1998 &lt;http://biology.usgs.gov/npsveg/rocr/pi_rpt.pdf&gt;
</taxonpro>
<taxoncom>Complete</taxoncom>
</taxonsys>
<taxongen>
Vegetation Alliances of the National Vegetation
Classification System (October 1995)
</taxongen>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Kingdom</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Plantae</taxonrv>
</taxoncl>
</taxonomy>
<accconst>None</accconst>
<useconst>
Any person using the information presented here
should fully understand the data collection and
compilation procedures, as described in these
metadata, before beginning analysis.  The burden
for determining fitness for use lies entirely with
the user.  For purposes of publication or
dissemination, citations should be given to the
U.S. Geological Survey and the National Park
Service
</useconst>
<ptcontac>
<cntinfo>
<cntorgp>
<cntper>USGS-NPS Vegetation Mapping Program Coordinator</cntper>
<cntorg>
USGS Biological Resources Division, Center for Biological
Informatics
</cntorg>
</cntorgp>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>Physical Address</addrtype>
<address>USGS</address>
<address>Biological Resources Division, CBI</address>
<address>Building 810, Room 8000</address>
<city>Denver</city>
<state>Colorado</state>
<postal>80225-0046</postal>
<country>USA</country>
</cntaddr>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>Mailing Address</addrtype>
<address>USGS</address>
<address>Biological Resources Division, CBI</address>
<address>PO BOX 25046, DFC, MS302</address>
<city>Denver</city>
<state>Colorado</state>
<postal>80225-0046</postal>
<country>USA</country>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>(303) 202-4220</cntvoice>
<cntfax>303-202-4229</cntfax>
<cntfax>303-202-4219 (org)</cntfax>
<cntemail>gs-b-npsveg@usgs.gov</cntemail>
</cntinfo>
</ptcontac>
<browse>
<browsen>http://biology.usgs.gov/npsveg/rocr/images/rocrveg.jpg</browsen>
<browsed>121 Kbyte graphic in map composition layout</browsed>
<browset>JPG</browset>
</browse>
<secinfo>
<secsys>None</secsys>
<secclass>None</secclass>
<sechandl>None</sechandl>
</secinfo>
<native>UNIX-ARC/INFO</native>
</idinfo>
<dataqual>
<attracc>
<attraccr>
Code verification involved running each
coverage attribute file through a series of ARC/INFO
commands that checked for invalid codes.  These
commands produced listings that aided in
identifying abnormal codes.  The errors were
checked against the vegetation delineation
and attribute overlays.  Corrections were made to
the listings and input into the database.   ESRI
produced a plot of the converted spatial data and
sequence numbers (label I.D.s) for the manuscript.
The plot was checked by AIS for cartographic
quality of the arcs defining the polygon features
and the accuracy of the label I.D. assignments.
The plot was overlaid to the manuscript map to
verify that the scanned data was not distorted
beyond .02 map inches.  Other problems were noted
on the plots, such as overshoots and undershoots,
missing lines, premature convergence of polygon
boundary lines that intersected arcs at acute
angles, and incorrect sequence number assignments.
ESRI produced code verification plots of the
community association codes, height and density
codes, and land use code attributes.  The plots
were checked for coding errors that may have
occurred during the polygon attribute encoding
step.  The plots were overlaid on the manuscript
map with attached corresponding code attribute
overlay created in the manual rectification step.
Code changes were noted on the plot.  The edited
plots were delivered back to ESRI for correction
of the attribute files.   Processors conducted
interactive ARCEDIT sessions to make the necessary
corrections to the coverages.
</attraccr>
</attracc>
<logic>
All polygon features are checked for topology
using the ARC/INFO software.  Each polygon begins
and ends at the same point with the node feature.
All nodes are checked for error so that there are
no dangling features.  There are no duplicate
lines or polygons.  All nodes will snap together
and close polygons based on a specific tolerance.
If the node is not within the tolerance, it is
adjusted manually.  The test for logical
consistency are performed in ARC/INFO.
</logic>
<complete>
All data that can be photointerpreted is also
digitized.  This includes alliance/association
classes, surface water, and unvegetated/landuse.
</complete>
<posacc>
<horizpa>
<horizpar>
Unknown.  The positional accuracy of the base
digital ortho image is not known.  It is assumed
the map meets National Map Accuracy Standards.
</horizpar>
</horizpa>
<vertacc>
<vertaccr>
Unknown.  The positional accuracy of the base
digital ortho image is not known.  It is assumed
the map meets National Map Accuracy Standards.
</vertaccr>
</vertacc>
</posacc>
<lineage>
<method>
<methtype>Field</methtype>
<methodid>
<methkt>None</methkt>
<methkey>AIS</methkey>
</methodid>
<methdesc>
The normal process in vegetation mapping is to
conduct an initial field reconnaissance, map the
vegetation units through photointerpretation, then
conduct a field verification. The field reconnaissance
visit serves two major functions. First, the
photointerpreter keys the signature on the aerial
photos to the vegetation on the ground at each
signature site. Second, the photointerpreter becomes
familiar with the flora, vegetation communities and local
ecology that occur in the study area. Park and /or
TNC field biologists that are familiar with the local
vegetation and ecology of the park are present to help
the photointerpreter understand these elements and their
relationship with the geography of the park.
Upon completion of the field reconnaissance, photo
interpreters delineate vegetation units on mylar that overlay
the 9x9 aerial photos. This effort is conducted in
accordance with the TNC vegetation classification and
criteria for defining each community or alliance. The initial
mapping is then followed by a field verification session,
whose purpose is to verify that the vegetation units were
mapped correctly. Any PI related questions are also
addressed during the visit.
The vegetation mapping at Rock Creek Park in general
followed the normal mapping procedure as described above.
However, a TNC vegetation classification did not exist for
Rock Creek Park at the time the initial delineations commenced.
The TNC ecologist and AIS photo interpreters worked together
to develop a temporary signature key which addressed what
was known at the time. Unlike most parks, no existing plot
data was available to create an interim classification.
</methdesc>
<methcite>
<citeinfo>
<origin>Aerial Information Systems (AIS)</origin>
<pubdate>Unpublished Material</pubdate>
<pubtime>Unknown</pubtime>
<title>
Photo Interpretation Report USGS-NPS Vegetation
Mapping Program Rock Creek Park
</title>
<edition>Version 1</edition>
<geoform>Report</geoform>
<serinfo>
<sername>Unknown</sername>
<issue>Unknown</issue>
</serinfo>
<pubinfo>
<pubplace>Unknown</pubplace>
<publish>Ed Reyes</publish>
</pubinfo>
<othercit>Unknown</othercit>
</citeinfo>
</methcite>
<methodid>
<methkt>None</methkt>
<methkey>TNC</methkey>
</methodid>
</method>
<srcinfo>
<srccite>
<citeinfo>
<origin>Air Survey Corporation Sterling, Virginia</origin>
<pubdate>19961029</pubdate>
<pubtime>Unknown</pubtime>
<title>Rock Creek Park</title>
<edition>Version 1.0</edition>
<geoform>image</geoform>
<serinfo>
<sername>1.0</sername>
<issue>Unknown</issue>
</serinfo>
<pubinfo>
<pubplace>Sterling Virginia</pubplace>
<publish>Air Survey Corporation</publish>
</pubinfo>
<othercit>The aerial photography is CIR 1:6,000 scale.</othercit>
<onlink>http://biology.usgs.gov/npsveg/rocr/photos.html</onlink>
</citeinfo>
</srccite>
<srcscale>12000</srcscale>
<typesrc>CIR Aerial Photography</typesrc>
<srctime>
<timeinfo>
<sngdate>
<caldate>19961029</caldate>
<time>Unknown</time>
</sngdate>
</timeinfo>
<srccurr>publication date</srccurr>
</srctime>
<srccitea>ASC</srccitea>
<srccontr>None</srccontr>
</srcinfo>
<procstep>
<procdesc>See Methodology Description above.</procdesc>
<srcused>ASC</srcused>
<procdate>19981001</procdate>
</procstep>
<procstep>
<procdesc>
The following continues to describe the tasks performed and
methodologies used by Aerial Information Systems (AIS)
during the vegetation data compilation for Rock Creek Park.
DATA CONVERSION: Typically, the first step of the data
conversion process is the Manual rectification was conducted
by attaching a new mylar overlay to the base. The photo
signature delineation units were transferred to the overlay
through local registration of the photos with the attached
photo signature delineation overlay. Existing orthophotography
for Rock Creek Park was created from photos flown in leaf off
conditions. Although this allowed greater ease for viewing
features such as roads in forest canopies, it proved difficult to
register vegetation from leaf on photography to the early spring
leaf off orthophotography. A small area of the photo was
registered to the base at a time. By matching photo image to
orthophoto image, the delineations were transferred to the base
overlay. Because the parallax of the photo differs from that of
the orthophoto base, care was required in transfer. Inconsistent
stretching or shortening of the images was common from the photo
to the base. When one area was completed, the photo was shifted
to register to another small area. The process continued until the
manual rectification and transfer of polygons was complete. The
codes for PI signature type, height, density, and community type
were transferred from the corresponding photo overlays.
</procdesc>
<procdate>19980601</procdate>
</procstep>
<procstep>
<procdesc>
FIELD RECONNAISSANCE EFFORT: A three day
photointerpretation field reconnaissance effort was  conducted
in May 1997 (see section III) to tie the photo signatures delineated
on the aerial photographs with units evident on the ground.
The field crew consisted of Eden Crane and Sue Salmons (park
biologists), Virginia Crouch (Heritage biologist), Julie Lundgen (TNC
ecologist) and John Menke (AIS photointerpreter).
Prior to the field reconnaissance effort, several in-house preparations
were performed in order to facilitate a more organized trip. Each photo
was prepared with a separate field overlay. Locational features (roads,
buildings, etc) were drafted onto the overlays. Each photo was reviewed
and field transect sites were chosen representing different signatures
types, geographic variables (% slope, aspect, shape of the slope, elevation),
and other abiotic variables noted on the photography. These sites were
drafted onto the field overlays with notations to each site as needed.
Multiple sites were chosen to provide alternatives if one or more sites
proved inaccessible.
The field crew conducted on-site investigations over the three-day period.
During the field visit, the photointerpreter worked with the field biologists to
identify the plant species, preliminary vegetation communities, and their
associated photo signatures throughout the park. Field site numbers were
annotated directly onto the photo field overlay, thereby correlating the field
site to a specific location and photo signature. A field notebook was used to
record pertinent information (canopy dominance, understory species present,
abiotic features, disturbance history) for each site visited. Several ground
photos were taken at selected locations that were later tied back to the aerial
photographs and the field sites. Sites not previously identified on the photos
were also visited. These sites included areas between initially selected sites,
areas of noteworthy or unusual significance as determined by park personnel,
and areas the photointerpreter deemed important in transit from site to site.
</procdesc>
<procdate>19981001</procdate>
</procstep>
</lineage>
</dataqual>
<spdoinfo>
<indspref>
The ecology field sites were digitized to indicate
the area for which a TNC ecologist conducted an
ecological field sampling.
</indspref>
<direct>Point</direct>
<ptvctinf>
<sdtsterm>
<sdtstype>Point</sdtstype>
</sdtsterm>
</ptvctinf>
</spdoinfo>
<spref>
<horizsys>
<planar>
<gridsys>
<gridsysn>Universal Transverse Mercator</gridsysn>
<utm>
<utmzone>18</utmzone>
<transmer>
<longcm>-180</longcm>
<latprjo>-90</latprjo>
<feast>50000</feast>
<fnorth>0</fnorth>
<sfctrmer>0.9996</sfctrmer>
</transmer>
</utm>
</gridsys>
<planci>
<plance>coordinate pair</plance>
<coordrep>
<absres>1</absres>
<ordres>1</ordres>
</coordrep>
<plandu>Meters</plandu>
</planci>
</planar>
<geodetic>
<horizdn>North American Datum of 1983</horizdn>
<ellips>Geodedic Reference System 80</ellips>
<semiaxis>6378137</semiaxis>
<denflat>298.257</denflat>
</geodetic>
</horizsys>
<vertdef>
<altsys>
<altdatum>North American Vertical Datum of 1988</altdatum>
<altres>1</altres>
<altunits>Feet</altunits>
<altenc>Explicit elevation coordinate included with horizontal coordinates</altenc>
</altsys>
</vertdef>
</spref>
<eainfo>
<overview>
<eaover>
The system is organized hierarchically to support
conservation and resource stewardship applications
across multiple scales.  The upper levels of the
hierarchy are based on the physical form or
structure of the vegetation (physiognomy) and have
been refined from the international standards
developed by the United Nations Educational,
Scientific, and Cultural Organization (UNESCO).
The two most detailed levels of the hierarchy are
based on the species composition of the existing
vegetation (floristics) and reflect the
phyto-sociological standards that were originally
developed by European ecologists.  The vegetation
classification is continually advanced through the
collection and analysis of new field data and will
be greatly strengthened during the course of the
USGS-NPS mapping efforts.  National Park
Service/Biological Resources Division Vegetation
Inventory and Mapping Program for Rock Creek
Park, Washington DC, Final Community Association
Classification, March, 1998.  DATA DICTIONARY -
ROCK CREEK PARK  Data Format Outline:  Variable
Coverage related variables: Area818F Perimeter818F
Veg#45B Veg-id45B Defined variables: Seqno33I
Mod44C PI 22I Height11I Density11I TNC 33C
Landuse44C Pattern11I  Data Dictionary:  MOD
(Defines the modules corresponding to the DOQQ
file name. 6 total - roughly corresponding to the
six individual plots)  WE4 WW1 WW2 WW3 WW3E WW4
Defines Photointerpretation Signature Type (PI)
Non Forest Types:  01=Code not Used 02=Managed
grass/lawns 03=Meadow grasslands  (native
component) 04=Shrub areas  (forest edges)
05=Canopy openings  (shrubs, vines, some trees)
06=Water 99=Urban/disturbed  (see detailed Urban
codes in Land Use field)  Forest Types:
10=Floodplain areas 11=Ash swamps 12=Oak/beech
13=Mesic oak 14=Dry mesic oak 15=Tulip/oak
16=Tulip 17=Pine/oak 18=Tulip/oak/beech 19=Tulip
floodplain 20=Exotic/planted trees with managed
grass/lawn  Defines Height (HEIGHT)  1=&lt; 0.5
meters 2=0.5-2 meters 3=2-5 meters 4=5-15 meters
5=15-35 meters 6=35-50 meters 7=&gt; 50 meters 9=Not
Applicable  Defines Density (DENSITY)
1=Closed/Continuous&gt;60% 2=Discontinuous40%-60%
3=Dispersed25%-40% 4=Sparse10%-25% 5=Rare2%-10%
9=Not Applicable  Defines Mapping Classification
Communities and Variants (TNC) 01=Forest canopy
gap 02=Loblolly pine - mixed oak forest Pinus
taeda - Quercus (alba, falcata, stellata) Forest
[Provisional] 03=Virginia pine - oak forest Pinus
virginiana - Quercus (alba, stellata, falcata,
velutina) Forest Association 04=Sycamore - green
ash forest (floodplain forest) Platanus
occidentalis - Fraxinus pennsylvanica Forest
05=Tulip poplar forest Liriodendron tulipifera
Forest [Provisional] 06=Chestnut oak forest
Quercus (prinus, velutina) / Gaylussacia baccata
Forest 07=code not used 08=MIXED OAK/BEECH VARIANT
of Beech - white oak / mayapple forest Fagus
grandifolia - Quercus alba / Podophyllum peltatum
Forest 09=code not used 10=Beech - white oak /
mayapple forest (CLASSIC TYPE) Fagus grandifolia -
Quercus alba / Podophyllum peltatum Forest
10B=Beech - white oak / mayapple forest (CLASSIC
TYPE) beech/tulip component Fagus grandifolia -
Quercus alba / Podophyllum peltatum Forest
11=Shrub areas 12=Managed grass/lawns 13=Meadow
grasslands 14=Managed grass/lawns with trees
98=Water  Defines Land Use (LANDUSE)  1000=Urban
1900=Residential 1910=Commercial and Services
1911=Nature center and planetarium 1912=Horse
center; maintenance yard 1913=Park headquarters
1914=Park police 1915=Amphitheater 1916=Mixed park
facilities 1917=Center for Urban Ecology 1918=Fort
Stevens 1919=Fort Reno Park 1920=Industrial
1930=Transportation, Communications, and Utilities
1931=Road 1932=Parking Area 1940=Industrial and
Commercial Complexes 1950=Mixed Urban or Built-up
Land 1960=Other Urban or Built-up Land
1961=Community gardens 1962=Golf course 1963=Ball
fields 1964=Tennis stadium and/or courts
1965=Tennis courts and gardens 1966=Swim center
1967=Area Under Construction 1968=Cemetery
2000=Agriculture 3000=Natural Vegetation
8000=Water  Defines Pattern (PATTERN) 1 = Evenly
Dispersed 2 = Clumped / Bunched 3 = Gradational /
Transitional 4 = Alternating 9 = Not Applicable
FILE SPECIFICATIONS: Coordinate system: NAD83 -
Maryland State Plane (zone 4126)
</eaover>
<eadetcit>
Grossman, D. Et al. 1994.  National Park Service
Vegetation Mapping Project, Standardized National
Vegetation Classification System 209 pp.
</eadetcit>
</overview>
</eainfo>
<distinfo>
<distrib>
<cntinfo>
<cntperp>
<cntper>USGS-NPS Vegetation Mapping Program Coordinator</cntper>
<cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, Center for Biological Informatics</cntorg>
</cntperp>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
<address>
U.S. Geological Survey, Center for Biological
Informatics, MS 302, Room 8000, Building 810,
Denver Federal Center
</address>
<city>Denver</city>
<state>Colorado</state>
<postal>80225</postal>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>(303) 202-4220</cntvoice>
<cntfax>303-202-4229</cntfax>
<cntfax>303-202-4219 (org)</cntfax>
<cntemail>gs-b-npsveg@usgs.gov</cntemail>
</cntinfo>
</distrib>
<resdesc>ROCR Veg Map</resdesc>
<distliab>
Although these data have been processed
successfully on a computer system at the U.S.
Geological Survey, no warranty expressed or
implied is made regarding the accuracy or utility
of the data on any other system or for general or
scientific purposes, nor shall the act of
distribution constitute any such warranty.  This
disclaimer applies both to individual use of the
data and aggregate use with other data.  It is
strongly recommended that these data are directly
acquired from a U.S. Geological Survey server, and
not indirectly through other sources which may
have changed the data in some way.  It is also
strongly recommended that careful attention be
paid to the contents of the metadata file
associated with these data.  The U.S. Geological
Survey shall not be held liable for improper or
incorrect use of the data described and/or
contained herein.
</distliab>
<stdorder>
<digform>
<digtinfo>
<formname>JPG</formname>
</digtinfo>
<digtopt>
<onlinopt>
<computer>
<networka>
<networkr>http://biology.usgs.gov/npsveg/rocr/images/rocrveg.jpg</networkr>
</networka>
</computer>
</onlinopt>
</digtopt>
</digform>
<fees>None</fees>
</stdorder>
<stdorder>
<digform>
<digtinfo>
<formname>EXE</formname>
</digtinfo>
<digtopt>
<onlinopt>
<computer>
<networka>
<networkr>http://biology.usgs.gov/npsveg/ftp/vegmapping/rocr/rocr.exe</networkr>
</networka>
</computer>
</onlinopt>
</digtopt>
</digform>
<fees>None</fees>
</stdorder>
<stdorder>
<digform>
<digtinfo>
<formname>SDTS</formname>
</digtinfo>
<digtopt>
<onlinopt>
<computer>
<networka>
<networkr>http://biology.usgs.gov/npsveg/ftp/vegmapping/rocr/rocrsdts.exe</networkr>
</networka>
</computer>
</onlinopt>
</digtopt>
</digform>
<fees>None</fees>
</stdorder>
<stdorder>
<digform>
<digtinfo>
<formname>EXE</formname>
</digtinfo>
<digtopt>
<onlinopt>
<computer>
<networka>
<networkr>http://biology.usgs.gov/npsveg/ftp/vegmapping/rocr/rocrbdy.exe</networkr>
</networka>
</computer>
</onlinopt>
</digtopt>
</digform>
<fees>None</fees>
</stdorder>
<stdorder>
<digform>
<digtinfo>
<formname>SDTS</formname>
</digtinfo>
<digtopt>
<onlinopt>
<computer>
<networka>
<networkr>http://biology.usgs.gov/npsveg/ftp/vegmapping/rocr/rocrbdysdts.exe</networkr>
</networka>
</computer>
</onlinopt>
</digtopt>
</digform>
<fees>None</fees>
</stdorder>
</distinfo>
<metainfo>
<metd>200102</metd>
<metrd>20050517</metrd>
<metc>
<cntinfo>
<cntorgp>
<cntorg>USGS-NPS Vegetation Mapping Program Coordinator</cntorg>
</cntorgp>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
<address>
U.S. Geological Survey, Center for Biological Informatics, MS 302,
Room 8000, Building 810, Denver Federal Center
</address>
<city>Denver</city>
<state>Colorado</state>
<postal>80225</postal>
<country>USA</country>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>(303) 202-4220</cntvoice>
<cntfax>(303) 202-4219</cntfax>
<cntemail>gs-b-npsveg@usgs.gov</cntemail>
</cntinfo>
</metc>
<metstdn>FGDC-STD-001.1-1999 Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata, 1998 Part 1: Biological Data Profile, 1999</metstdn>
<metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
<metextns>
<onlink>http://biology.usgs.gov/fgdc.bio/bionwext.txt</onlink>
<metprof>Biological Data Profile FGDC-STD-001.1-1999</metprof>
</metextns>
</metainfo>
<mercury><begdate>19961029</begdate><enddate>19961029</enddate><htmlurl>http://mercury.ornl.gov/metadata/nbii/html/nbii/www.nbii.gov_metadata_mdata_CBI_usgs_brd_cbi_d_rocrveg.html</htmlurl><LTER-Site>nbii</LTER-Site></mercury></metadata>
