<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<metadata><Source>http://www.nbii.gov/metadata/mdata/brd-bib/usgs_brd_fresc_b_ospreychick.sgml</Source>
<idinfo>
<citation>
<citeinfo>
<origin>Elliott, John E., Laurie K. Wilson, Charles J. Henny, Suzanne F. Trudeau, Kimberly M. Cheng</origin>
<pubdate>2001</pubdate>
<title>Assessment of biological effects of chlorinated hydrocarbons in osprey chicks</title>
<geoform>Journal article</geoform>
<serinfo>
<sername>Environmental Toxicology and Chemistry</sername>
<issue>20(4): 866-879</issue>
</serinfo>
<othercit>
Science Information System Project #:5001368
Publication Control #:900
</othercit>
</citeinfo>
</citation>
<descript>
<abstract>Ospreys (Pandion haliaetus) were first studied throughout Oregon in 1976 and have become a common nesting species along the lower Columbia and Willamette Rivers. A wide range of toxic chemicals is found in the water and sediments and aquatic biota along these rivers, causing concern for many wildlife species associated with the river. Residues of some organochlorine insecticides (OCs), polychlorinated biphenyls (PCBs), dioxins and furans are potentially toxic to fish, wildlife and humans. These toxic chemicals accumulate in an organism over time through bioaccumulation. OC molecules become more concentrated in organisms at higher trophic levels of the food web through biomagnification. The species of most concern are either fish or fish-eating wildlife species at the top of the food web. Ospreys have many life history traits making it useful for environmental contaminant reseach: 1) eating and capturing fish within a relatively short distance from their nest sites, 2) long-lived with high nest site fidelity, 3) nests easily detected during surveys, 4) often nests on man-made structures, facilitating nest access, 5) tolerates short-term nest site disturbance, 6) removal of sample egg has minimal effect on local population, and 7) species reproduction adversely impacted by DDE-induced eggshell thinning and effects of chlorinated hydrocarbon and mercury pollutants. An Osprey egg provides a snapshot of the toxic contaminants present in the adult female&amp;#146;s body at the time the egg was formed. Therefore, we initiated studies along the Willamette and the Columbia River to evaluate contaminants in Osprey eggs and prey and to determine if Osprey could be used as an indicator or sentinel species for long-term monitoring of contaminant loading and the general health of the rivers.</abstract>
<purpose>Reporting research results</purpose>
<supplinf>
Extent of item: 13pp
Illustrative Matter:  tables, maps, graphs
</supplinf>
</descript>
<timeperd>
<timeinfo>
<sngdate>
<caldate>2001</caldate>
</sngdate>
</timeinfo>
<current>publication date</current>
</timeperd>
<status>
<progress>Complete</progress>
<update>None planned</update>
</status>
<spdom>
<descgeog>Willamette River in Oregon and lower Columbia River in Oregon and Washington</descgeog>
<bounding>
<westbc>-125</westbc>
<eastbc>-120</eastbc>
<northbc>47</northbc>
<southbc>45</southbc>
</bounding>
</spdom>
<keywords>
<theme>
<themekt>none</themekt>
<themekey>Dioxin</themekey>
<themekey>toxic equivalents</themekey>
<themekey>CYPIA</themekey>
<themekey>Vitamin A</themekey>
</theme>
<theme>
<themekt>Science Information System Controlled Vocabulary</themekt>
<themekey>Analytical Chemistry</themekey>
<themekey>Birds</themekey>
<themekey>Human Impacts</themekey>
<themekey>Toxicology</themekey>
</theme>
<place>
<placekt>none</placekt>
<placekey>Oregon</placekey>
<placekey>Washington</placekey>
<placekey>OR</placekey>
<placekey>WA</placekey>
<placekey>Willamette River</placekey>
<placekey>Columbia River</placekey>
</place>
</keywords>
<taxonomy>
<keywtax>
<taxonkt>none</taxonkt>
<taxonkey>osprey</taxonkey>
<taxonkey>birds</taxonkey>
</keywtax>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Kingdom</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Animalia</taxonrv>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Phylum</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Chordata</taxonrv>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Subphylum</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Vertebrata</taxonrv>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Class</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Aves</taxonrv>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Order</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Falconiformes</taxonrv>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Family</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Accipitridae</taxonrv>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Genus</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Pandion</taxonrv>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Species</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Pandion haliaetus</taxonrv>
<common>osprey</common>
</taxoncl>
</taxoncl>
</taxoncl>
</taxoncl>
</taxoncl>
</taxoncl>
</taxoncl>
</taxoncl>
</taxonomy>
<accconst>None</accconst>
<useconst>None</useconst>
<ptcontac>
<cntinfo>
<cntperp>
<cntper>Henny, Charles</cntper>
<cntorg>USGS Forest and Rangeland Ecosystem Science Center</cntorg>
</cntperp>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
<address>3200  SW Jefferson Way</address>
<city>Corvallis</city>
<state>OR</state>
<postal>97331</postal>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>541/757/4840</cntvoice>
<cntemail>charles_j_henny@usgs.gov</cntemail>
</cntinfo>
</ptcontac>
</idinfo>
<distinfo>
<distrib>
<cntinfo>
<cntorgp>
<cntorg>Olendorff Library</cntorg>
</cntorgp>
<cntpos>Librarian</cntpos>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
<address>
USGS FRESC Snake River Field Station
970 Lusk Street
</address>
<city>Boise</city>
<state>ID</state>
<postal>83706</postal>
<country>USA</country>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>208 426-5218</cntvoice>
<cntfax>208 426-5210</cntfax>
</cntinfo>
</distrib>
<resdesc>Publication Control #:900</resdesc>
<distliab>
The USGS Forest and Rangeland Ecosystem Science Center and its research partners make every effort to provide and maintain accurate, complete, usable, and timely information. However, some USGS data and information may, of necessity, be preliminary in nature. These data and information are provided with the understanding that they are not guaranteed to be correct or complete. Users are cautioned to consider carefully the provisional nature of these data and information before using them for decisions that concern personal or public safety or the conduct of business that involves substantial monetary or operational consequences. It is also strongly recommended that careful attention be paid to the contents of the metadata file associated with these data and information. Conclusions drawn from, or actions undertaken on the basis of, such data and information are the sole responsibility of the user.
USGS-authored or produced data and information are in the public domain. Whereas the content of many USGS publications and other information resources are in the public domain, some USGS products contain material that is copyrighted by others and used by the USGS with permission. Users of this information may need to obtain permission from the copyright owner for other uses. Furthermore, some non-USGS data, products, and information referred to may be protected under U.S. and foreign copyright laws. Users may need to obtain permission from the copyright owner to acquire, use, reproduce, or distribute these materials. It is the sole responsibility of the user of the information to secure all necessary permission.
</distliab>
<stdorder>
<nondig>Publications are available as reprints, reports, pamphlets, or brochures.</nondig>
<fees>None</fees>
<ordering>Request specific publications by reference number.</ordering>
</stdorder>
</distinfo>
<metainfo>
<metd>20010615</metd>
<metc>
<cntinfo>
<cntorgp>
<cntorg>USGS Forest and Rangeland Ecosystem Science Center (FRESC)</cntorg>
</cntorgp>
<cntpos>Library</cntpos>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
<address>
777 NW 9th St.
Suite 100
</address>
<city>Corvallis</city>
<state>OR</state>
<postal>97330</postal>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>541-750-1030</cntvoice>
<cntfax>541-750-1069</cntfax>
<cntemail>fresc_outreach@usgs.gov</cntemail>
</cntinfo>
</metc>
<metstdn>FGDC Biological Data Profile of the Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
<metstdv>FGDC-STD-001.1-1999</metstdv>
</metainfo>
<mercury><begdate>20010101</begdate><enddate>20011231</enddate><htmlurl>http://mercury.ornl.gov/metadata/nbii/html/brd/www.nbii.gov_metadata_mdata_brd-bib_usgs_brd_fresc_b_ospreychick.html</htmlurl><LTER-Site>brd</LTER-Site></mercury></metadata>
