<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<metadata><Source>http://www.nbii.gov/metadata/mdata/frames/nbii_frames_d_CombMesitaBlanca.sgml</Source>
<idinfo>
<citation>
<citeinfo>
<origin>D. Lewis (collector and crossdater)</origin>
<origin>H.D. Grissino-Mayer (collector and crossdater)</origin>
<origin>E. Atchley (collector)</origin>
<origin>M. Armbrister (collector)</origin>
<pubdate>1991, 200106</pubdate>
<title>Combined Mesita Blanca Fire History _fhx (combined with Grissino-Mayer 1995)</title>
<geoform>maps data</geoform>
<othercit>file name: newmb.fhx</othercit>
<onlink>http://web.utk.edu/~grissino/jfsp013329/data.html</onlink>
<onlink>http://web.utk.edu/~grissino/jfsp013329/newmb.fhx</onlink>
<lworkcit>
<citeinfo>
<origin>Daniel B. Lewis</origin>
<pubdate>2003</pubdate>
<title>Fire regimes of kipuka forests in El Malpais National Monument, New Mexico, USA</title>
<pubinfo>
<pubplace>Knoxville, TN</pubplace>
<publish>The University of Tennessee</publish>
</pubinfo>
<othercit>
This dataset is part of the project with FRAMES resource id {E4211B5D-4B1D-4EEA-8262-BD97E5FE8E95} and part of the thesis cited below:
Daniel B. Lewis, 2003. Fire regimes of kipuka forests in El Malpais National Monument, New Mexico, USA. M.S. thesis, The University of Tennessee, Knoxville. 145 pp.  -- {8797FC16-90F4-4BFB-AC2B-2D49317316D6}
</othercit>
<onlink>http://web.utk.edu/~grissino/jfsp013329/thesis.html</onlink>
</citeinfo>
</lworkcit>
</citeinfo>
</citation>
<descript>
<abstract>
Combined Mesita Blanca Fire History dataset (combined with Grissino-Mayer 1995) as part of the thesis -- Daniel B. Lewis, 2003. Fire regimes of kipuka forests in El Malpais National Monument, New Mexico, USA. M.S. thesis, The University of Tennessee, Knoxville. 145 pp.
Currently, ecosystem processes that maintain the forests of the American Southwest are operating outside the historical range of variation that existed prior to Euro-American settlement. Areas that have been minimally disturbed by humans should be targeted for research because they contain valuable information about past ecological processes. In El Malpais National Monument, islands of older substrate material are surrounded by younger lava flows. These areas, known as kipukas, likely preserve presettlement forest structure and contain trees old enough to provide information on past ecological processes.
</abstract>
<purpose>The purpose of this study is to reconstruct fire history on minimally disturbed kipukas in El Malpais National Monument, New Mexico. Eight sites were sampled and 105 fire-scarred samples were collected. Increment cores were taken from living ponderosa pine (Pinus ponderosa Dougl. ex. Laws) trees on two kipukas to examine the age structure of the kipuka forests and to determine whether fire suppression away from the kipukas may be allowing ponderosa pines to encroach onto areas not in their local distribution in the monument.</purpose>
<supplinf>
Mesita Blanca is the largest of the kipukas sampled for this study. It is ca. 1.7 km long and ca. 460 m wide at its widest point. It has a northwest/southeast orientation, and the elevation of the upper crest is above 2275 m asl (above sea level). This kipuka is one of the sedimentary kipukas, comprised primarily of San Andres Limestone (Lower Permian) (Maxwell 1986). Access to Mesita Blanca is via a narrow road over the Hoya de Cibola Flow. Open ponderosa pine forests are found on the adjacent lava flows encircling the kipuka. The upper crest is covered by denser pion-juniper woodland, with a number of ponderosa pines mixed in. The lower slopes are covered by grasses, some shrubs, and a few even-aged ponderosa pines. Gambel oak (Quercus gambellii Nutt.) grows in dense clusters on the eastern slope of the kipuka. Ground fuels at present appear adequate to support the spread of wildfire on the kipuka.
Some human-related disturbance is also indicated by the reconstruction of fire history on the kipuka (Grissino-Mayer 1995). Although the kipuka actively recorded fire well into the 20th century, fire began a noticeable decline in frequency ca. 1940.
Although livestock grazing may have minimally altered the kipuka, no evidence of logging was visible anywhere on Mesita Blanca. It is also believed that fires have not been actively suppressed on this kipuka. Visual signs of wildfire, such as charred bark and fire-scarred trees, were evident most everywhere. The largest percentage of firescarred trees were located along the outer periphery of the kipuka, closest to the surrounding lava flow.
Taken from section 3.4.1 of Daniel B. Lewis, 2003. Fire regimes of kipuka forests in El Malpais National Monument, New Mexico, USA. M.S. thesis, The University of Tennessee, Knoxville. 145 pp.
(previous geoform was 'maps or data')</supplinf>
</descript>
<timeperd>
<timeinfo>
<mdattim>
<sngdate>
<caldate>1991</caldate>
</sngdate>
<sngdate>
<caldate>200106</caldate>
</sngdate>
</mdattim>
</timeinfo>
<current>as indicated by dataset</current>
</timeperd>
<status>
<progress>Complete</progress>
<update>Unknown</update>
</status>
<spdom>
<bounding>
<westbc>-108.07</westbc>
<eastbc>-107.80</eastbc>
<northbc>34.88</northbc>
<southbc>34.68</southbc>
</bounding>
</spdom>
<keywords>
<theme>
<themekt>FRAMES Resource ID</themekt>
<themekey>{A9036E32-6008-4979-BEB4-212C04BC4DCA}</themekey>
</theme>
<theme>
<themekt>GACC Regions</themekt>
<themekey>Southwest</themekey>
</theme>
<theme>
<themekt>FRAMES Subject Categories</themekt>
<themekey>fire history</themekey>
</theme>
<theme>
<themekt>none</themekt>
<themekey>pinus ponderosa</themekey>
<themekey>kipuka</themekey>
<themekey>Gambel Oak</themekey>
<themekey>pinon-juniper</themekey>
</theme>
</keywords>
<accconst>none</accconst>
<useconst>Please provide the appropriate citation/credit to the originator(s) or individual/organization(s) that should receive recognition for their contribution to the data set.</useconst>
<ptcontac>
<cntinfo>
<cntperp>
<cntper>Henri D. Grissino-Mayer</cntper>
<cntorg>Department of Geography, The University of Tennessee</cntorg>
</cntperp>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>physical address</addrtype>
<address>Department of Geography, The University of Tennessee</address>
<city>Knoxville</city>
<state>Tennessee</state>
<postal>37996</postal>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>865.974.6029</cntvoice>
<cntfax>865.974.6025</cntfax>
<cntemail>grissino@utk.edu</cntemail>
</cntinfo>
</ptcontac>
<native>Microsoft Windows XP Version 5.1 (Build 2600) Service Pack 2; ESRI ArcCatalog 9.1.0.780</native>
<crossref>
<citeinfo>
<origin>Henri D. Grissino-Mayer, Department of Geography, The University of Tennessee, Knoxville, TN</origin>
<origin>Herschel Schulz, El Malpais National Monument, Grants, NM</origin>
<pubdate>2001</pubdate>
<title>Assessing Anthropogenic Changes in Fire Regimes Using Relict Areas in El Malpais National Monument, New Mexico -- JFSP 01-3-3-29 {E4211B5D-4B1D-4EEA-8262-BD97E5FE8E95}</title>
<othercit>This dataset is part of the project with FRAMES resource id {E4211B5D-4B1D-4EEA-8262-BD97E5FE8E95}.</othercit>
<onlink>http://web.utk.edu/~grissino/jfsp013329/proposal.html</onlink>
</citeinfo>
</crossref>
<crossref>
<citeinfo>
<origin>Daniel B. Lewis</origin>
<pubdate>2003</pubdate>
<title>Fire regimes of kipuka forests in El Malpais National Monument, New Mexico, USA -- {8797FC16-90F4-4BFB-AC2B-2D49317316D6}</title>
<othercit>
This dataset is part of the thesis cited below:
Daniel B. Lewis, 2003. Fire regimes of kipuka forests in El Malpais National Monument, New Mexico, USA. M.S. thesis, The University of Tennessee, Knoxville. 145 pp.  -- {8797FC16-90F4-4BFB-AC2B-2D49317316D6}
</othercit>
<onlink>http://web.utk.edu/~grissino/jfsp013329/thesis.html</onlink>
</citeinfo>
</crossref>
</idinfo>
<dataqual>
<attracc>
<attraccr>none</attraccr>
</attracc>
<logic>Unknown</logic>
<complete>unknown</complete>
<lineage>
<procstep>
<procdesc>UNKNOWN</procdesc>
<procdate>UNKNOWN</procdate>
</procstep>
</lineage>
</dataqual>
<spref>
<horizsys>
<geograph>
<latres>34.88</latres>
<longres>108.07</longres>
<geogunit>Decimal degrees</geogunit>
</geograph>
</horizsys>
</spref>
<eainfo>
<overview>
<eaover>More about FHX2 format (standard format for fire history data) can be found at the International Multiproxy Paleofire Database (IMPD) as described under Tree-Ring Fire Event Data Description available at http://www.ncdc.noaa.gov/paleo/impd/tree_event_info.html.</eaover>
<eadetcit>UNKNOWN</eadetcit>
</overview>
</eainfo>
<distinfo>
<distrib>
<cntinfo>
<cntperp>
<cntper>Henri D. Grissino-Mayer</cntper>
<cntorg>Dept. of Geograhy, The University of Tennessee</cntorg>
</cntperp>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>physical address</addrtype>
<address>Dept. of Geography, The University of Tennessee</address>
<city>Knoxville</city>
<state>Tennessee</state>
<postal>37996</postal>
<country>USA</country>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>865.974.6029</cntvoice>
<cntfax>865.974.6025</cntfax>
<cntemail>grissino@utk.edu</cntemail>
</cntinfo>
</distrib>
<resdesc>Downloadable Data</resdesc>
<distliab>UNKNOWN</distliab>
<custom>Data available in FHX2 format at http://web.utk.edu/~grissino/jfsp013329/data.html</custom>
</distinfo>
<metainfo>
<metd>20061002</metd>
<metc>
<cntinfo>
<cntperp>
<cntper>Christopher C. Szell</cntper>
<cntorg>National Biological Inventory Infrastructure (NBII) Fire Research and Management Exchange System (FRAMES) The Nature Conservancy (TNC)</cntorg>
</cntperp>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
<address>6114 Fayetteville Rd.</address>
<address>suite 109</address>
<city>Durham</city>
<state>NC</state>
<postal>27713</postal>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>919.484.7857</cntvoice>
<cntemail>cszell@tnc.org</cntemail>
</cntinfo>
</metc>
<metstdn>FGDC Content Standards for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
<metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
<mettc>local time</mettc>
</metainfo>
<mercury><begdate>19910101</begdate><enddate>20010631</enddate><htmlurl>http://mercury.ornl.gov/metadata/nbii/html/frames/www.nbii.gov_metadata_mdata_frames_nbii_frames_d_CombMesitaBlanca.html</htmlurl><LTER-Site>frames</LTER-Site></mercury></metadata>
