<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<metadata><Source>http://www.nbii.gov/metadata/mdata/brd-bib/usgs_brd_npwrc_b_bulrushlit.sgml</Source>
<idinfo>
<citation>
<citeinfo>
<origin>Harold A. Kantrud</origin>
<pubdate>1996</pubdate>
<title>The Alkali (Scirpus maritimus L.) and Saltmarsh (S. robustus Pursh) Bulrushes: A Literature Review</title>
<edition>Version 16JUL97</edition>
<geoform>bibliography</geoform>
<pubinfo>
<pubplace>Jamestown, North Dakota</pubplace>
<publish>National Biological Service (now known as the U.S. Geological Survey, Biological Resources Division, Northern Prairie Wildlife Research Center)</publish>
</pubinfo>
<othercit>Northern Prairie Wildlife Research Center Home Page</othercit>
<onlink>http://www.npwrc.usgs.gov/resource/literatr/bulrush/bulrush.htm</onlink>
</citeinfo>
</citation>
<descript>
<abstract>Alkali (Scirpus maritimus L.) and saltmarsh (S. robustus Pursh) bulrushes are closely related, emergent hydrophytes that are important as foods of waterfowl and other wildlife. Water depth, water level fluctuations, exposure, sediment and water salinity, and shading by taller emergents strongly affect growth and reproduction. Important management problems are inconsistent achene germination, difficulties with maintenance and timing of water level and salinity cycles, and acidification of sediments. Other serious problems are competition from other hydrophytes and the largely unpredictable effects of grazing, burning, tilling, and other land use practices. Recent management efforts have focused on thinning stands of the two bulrushes or intermixing them with stands of shorter emergents and submersed plants in order to increase the variety of food plants available to waterfowl and other birds. Information needed for more effective management includes the optimum size and vegetation interspersion of treated areas, treatment response, and the combined effects of natural disturbances such as grazing and burning. Control of a few salt-tolerant plants requires closure of some impoundments to the open sea for long periods. Such closures are of concern to fisheries managers, especially in areas where coastal marshes are disappearing. Conversely, in other managed wetlands, freshwater diverted from rivers pushes estuarine water seaward, making it difficult to obtain waters of sufficient salinity to control undesirable freshwater plants. Research and conservation thus need to be combined in many areas to improve management of these bulrushes.</abstract>
<purpose>Despite their importance to wildlife, the author found no published life histories of Scirpus maritimus and S. robustus.</purpose>
</descript>
<timeperd>
<timeinfo>
<sngdate>
<caldate>199609</caldate>
</sngdate>
</timeinfo>
<current>publication date</current>
</timeperd>
<status>
<progress>Complete</progress>
<update>None planned</update>
</status>
<spdom>
<descgeog>Scirpus maritimus L. and S. robustus Pursh belong to a small, worldwide group of the family Cyperaceae, in North America often called the "tuberous bulrushes".</descgeog>
<bounding>
<westbc>-170</westbc>
<eastbc>-50</eastbc>
<northbc>80</northbc>
<southbc>10</southbc>
</bounding>
</spdom>
<keywords>
<theme>
<themekt>none</themekt>
<themekey>emergent hydrophytes</themekey>
<themekey>autoecology</themekey>
<themekey>management</themekey>
<themekey>sedges</themekey>
<themekey>taxonomy</themekey>
<themekey>wetlands</themekey>
<themekey>wildlife</themekey>
<themekey>bulrush</themekey>
</theme>
<place>
<placekt>none</placekt>
<placekey>North America</placekey>
</place>
</keywords>
<taxonomy>
<keywtax>
<taxonkt>none</taxonkt>
<taxonkey>Scirpus robustus</taxonkey>
<taxonkey>Scirpus maritimus</taxonkey>
</keywtax>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Kingdom</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Plantae</taxonrv>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Subkingdom</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Tracheobionta</taxonrv>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Division</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Magnoliophyta</taxonrv>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Class</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Liliopsida</taxonrv>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Subclass</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Commelinidae</taxonrv>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Order</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Cyperales</taxonrv>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Family</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Cyperaceae</taxonrv>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Genus</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Schoenoplectus</taxonrv>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Species</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Schoenoplectus maritimus</taxonrv>
<common>sturdy bulrush</common>
</taxoncl>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Species</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Schoenoplectus robustus</taxonrv>
<common>sturdy bulrush</common>
</taxoncl>
</taxoncl>
</taxoncl>
</taxoncl>
</taxoncl>
</taxoncl>
</taxoncl>
</taxoncl>
</taxoncl>
</taxonomy>
<accconst>none</accconst>
<useconst>none</useconst>
<ptcontac>
<cntinfo>
<cntperp>
<cntper>Harold Kantrud</cntper>
<cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, Biological Resources Division, Northern Prairie Wildlife Research Center</cntorg>
</cntperp>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
<address>8711 37 St. SE</address>
<city>Jamestown</city>
<state>North Dakota</state>
<postal>58401-7317</postal>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>(701)-253-5500</cntvoice>
<cntfax>(701)-253-5553</cntfax>
<cntemail>harold_kantrud@usgs.gov</cntemail>
<cntinst>Contact Northern Prairie Wildlife Research Center in order to leave a message for Harold Kantrud who retired in 1997.</cntinst>
</cntinfo>
</ptcontac>
<datacred>I thank E. J. Kantrud, who translated several French and German references, and D. L. Larson, G. E. Larson, J. T. Lokemoen, D. M. Mushet, and A. B. Sargeant, who reviewed the manuscript; M. C. Hager for editorial services; and S. Lauritzen for the layout.</datacred>
<crossref>
<citeinfo>
<origin>Harold A. Kantrud</origin>
<pubdate>1996</pubdate>
<title>The alkali (Scirpus maritimus L.) and saltmarsh (S. Robustus Pursh) bulrushes: A literature review.</title>
<geoform>Journal article</geoform>
<serinfo>
<sername>Information and Technology Report</sername>
<issue>6</issue>
</serinfo>
<pubinfo>
<pubplace>Jamestown, North Dakota</pubplace>
<publish>National Biological Service (now U.S. Geological Survey, Biological Resources Division, Northern Prairie Wildlife Research Center</publish>
</pubinfo>
<othercit>77 pages</othercit>
</citeinfo>
</crossref>
</idinfo>
<dataqual>
<logic>not applicable</logic>
<complete>The literature review is a synthesis of life histories and management assessment of alkali and saltmarsh bulrushes. The information is mostly from reports written in English, from reports with English summaries, and from some foreign material. The author did not reference the simple occurrence of either bulrush in various wetlands worldwide or early taxonomic and genetic studies.</complete>
<lineage>
<method>
<methtype>literature review</methtype>
<methodid>
<methkt>none</methkt>
<methkey>literature review</methkey>
</methodid>
<methdesc>The author created a literature review of the life histories and management assessment of Alkali and Saltmarsh Bulrushes by looking at reports written in English, at reports with English summaries and some foreign material.</methdesc>
</method>
<method>
<methtype>literature review</methtype>
<methodid>
<methkt>none</methkt>
<methkey>interviews with wetland managers</methkey>
</methodid>
<methdesc>The author interviewed many wetland managers in the United States who are familiar with Scirpus maritimus and S. robustus. The importance of the two bulrushes for wildlife was recognized by most managers, and they were confident of their ability to establish and maintain stands of these plants on the lands they manage. However, many of the management techniques currently in use involve costly trial-and-error methods. To help reduce the inefficiency of such methods, managers need information to account for the variability of their observed results.</methdesc>
</method>
<procstep>
<procdesc>The author focused on English documents, and articles with abstracts in English.</procdesc>
<procdate>unknown</procdate>
</procstep>
</lineage>
</dataqual>
<spdoinfo>
<indspref>Based on local reference names.</indspref>
</spdoinfo>
<eainfo>
<overview>
<eaover>Entity - Alkali and Saltmarsh Bulrushes; Associated attributes - life histories and management assessment</eaover>
<eadetcit>U.S. Geological Survey, Biological Resources Division, Northern Prairie Wildlife Research Center</eadetcit>
</overview>
</eainfo>
<distinfo>
<distrib>
<cntinfo>
<cntperp>
<cntper>Tom Sklebar</cntper>
<cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, Northern Prairie Wildlife Research Center</cntorg>
</cntperp>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
<address>8711 37th Street, S.E.</address>
<city>Jamestown</city>
<state>North Dakota</state>
<postal>58401</postal>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>701-253-5500, 701-253-5554</cntvoice>
<cntfax>701-253-5553</cntfax>
<cntemail>tom_sklebar@usgs.gov</cntemail>
</cntinfo>
</distrib>
<distliab>Although these data have been processed successfully on a computer system at the U.S. Geological Survey, no warranty expressed or implied is made regarding the accuracy or utility of the data on any other system or for general or scientific purposes, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty. This disclaimer applies both to individual use of the data and aggregate use with other data.  It is strongly recommended that these data are directly acquired from a U.S. Geological Survey server, and not indirectly through other sources which may have changed the data in some way.  It is also strongly recommended that careful attention be paid to the contents of the metadata file associated with these data.  The U.S. Geological Survey shall not be held liable for improper or incorrect use of the data described and/or contained herein.</distliab>
</distinfo>
<metainfo>
<metd>20020131</metd>
<metfrd>20030131</metfrd>
<metc>
<cntinfo>
<cntperp>
<cntper>Cheryl Solomon</cntper>
<cntorg>Science Systems and Applications, Inc.</cntorg>
</cntperp>
<cntpos>Metadata specialist</cntpos>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
<address>10210 Greenbelt Road, Suite 500</address>
<city>Lanham</city>
<state>Maryland</state>
<postal>20706</postal>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>301 867-2080</cntvoice>
<cntfax>301-867-2149.</cntfax>
<cntemail>solomon@gcmd.nasa.gov</cntemail>
</cntinfo>
</metc>
<metstdn>FGDC Biological Data Profile of the Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
<metstdv>FGDC-STD-001.1-1999</metstdv>
<metac>none</metac>
<metuc>none</metuc>
</metainfo>
<mercury><begdate>19960901</begdate><enddate>19960931</enddate><htmlurl>http://mercury.ornl.gov/metadata/nbii/html/brd/www.nbii.gov_metadata_mdata_brd-bib_usgs_brd_npwrc_b_bulrushlit.html</htmlurl><LTER-Site>brd</LTER-Site></mercury></metadata>
